<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter version="5.0" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
         xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
         xmlns:svg="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"
         xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
         xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
         xmlns:db="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
  <title>Prologue</title>

  <section>
    <title/>

    <para>The curator adjusted the head torch then began warming the short,
    thin-bladed knife over the spirit burner which was placed diagonally
    across the table from her. Satisfied that the sliver of steel was warm
    enough to do its job yet not so hot as to cause melting, she carefully
    worked it between the embossed disk of dark red wax and the paper beneath
    it. The seal had also been applied on top of a silk cord from which it
    took some careful working of the blade to remove but finally it came away
    intact to be laid aside with a frisson of relief that no damage had been
    done during its removal. Her mission was to reveal the contents of the
    artefact with a view to re-assembling the parts into the exact form in
    which the whole had been created over a century earlier. This was no easy
    task since the packet, which was about the size of modern paperback, had
    been thoroughly secured so as to evidence even the slightest attempt at
    tampering.</para>

    <para>A second seal was slowly and painstakingly removed, allowing the
    length of silk cord which had parcelled up the packet to be gently eased
    off. The cord, still dutifully trying to hold its shape, was placed to the
    left of the table. Soon all of the five seals that had been applied to the
    the enveloping sheet of paper were removed and set down beside the cord.
    The time had come to open the outer wrapper and take the first glimpse of
    what lay beneath.</para>

    <para>The packet had spent the day in a sealed box with the vapours of a
    seven parts alcohol to one part water mixture. This should have worked on
    the white glue, which owed its adhesive properties to the protein colloid
    processed from the bones of animals and fish, degrading it so as to allow
    the top triangle of fine wove paper to be lifted easily. It was not to be,
    however, and the edges of the flap needed delicate dabbing with a small
    sponge held by tweezers and dampened with some of the alcohol and water
    mix that had been warmed a little. Perhaps impatience got the better of
    the curator as she took up the slender knife once more for her first
    attempt at working the knife beneath the flap because the blade snagged,
    almost tearing the paper.</para>

    <para>The select group of museum friends dwho had been invited to attend
    this special event and who had been unconsciously leaning ever further
    forward as the curator did her work now drew in their breath as one. Each
    now became suddenly self-conscious, their rapt attention broken, and they
    began exchanging meaningful looks. For all that they tried to keean aura
    of a discrete distance and a reverend hush, their presence had now
    intruded and broken the curator's concentration. She leant back in her
    chair, removed the irksome head torch and massaged her forehead.
    Accustomed to the intense torchlight, the candlelit room now seemed dim.
    Perhaps this was just as well as it helped to maintain a professional
    distance from the audience.</para>

    <para>The meticulous preparations for tonight's event had begun some hours
    earlier. A blanket was spread over the polished wood of the dinning room
    table then covered with a clean, white, cotton cloth. A single,
    leather-covered, straight-backed chair was placed behind the table with
    its back to the huge dining room window. Everything that could conceivably
    be needed was arranged on the cloth so as to all be within easy reach from
    the chair. Next, the ornate double doors into the grand salon were slid
    open so that the two dozen or so invited guests could be accommodated
    between the two rooms without having to crowd round the table.</para>

    <para>It was now midsummer dark outside but inside a romantic tallow glow
    belied the long process of lighting all the candles of the many candelabra
    in the hall, reception room, grand salon and dining room. The heavy, blue
    velvet curtains at the windows facing onto the road which passes between
    the front of the house and the park beyond were drawn. The huge shutters
    at windows to the rear of the house were closed, excluding their view of
    the old, formal garden with its ancient copper beech and the waters of the
    Hollandse IJssel beyond. Finally, the curator had gone to the vapour box
    and carefully removed the treasured packet, borne it through the house and
    laid on the table with great reverence.</para>

    <para>Late on the previous day a sober-suited lawyer had brought the
    packet from the safe at the museum's trustees premises in Rotterdam. The
    trustees had been most reluctant to agree to the packet's removal from
    their purview but the curator had stood her ground until they relented.
    The museum was the house where the artifact had been produced and was
    where it's contents should be revealed. It had come home, so to speak, to
    be properly cared for rather than pawed at by soulless money-men. The
    trustees had not capitulated totally, imposing the condition that their
    lawyer remain present throughout proceedings, even keeping an
    uninterrupted vigil beside the vapour box.</para>

    <para>The curator gathered her wandering thoughts, replaced the head torch
    and returned her attention to the packet The guests quietened down at the
    resumption of activity as at the package. This time the curatot made
    greater allowance being for the liquid being applied to soak into the
    old-fashioned glue. Timing was of the essence as letting the fine wove
    paper become wet to the point of soggy would also court disaster. But, at
    last, the flap permitted itself to be prised open.</para>

    <para>Now the moment had arrived for the packet to be opened and the cache
    of documents that it had concealed since 1922 released into the light. It
    would have brought a touch of magic to the proceedings had it been
    possible to withdraw the papers one by one with a flourish as a conjourer
    might pull playing cards from a top hat. However, the thoroughness of
    their author's preparation thwarted this performance with an encircling
    girdle of fine, pink, silk ribbon intended to maintain the neatness of her
    precious bundle. This occasioned a further delay as time was needed for
    the careful removal of the intact bundle from its outer clothing, followed
    by the teasing apart of another knot and the laying aside of paper and
    ribbon.</para>

    <para>One hundred years of close confinement had trained the documents to
    stay in their allotted places despite the removal their restraints. The
    curator could not resist giving in to the impulse to theatricality as she
    made a play of clothing her hands in a pair of fine, white cotton gloves,
    slowly smoothing each finger into its sheath. Only when the protective
    gloves were situated to her complete satisfaction was the top paper
    separated from the rest of the pile in preparation for reading its
    contents out to the assembled audience. She faltered now, being a child of
    the age of digital type the curator was unaccustomed to reading this sort
    of handwritten material. It added to the challenge that the text was in
    the shaky hand of an octogenarian given to idiosyncratic abbreviations and
    using an antiquated form of the Dutch language. So, it was a halting but
    contemporary rendition of the letter which was read out loud for the
    benefit of those present:</para>

    <blockquote>
      <attribution>Weduwe Bisdom van Vliet, 21e december 1922</attribution>

      <para>To the people of Haastrecht, My last will and testament, which was
      signed and witnessed this day, bequeaths my house and sufficient of my
      estates to support its upkeep in trust for you, the people of
      Haastrecht, on condition that nothing in the house is changed. When you
      read this letter then one hundred years will have passed since my death
      and the execution of my will must have secured the physical legacy of
      the Bisdom van Vliet family. So, I will now address another aspect of
      the Bisdom van Vliet legacy that I am anxious should be
      preserved.</para>

      <para>It is said that a person is not truly lost to the living whilst
      they are still remembered and spoken of. I believe this to be true.
      Since I am the last Bisdom van Vliet it falls to me to pass on the human
      legacy of my family through means other than the blood line, by which I
      mean my biography as seen through the clear lens of time. The notes,
      letters and diary pages enclosed in this packet have been carefully
      selected by me in order to reveal something of the true characters and
      private lives of the individuals involved. By waiting for a century to
      pass I can be sure that none of those mentioned will neither feel any
      hurt nor be tempted to arrogance by what is contained herein. It is my
      wish that someone will take up their pen to reveal my story.</para>

      <para>I have witnessed many changes during my long life and wish to
      acknowledge that, a century after my passing, much will again be altered
      from the world I know. The last document in this packet is a codicil to
      my original will, which I am assured will be legally binding. In it I
      have made provision for a response to these changes.</para>
    </blockquote>

    <para>Anxious to discover what was meant by this unexpected final word
    from the writer, the curator tried to separate the bottom paper from those
    above it but, frustratingly, it refused to budge. So, slowly and
    painstakingly, beginning at the top of the pile, the documents were
    separated one by one then laid out in strict order across the table so
    that the gathering might at least look upon them. The final two documents
    proved to be stuck together by the seal affixed to the bottom one. The
    assembled pile must have been placed on top of the will codicil before the
    wax of its seal had completely set. Once more, the warmed knife was
    patiently applied to achieve the separation of the two documents. Then,
    just as the knife was about to be applied to the removal of the seal from
    the will codicil there was a distraction in the form of a bustle of motion
    and a stage cough nearby. Looking up, the curator came face to stony face
    with the Bisdom van Vliet trust's lawyer.</para>

    <para><quote>I think that we should observe the same legal procedure as is
    usual for the reading of a will. It is my view, also, that the appropriate
    experts in the relevant speciality of the law should be consulted in order
    to make a determination as to whether this additional document is, indeed,
    valid and binding. We need to be sure of our position before we announce
    Weduwe Bisdom van Vliet's final wish to the public.</quote></para>

    <para>The curator knew that the lawyer was right despite her frustration
    at the anti-climax of having so nearly exposed this last, unanticipated
    mystery. With reluctance, the sealed document was yielded up to the
    lawyer's outstretched, ungloved hand with a request that the he set about
    making the necessary arrangements as soon as possible. For the time being,
    all that remained was to supervise the museum's guests as they filed past
    the table to view the materials laid out upon it and made their way out of
    the building.</para>

    <para>After what seemed like an eternity, the curator was alone in the
    house. A decade had passed since her appointment as curator of the museum
    during which time she felt that a relationship had developed between
    Paulina, as she called the widow, and herself. The curator lived in a
    small but modern flat in what had previously been part of the house used
    only by servants. Her working days were spent in the dusty splendour of
    the main part of the house which had, indeed, been left in a century long
    time warp. She had also got inot the habit of wandering the rooms when the
    museum was closed, sometimes coming to rest in a chair and exercising her
    imagination in order to empathise with Paulina. It would only be right
    that she should be the one to write the widow's biography since she felt
    such a strong connection with her already. This surely gave her the right
    to be the first to see what was contained in the documents Paulina had
    provided as a window onto her life. Resuming her seat at the dinning
    table, the curator replaced her white, cotton gloves and gently picked up
    the first piece of paper ...</para>

    <para/>
  </section>
</chapter>
