<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter version="5.0" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
         xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
         xmlns:svg="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"
         xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
         xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
         xmlns:db="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
  <title>Overig August 1869</title>

  <section>
    <title></title>

    <para>The man considered it a sound investment to spend a few days working
    at a menial task for poor payment whilst enduring the bullying tirades of
    the nasty little chap who considered himself to be his superior. He
    laboured away fetching and carrying everything from heavy tables to the
    starched white cloths that would cover them, from boxes of silver cutlery
    to delicate floral arrangements, from crates of Champagne to trays of the
    fragile glasses from which it would be drunk. Then the pace changed as the
    tables were dressed and the places set with a military regularity that was
    checked with a measuring stick to ensure perfect spacings and alignments.
    Once the Tivoli's <emphasis>grote zaal</emphasis> had been laid out to the
    exacting standards of the overseer, the hired help were given time to rest
    and eat a basic meal of bread and cheese washed down with water or milk
    that was not provided out of any concern for the workers' welfare but from
    the necessity of discouraging them from helping themselves from the food
    and drink intended for the banquet.</para>

    <para>After being sent away to clean themselves up and put on the uniforms
    that would transform them from workmen into stewards, their next task was
    to greet the guests, surreptitiously checking that they were
    <emphasis>bona fide</emphasis> before showing them to their proper places.
    Two long tables ran the length of the <emphasis>grote zaal </emphasis>from
    the slightly raised top table which stretched across the head of the room.
    In the centre of the top table and right opposite the main doors so that
    it was the first thing the guests would see as they entered the
    <emphasis>room</emphasis> was the grand 'throne' upon which the bride and
    groom would sit beneath its fragrant canopy of pine branches which
    symbolised the evergreen nature the marital bond. Someone had put
    considerable diplomatic effort into the seating plan for the two long
    tables, making sure that the most important guests were seated in their
    proper order of importance whilst avoiding <emphasis>cliques</emphasis> or
    uncomfortable clashes of interests or personalities. So, it had been
    impressed upon the stewards that no changes of place whatsoever were to
    occur, either by accident or design.</para>

    <para>Although there was still an hour or more to go before the event was
    due to start, well-dressed men and women were already arriving and milling
    about the gardens. Whilst his colleagues were content to wait at the doors
    to the <emphasis>grote zaal</emphasis> for guests to approach them, the
    man set about unobtrusively identifying the wanderers and the new
    arrivals, shepherding them towards the stewards at the doors without them
    noticing either him or his influence upon them. His invisibility enabled
    him to overhear snippets of unguarded conversation, making good use of his
    knowledge of languages other than Dutch, and observe subtleties of
    behaviour. He noticed who bribed his colleagues in order to be seated
    nearer to whom, or further away from whom. This was why he was here, to
    gather information that would no doubt be of use to him in his usual, more
    lucrative, occupation. To this end he used his keen awareness of what was
    going on around him to avoid being co-opted to help with managing the
    press of carriages clogging the drive or carrying in the food which was
    being delivered to the back door.</para>

    <para>As the last guests took their seats in good time for the arrival of
    the bride and her wedding party, the man insinuated himself into a
    position where he would naturally be attending to the most important
    guests who were placed near to the top table. At 17.00 hours exactly,
    Paulina Maria Bisdom van Vliet swept into the room and took her place on
    the 'throne' in the centre of the top table. The familiar figures of her
    father and uncle, brother-in-law Viruly and Gilles le Fevre de Montigny,
    all accompanied by their wives, followed her along with her soon-to-be
    husband, about whom the man knew more than he had ever told. The women of
    the party seated themselves amid much arranging of skirts whilst the men
    had only to worry about their coat tails. The bride was joined on the
    'throne' by Johan Jacob le Fevre de Montigny seated to her left whilst her
    father was on her right flank. Once the top table had settled themselves
    and an expectant hush had descended upon the assembled body the Master of
    Ceremonies stepped forward and set the nuptial celebrations in motion with
    the traditional welcome:</para>

    <para><emphasis>Blijde feestdag, blijde feestdag, blijde
    feestdag</emphasis></para>

    <para><emphasis>Wij juighen u tegen</emphasis></para>

    <para><emphasis>Gij bragt aan de burger een zeer grote
    zegen</emphasis></para>

    <para><emphasis>De velden doorklonk het uit iederen mond</emphasis></para>

    <para><emphasis>Blijde feestdag, blijde feestdag</emphasis></para>

    <para><emphasis>Ter eere van Bruid en Bruidegom</emphasis></para>

    <para><emphasis>Een hartelijk welkom</emphasis></para>

    <para></para>

    <para>Happy holiday, happy holiday, happy holiday</para>

    <para>We cheer you</para>

    <para>You brought to the citizen a very large blessing</para>

    <para>It rings through the fields from every mouth</para>

    <para>Happy holiday, happy holiday</para>

    <para>For the honour of bride and groom</para>

    <para>A warm welcome</para>

    <para></para>

    <para>A huge cheer rang out from the guests who clapped the couple with
    enthusiasm, although many of them had never before set eyes on either of
    them. The man thought that they were really celebrating the signal to
    begin eating and drinking as much as they liked at someone else's expense,
    as well as capitalising on the opportunity to further their political,
    business and amorous interests. He himself was not particularly interested
    in the food on offer, although one of the other stewards had gossiped that
    he had counted forty-seven different savoury dishes, gleefully listing
    pike, perch, chicken, suckling pig, snipe, hare, partridge, pigeon, lamb
    stuffed with cauliflower, <emphasis>petit pois</emphasis>, beans and
    endives before either his memory or his imagination ran out. This was to
    be followed by seventeen deserts, apparently, but the man had lost
    patience with the fellow's account of these after the fourth type of tart
    had been described. What he was here for was what he would observe and
    overhear as he cleared away the empty plates and glasses.</para>

    <para>As if all the food and drink were not enough to keep the diners
    occupied, the meal was frequently punctuated by speeches from friends and
    family who told the life story of the bride and the groom, or a version of
    it, as well as offering anecdotes which illustrated the admirable
    qualities of each. On a livelier note, the company were invited to join in
    several songs of a whimsical nature relating to magic mops and such like.
    One alleged that the Zweeuwse farmers were amazed at the agility and
    genius of the bride and groom, which the man thought could be taken in
    several ways. These interludes resulted in the majority of the guests
    returning to their seats providing a respite from the general milling
    about which made the man's job more complicated.</para>

    <para>As well as for the usual calls of nature, guests who were not making
    speeches also got up to deliver presents to the bride and groom which she
    unwrapped there and then before handing them over to her intended so that
    they could both admire them before passing them around for the approval of
    everyone else. As was her nature, she kept a meticulous list of who had
    given them what so that the right gift might be brought out on show during
    future visits of the giver. All of this rigmarole took an inordinate
    amount of time and entailed a lot of wandering about, which made it
    difficult for the man to keep track of those people he had identified as
    of special interest to him. But, he also picked up some unexpected pieces
    of intelligence from others as they crossed his path.</para>

    <para>The light had already faded from the summer sky by the time the
    gathering partook of the last few items on the carefully orchestrated
    programme. Three large silver bowls full of brandy and raisins, one for
    each table, began their progress from person to person whilst the assembly
    energetically sang the song;</para>

    <para><emphasis>Hoe zoet is het daar de vriendschap
    woont</emphasis></para>

    <para><emphasis></emphasis></para>

    <para>How sweet it is where friendship dwells</para>

    <para></para>

    <para>Some of the stewards took up baskets laden with small gifts of the
    sweets and wine which they offered to each guest. The <emphasis>Bruid
    suikas</emphasis>, little packages of five sweets wrapped in tulle,
    symbolized the wedding wishes of love, happiness, loyalty, prosperity, and
    virility causing several of the recipients to make wry comments upon the
    latter. The <emphasis>Bruidstranen</emphasis>, small bottles of spiced
    wine containing a little gold leaf to represent the bride's tears, further
    provoked innuendos. The Master of Ceremonies made his closing
    declarations, thanked the assembled party for the Paulina and Johan's
    nuptial celebrations then bade everyone farewell on behalf of the bride
    and groom. The bride and groom rose from their throne to lead the platform
    party out of the <emphasis>grote zaal</emphasis> to a final round of
    cheers and applause.</para>

    <para>In the body of the hall chairs scraped back, clothing rustled and
    the hubbub of conversation resumed as people headed for the doors and
    their waiting transport beyond. This was the last chance for the man to
    pick up morsels of information for the already brimming storehouse in his
    brain before he and the other stewards had to set about the task of
    clearing away and setting the room straight. There was a lull as the men
    changed pace again from the public performance of stewarding to the more
    relaxed nature of backstage domestics. Taking advantage of this social
    space, the man quickly and quietly made his way round the tables pocketing
    those lost, forgotten or abandoned personal items that might later be of
    use to him in his work.</para>

    <para>Once the clatter of work resumed, the man joined in the camaraderie
    which so often spontaneously develops between those who serve as they wind
    down from of important events like this. They, too had heard things and
    were as keen to gossip to their fellows as he was to listen and encourage.
    Even the overseer was in better spirits now that the day had passed off
    successfully, no doubt helped by his having surreptitiously rewarded
    himself with the dregs of the bottles as they were taken out for
    collection. On the orders of the bride, any left-over food had been taken
    for distribution to the poor but she had forbidden them any alcohol and
    the overseer believed that it would have been a shame to waste it. The men
    were instructed to take off their white aprons and shirts so that the
    laundry baskets, into which the table cloths and napkins had already been
    thrown, could be taken away for laundering overnight. They were to hang up
    the rest of their uniforms and change back into their own working clothes
    for the last cleaning up before they straggled out into the night to make
    their weary way home.</para>

    <para>The man was careful to avoid company as he made his way along
    Kruisstraat in the direction of the his hotel which he had carefully
    chosen to afford anonymity by being the largest in Utrecht. As he walked
    along he adjusted his clothing to give a smarter appearance, altering his
    bearing and gait to such good effect that a gentleman returning from a
    late night stroll collected his room key and messages from the night
    porter. He ordered a good supper to be brought to his room, being now very
    hungry as well as wishing to sustain himself for the work of the day yet
    to be done. A ewer of hot water was waiting for him by the time he opened
    his door so he was able to wash and change into his nightshirt and
    dressing gown whilst waiting for his supper tray. The servant bringing his
    food stayed briefly to hang up his clothes and remove the empty water jug
    before being assured that he would not be wanted again that night.</para>

    <para>Having made himself comfortable and secured the privacy of his
    chamber, the man set about organising the material he had gathered at the
    banquet. First he retrieved from his mental filing system all that he
    already knew about the persons of interest whom he had encountered that
    day. Then he put pen to paper making additional notes about each one as
    well as adding some new individuals to his bank of knowledge. One by one
    he dealt with the people he was watching, committing the contents of each
    sheet of notes to his phenomenal memory store. Once all had been attended
    to, the man bent over the grate and dismantled the fire which had been
    laid there against a sudden drop in temperature or bout of illness. He
    carefully twisted and knotted his now discarded papers into bows and
    placed them amongst those which had already formed the basis of the unlit
    fire. He replaced the sticks of kindling and the coals, from small to
    large. Taking a taper from the jar on the grate he lit it from one of the
    lamps and applied it to the foundations of the fire, pleased to see the
    flames immediately take hold creating a sudden and intense conflagration
    which destroyed all it could find to feed on.</para>

    <para>Only now could the man allow himself the luxury of a glass of brandy
    and a cigar sitting in a chair beside the roaring fire. It did not take
    long for him to relax into a state where he was able to get into bed,
    falling asleep to the first bird calls of a new day. It was only a few
    hours until he was woken by the arrival of his morning shaving water but
    he felt refreshed and alert, ready for another working day. Although his
    duties at Tivoli would begin later today, no furniture needing to be moved
    until the second day of banqueting was over, the man began his
    observations at breakfast in the hotel. Here he could keep his eyes on the
    numerous other guests, some due to depart after the previous day's
    celebrations and some preparing for those to come that day, all of whom
    seemed to share the feeling that they could not refuse their invitation as
    it was hard to plead prior engagements for both days. Only Hendrick Prins
    der Nederlanden en Prins van Oranje-Nassau could decline to attend without
    any embarrassment to anyone. Henrik <emphasis>de Zeevaarder</emphasis>, as
    he was known, was a naval man and a navigator like the groom with whom he
    frequently socialised in the manner of sailors on shore leave. The man had
    been very careful not to disclose what he knew of the activities of these
    men when making his report to Theodorus Viruly concerning the groom's
    suitability as a husband for the Bisdom van Vleit daughter.</para>

    <para>Having lingered over breakfast, the man made a thorough check to
    make sure that all was in order in his room then paid his bill and left
    instructions for his luggage to be packed and conveyed to the station left
    luggage office. It was time to set out for his second day at the Tivoli,
    reversing the transformation from gentleman to working man of the previous
    night as he strode along. Although the programme was exactly the same as
    that of the previous day down to the last detail the different mix of
    guests made for a quite distinct experience. The man followed the same
    strategy as previously but found his task was complicated by the
    disruptive boisterousness of the groom's naval shipmates and the presence
    of several important political figures who had seen him before but in a
    different guise. To his relief and satisfaction, he did not appear to have
    been recognised but nevertheless took pains to keep at a distance from
    those who might be able to identify him. On the other hand, the to-ing and
    fro-ing of the seafarers, who refused to stay in their alloted seats and
    demanded a great deal of attention from the stewards, added to the already
    raised levels of activity with the effect that they somewhat hampered the
    man's ability find an unobtrusive place from which to watch and
    listen.</para>

    <para>By the time the guests had left and the clearing up began patience
    was getting stretched among the servants making everyone irritable.
    Tonight they had the added labour of clearing the furniture from the
    <emphasis>grote</emphasis><emphasis> zaal</emphasis>, heavy work for the
    tired men whose minds were already elsewhere with wives and sweethearts,
    food and drink. At last the overseer was satisfied that the room was being
    left as it had been found and called the staff to line up to receive their
    payment before dismissing them to go their separate ways into the night.
    The man had a few hours to kill before catching the early train to Den
    Haag so took a circuitous route to the station, ruefully turning over the
    few coins in his pocket that had been his payment at the end of the two
    days. By the time he had bought himself an early breakfast at the bargee's
    favourite eetcafe on the Oude Gracht and tipped the station porter who
    dealt with his luggage there was not much left. His work was not yet done,
    either, as he still had his records to get up to date once he arrived back
    at his own, solitary dwelling.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title></title>

    <para>If Paulina had harboured any concerns about being left at the alter
    they were soon dispelled. The whole village could hear the groom's
    procession as it came along the dyke top from Gouda since it was headed up
    by the band of the field artillery regiment playing for all they were
    worth. The groom's carriage was escorted by a huge troop, later reported
    in the Schoonhovensche en Haastrechtsche Courant to have numbered 90, of
    young men dressed in uniforms to match that of the groom. All of his
    guests followed in a long train of horse-drawn conveyances which added to
    their clatter and chatter to the din. As the whole noisy entourage arrived
    at the edge of the village another guard of honour joined them and
    escorted the groom, now on foot, in a swaggering and jubilant procession
    to the Bisdom van Vliet house.</para>

    <para>The Haastrecht villagers had not been unsparing in their
    preparations for Paulina's marriage either. The front door of the house
    had been painted green, as was the tradition, and a triumphal arch erected
    in front of it for the bride to pass under. The children from the village
    school had greatly enjoyed decorating this arch and joining in with the
    making of green flags which were then strung between all the houses in
    Haastrecht and along the fronts of the farms in Stein and Vlist. Flowers,
    and various insignia completed the festoons and even the competing
    religious denominations had come together to raise money in order to make
    a display of their various arms and symbols.</para>

    <para>The correspondent for the Schoonhovensche en Haastrechtsche Courant
    was so overwhelmed by all these wedding preparations that he was reduced
    to somewhat heatedly reporting;</para>

    <para>... <emphasis>het strekke alleen ten bewijze dat daar, waar
    eensgezindheid en erkentijkheid op de voorgrond staan, welwillendheid en
    liefde niet achterblijven.</emphasis></para>

    <para><emphasis></emphasis></para>

    <para>... this demonstrates that, where harmony and gratitude are to the
    fore, benevolence and love are not far behind.</para>

    <para></para>

    <para>The groom's cavalcade halted when it came to the Bisdom van Vliet
    house and here they re-arranged themselves for the next stage in their
    progress. The chamber in the Raadhuis where the formal marriage ceremony
    was to take place was too small to accommodate more than a modest wedding
    party restricted to the couple's most intimate family and friends. All the
    other guests would be provided with light refreshments at the house before
    moving on to the church. Those members of the groom's band, escort and
    honour guard who were not required for the next stage of the procession
    were allowed to relax in the<emphasis> overtuin</emphasis> where they were
    given some rather more modest food and drink than that on offer indoors.
    It took a while for the clamour of the groom's arrival to die down during
    which time Paulina waited patiently in her room until the moment arrived
    when she could be sure of being the centre of attention as she processed
    through the village to begin her nuptials. Those who were to accompany her
    to the Raadhuis gathered in the vestibule, the groom's excess of high
    spirits gradually being calmed by his brother.</para>

    <para>Once the Raadhuis cortege, with a somewhat reduced number of
    musicians and guard of honour, had formed up Marcellus went to fetch his
    daughter. They were both rather disconcerted by Johan Jacob's grandiose
    and flamboyant arrival which threatened to upstage their preparations and
    to eclipse the augustness of the marriage rite itself. Marcellus was aware
    that Viruly still had doubts about the suitability of the bridegroom and
    for the first time he began to have misgivings himself. Paulina sensed a
    reserve in her father's behaviour which made for an awkwardness between
    them quite uncharacteristic of their relationship. She had felt a little
    on edge already but attributed this to the gravity of the occasion. On top
    of this, the delay caused by Johan Jacob's unanticipated departure from
    her carefully arranged schedule had perturbed her. So, she attributed the
    strangeness between herself and her father to bridal nerves which caused
    her to anxiously avert her gaze from him thereby effectively blocking any
    further communication between them. The distance between them meant that
    Marcellus felt unable to gently remind his only child that it was not too
    late to call the wedding off, so he followed her down to the vestibule in
    silence instead.</para>

    <para>Once they reached the crowded vestibule both father and daughter
    found themselves caught up by the expectations of the assemblage which
    involuntarily propelled them into the day their, minds empty of all doubt
    or apprehension. They did, however, depart from protocol in just one way
    when, as a result of some tacit agreement between them, Paulina took her
    father's arm and not that of her bridegroom before stepping out through
    the green door, walking under the triumphal arch and out onto the
    petal-strewn street to take her place at the head of the wedding
    procession. The groom had been so caught up in putting on his own show for
    his admirers that he let the moment pass when he might have intervened and
    claimed his bride for his own arm. It took some management by his brother
    to focus his attention and prevail upon him to fall in behind his bride
    and her father ahead of the other members of their families and the chosen
    friends.</para>

    <para>The Hoogstrat was lined with cheering adults and children who had
    come out in their numbers to scatter petals under the bride's feet and
    wish the her well. Paulina and Marcellus walked slowly so as to
    acknowledge the crowd's good wishes and show their appreciation and
    admiration for the bedecked streets. At last they arrived at the bottom of
    the stone steps leading up to the marriage room within the Raadhuis. The
    pretty little step-gabled town hall was so old that it even pre-dated the
    arrival of Adriaan Bisdom in Haastrecht. At one point its steps decayed to
    become so unsafe that old Oma's husband, burgemeester Salomon Reynders
    Bisdom van Vliet, had ordered them demolished and replaced by the handsome
    hard stone steps which now rose to the door into De Burgerzaal where all
    the marriages were solemnized including those of Paulina's ancestors. It
    was only when they reached the bottom of the steps that Paulina's father
    looked round for Johan Jacob, signaling that the groom should now step up
    beside the bride to accept the greetings and thanks of the guests as they
    made their way into the wedding room.</para>

    <para>When everyone in the intimate circle had disappeared into the
    Raadhuis, Paulina made her way up the seven steps supporting herself by
    holding onto the iron hand rail with one had and her groom with the other.
    Perhaps it was that his feet were obscured by her huge skirts but Paulina
    did not feel that Johan Jacob was entirely confident on his feet and was
    glad when they reached the level platform between the steps and the
    doorway. A lion statue stood at either end of this balcony, one holding
    the coat of arms of Haastrecht and the other holding the arms of South
    Holland. Since she had been a child visiting her father in his
    burgermeesterskamer Paulina had been in the habit of touching the top of
    each lion's head for good luck and she did not intend to tempt fate by
    breaking this pattern today. As she reached for the first lion she
    inadvertently jostled Johan Jacob causing him to totter back down the top
    step, confirming her feeling that he had not quite lost his sea legs. Once
    the second lion had had his head tapped Paulina made her grand entry into
    the Raadhuis with the now recovered Johan Jacob in her wake.</para>

    <para>Marcellus's deputy was to perform the ceremony and was there inside
    the door to greet the bride and groom, ushering them to their places
    before the table which held the large book in which their marriage was to
    be recorded. As Johan Jacob removed his ceremonial sword and handed it to
    his brother before being seated, Paulina took her first proper look at her
    bridegroom. He was resplendent in a uniform decorated with shiny buttons,
    badges and shoulder boards as well as the belt which had held his sword
    and scabbard. Her heart leapt at the sight of him, restoring to the full
    her confidence in the marriage she was about to contract. But first they
    had to wait for the company to settle down. The room was full to capacity
    as the importance of the Bisdom van Vliet's dictated that the maximum
    possible number of guests be accommodated. The generous proportions of the
    floral arrangements placed on the floor at the end of each row of seats
    combined with the copious skirts of the ladies to fill every available
    niche so that it seemed as though the smiling faces of the guests were
    floating above a billowing sea of shimmering fabrics and colourful blooms.
    It was also quite dim and hot in the chamber as the door and lower window
    shutters had been closed for privacy allowing little light or air to wash
    over what remained of the unoccupied space in the room.</para>

    <para>Paulina was, therefore, glad that the formalities were quickly under
    way and conducted at a brisk pace. After a brief speech of welcome, the
    Loco-burgemeester asked the couple to stand and face each other, clasping
    their right hands. First his marriage vow was read to Johan Jacob to which
    he assented in a clear, firm voice. Then Paulina Maria heard her vows and
    also gave her assent without hesitation. A murmur of delight ran round the
    room. In his role as Ambtenaar van de Burgerlijke Stand, Marcellus's
    deputy managed to balance due gravitas with a lightness of touch that left
    the gathering in a suitably celebratory mood when he seized the right
    moment to pronounce Paulina and Jacob wedded in the eyes of the law. Johan
    kissed his bride to a round of applause from the gathering before the
    couple took their seats again for the final formality of signing the
    register.</para>

    <para>Man and wife now led the way back through the cheering villagers
    lining Hoogstraat, taking the turning down to the church instead of
    continuing to the house.. They passed beneath another triumphal arch and
    were scattered with more petals as they stood to one side and accepted the
    congratulations of the last members of the congregation as they filed past
    them into the church. Once everyone was seated inside, the Pastor led the
    couple to their seats beside him at the front of the knave. The interior
    of the plain white church was decorated with floral displays of an even
    more striking size and vibrancy than those in the Raadhuis and swags of
    pure white tulle decorated the ends of all the pews.</para>

    <para>Paulina was thankful that there was more space, light and air inside
    the church as she knew that the consecration of her marriage before God
    was going to be a more lengthy affair than the civil ceremony had been.
    She was glad of the presence of her parents seated nearby in the front row
    of pews, surprising herself at how much she drew support just from seeing
    them there. She was feeling more emotional than she would ever have
    thought she could be and, although she considered herself to be a devout
    woman who was a regular worshiper at the church, Paulina found the length
    of the wedding service tested her capacity for stoicism almost to its
    limit. With great self-discipline she sat through many readings from the
    Bible, a lengthy homily from the Pastor and more speeches by close family
    and friends. It was something of a relief when this seemingly endless
    stream of well-intentioned words was punctuated by music and, better yet,
    standing to sing a hymn.</para>

    <para>Then Paulina and Johan were stirred to action as they were called to
    stand before the Pastor and take turns in repeating their vows before God,
    now more fully and explicitly stating the duties and responsibilities of
    marriage which they were accepting. A gold ring resting on a plush velvet
    cushion was brought before the Pastor who blessed it and reminded the
    couple that it was a symbol of the eternity of the marriage bond which was
    to be placed on the right hand as this was the good, not sinister, hand
    and so connected to the divine. Johan picked up the ring then gently took
    Paulina's right hand in his left and slipped the ring onto her third
    finger. She felt a lump rise in her throat and tears well up in her eyes,
    indeed she trembled with a suppressed sob. In response to this Johan gave
    her hand a gentle squeeze and, when she turned to look at him, she found
    that he, too, had moist eyes.</para>

    <para>Another red velvet cushion was brought to the Pastor, this one
    supporting the wedding bible in the front of which their marriage was
    already inscribed and where they would go on to add the names and dates of
    birth of their children along with other significant events, not all of
    which would be so joyous. The bible was given into Johan's keeping with
    the direction that the couple should keep it as the family bible for the
    new le Fevre de Montingy - Bisdom van Vliet line. Paulina felt a flush of
    pride when she heard her family name so openly and directly linked with
    that of her husband as founders of a new branch of the family. It mattered
    very much to her that she should produce an heir to the wealth and
    position of her family. But there was a deeper need arriving within her
    that suddenly demanded her attention - she wanted to have children, soon
    and lots of them. She was abashed at this very public allusion to such
    intimate matters, not fully realising that her private thoughts remained
    hidden from scrutiny and not as conspicuous to the congregation looking on
    as she feared. Rather self-consciously, she risked a sidelong glance at
    Johan and found him looking intently at the bible in his hands with a
    sheepish expression on his face which somewhat puzzled her.</para>

    <para>Then suddenly it was over and Paulina felt thoroughly and very
    publicly married. As she and Johan turned to face the body of the church
    in preparation for making their exit, Paulina half hoped that he would be
    romantic enough to kiss her again in front of everybody whilst admitting
    to herself that this would actually embarrass her. She did not quite know
    if she was glad or not that no kiss was forthcoming, instead he took her
    hand and placed it through his arm for the procession out of the church
    where, reunited with his sword, he would escort her back to the family's
    house. Once more they made their way haltingly as they accepted the
    congratulations of the onlookers, smiling until their faces felt as if
    they might never go back straight again. When they had attained the
    sanctuary of the house they were tactfully granted some time to themselves
    in a small ante-room on the ground floor the old
    <emphasis>familiehuis</emphasis>. Now they held each other and exchanged
    kisses with the freedom that being married now allowed them as well as the
    awkwardness of novelty.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title></title>

    <para>The rest of her wedding day did not pass off with quite the finesse
    that Paulina could have wished for. It had sounded eminently sensible when
    Johan had explained to her that, by the time they might reasonable expect
    to be able to take their leave from Haastrecht, it would be too late in
    the day for an immediate departure for Germany and the start of their
    honeymoon trip, yet she could not hide from herself that she was a little
    disappointed. This sense of blighted hopes deepened into disgruntlement
    when he told her that they would be spending their first night of marriage
    in his rooms at the Hotel De Zalm. Perhaps familiarity should not breed
    contempt but nevertheless she felt somewhat irked that commonplace old
    Gouda and Johan's habitual residence were to be the setting for the
    consummation that would mark the final covenant of their marriage. If the
    arrangements had been left to her then a more exclusive and original venue
    would have been found, one which held no resonances with their separate
    pasts. On the other hand, Gouda did have the cachet of being the place
    where they met.</para>

    <para>To convey them to the hotel Johan had ordered an appropriately
    luxurious landau which was pulled by a pair of fine white horses and
    decorated with flowers and ribbons. When the time came for them to set out
    for their new life together their closest family gathered in the
    <emphasis>familiehuis</emphasis> vestibule for the final farewells.
    Paulina found it hard to tear herself away from her papa's embrace but saw
    that her mama was waiting for her turn to tearfully hug and kiss her
    youngest daughter as she left the shelter of her family to embark on the
    joys and sorrows of the wedded state. After discreetly allowing the Bisdom
    van Vliets a few moments of farewell Johan stepped forward to claim his
    bride, leaving her mother and father to cling to each other in their
    happiness and grief.</para>

    <para>A liveried coachman assisted the couple into the landau to take the
    seats which faced forwards whilst a boy groom held the horses. When they
    were settled and ready to depart, the lad took his seat behind them whilst
    the coachman climbed up onto his box, taking the four reins in hand ready
    for the signal to set off. The top of the carriage was folded down which,
    along with its low shell, insured that anyone looking on would have a good
    view of the couple in all their finery. In readiness for going away
    Paulina had changed into a quite plain but full cut skirt made of a richly
    patterned ivory silk on top of which she wore a jacket of a deep red satin
    silk which was ruffled around the edges as well as the top and bottom of
    the narrow cut sleeves. This was her new carriage costume which had been
    specially made for use on her honeymoon, her bride dress being now a
    discarded thing left behind whilst the rest of her trousseau already sent
    on ahead to await her arrival in Gouda. An ivory lace scarf tied at the
    high neck of an ivory under blouse completed the outfit and gave it a
    slightly jaunty look. Bare-headed as usual, her only adornment was the
    earrings which had been a gift from Johan during their brief courtship
    and, of course, her golden wedding ring.</para>

    <para>The rump of Johan's musicians and guard of honour led the way out of
    the village and along the dyke top, but they had lost some of their
    enthusiasm and, for Paulina, all of their rather limited charm so she was
    thoroughly relieved when they called a halt at Stolwijkersluis so that she
    and Johan could continue the last leg of its journey alone and in peace.
    Their escort had served one valuable purpose which was distract from a
    sudden reticence that caused a lull in the conversation between herself
    and Johan. He seemed rather preoccupied with preening his uniform and
    smoothing his hair, having apparently paid scant attention to her or made
    any comment on her change of costume. Paulina was left to gaze rather
    sullenly at the familiar passing landscape and try not to feel . Upon
    their arrival at De Zalm she was disconcerted to find all his friends and
    fellow hotel guests assembled outside to greet him and, rather secondarily
    it seemed, his wife. She forced her aching face to smile and her
    complaining stomach to accept a glass of Champagne and some savouries from
    the trays which circulated in quick succession. Johan was reinvigorated by
    the attention of his cronies, not to mention the ingestion of several
    glasses of Champagne, whilst she was wilting and starting to doubt her
    ability to stay on her feet for much longer.</para>

    <para>Not at all accustomed to the sensation of physical weakness, Paulina
    did not know what to do except try to lean on Johan for support but he had
    disappeared into the bustle of people and was lost to her. Suddenly a maid
    appeared at her side and suggested that she might like to follow her
    inside the hotel to find somewhere quiet to catch her breath. This pretty
    little creature seemed to know exactly what was needed and how to arrange
    things without making Paulina feel in the least bit inferior or
    vulnerable. Paulina followed the maid to a small drawing room where she
    was alone and allowed herself to be helped to take a seat in the
    protective embrace of a comfortable wing chair. A glass of seltzer water
    was fetched and the maid unobtrusively shut the curtains on the sunny side
    of the room before asking if there was anything else madam required.
    Paulina could think of nothing, nothing at all, so thanked the young woman
    and dismissed her with a slight waft of her right hand.</para>

    <para>As soon as the maid was gone Paulina started to feel a bleakness of
    spirit which only grew worse as she brooded on the thought that Johan had
    abandoned her, seemingly heedless of his obligations, on their special
    day. She was glad to have the space to recover herself from the hurley
    burley outside and yet the notion that Johan had not noticed her absence
    and come looking for her promoted a sudden wavering in her belief in his
    love and his commitment to their marriage. She started to sink into a
    perilous quagmire of hurt and insecurity, a novel sensation which she did
    not like at all. As she reached the brink of despair and peered into the
    black abyss beyond, the apparatus at the core of her character stirred
    into action and drove a rallying of her strength that energised her will
    to deal with the situation. She must behave as the independent woman she
    knew herself to be deep down and not the sort of silly person whose role
    she had rejected not so many weeks ago and in the very church now just
    across the Maarkt. On that June day she had determined to have her own
    life and not be governed by conventions of marriage or the demands of a
    husband.</para>

    <para>She had anticipated a period of quiet settling into their rooms
    would follow arrival at De Zalm so this was just what she would arrange
    for herself. Paulina rose from her chair and rang for a servant. When the
    little maid appeared she gave instructions that she wished to be shown to
    their rooms where she desired to have tea and cakes brought to her. A
    flash of spite held her back from asking for Johan to be informed of her
    whereabouts, however. The maid went to fetch a porter with the key and
    Paulina followed him up the stairs to the second floor where she was let
    into a drawing room at the front of the building. She held out her hand
    for the key which the porter hesitantly yielded up in exchange for a small
    gratuity, quickly pocketed, before departing to organise her tea tray to
    be sent up. Going over to one of the rooms two tall windows she held back
    the edge of the net curtain and took in the view of the Stadhuis and,
    across the Maarkt, Sint Janskerk. Despite her taut nerves she could not
    help but appreciate the outlook and draw comfort and strength from seeing
    the tower of the great church rising above the city. </para>

    <para>After some minutes contemplation of the view from the window, she
    turned to take in the rest of the room which she saw to be equipped with
    good quality, fashionable furniture of a style in keeping with that of the
    building itself. Through her visits to Aggie and Theo she was keenly aware
    of the controversy which had surrounded the granting of permission for the
    original De Zalm, claimed by some to be the oldest inn in the Netherlands,
    to be completely remodelled in the style fashionable in Den Haag. The new
    building towered over the old Waag, something that could never have been
    countenanced in earlier centuries, and its bright, white exterior
    dominated the market square and upset many local traditionalists. Theo had
    been keen to push for progress and she now found that she rather approved
    of what had been achieved, considering that the old place had been rather
    dilapidated and vulgar whereas the room she was standing in was light,
    tasteful and very respectable.</para>

    <para>Aside from the main door leading out onto the landing, there was a
    second door in the room which could only lead to the more private
    quarters. It stood ever so slightly ajar tempting her to push it further
    open whereas she would have hesitated to open a closed door. It was a
    heavy door and a tentative nudge only moved it a little but that was
    enough to reveal a dresser on which stood an open gentleman's travelling
    dressing table case, a selection of its contents having been taken out for
    use and left lying on the dresser top beside it. Paulina was rooted to the
    spot as she looked at these personal items belonging to Johan and which
    now possessed the cachet of marital intimacy. Until now Paulina had not
    even considered what married life might mean in the way of such personal
    details, having been completely caught up with the event of the wedding
    itself. The silver shaving brush and holder, the shaving stick in its
    holder, an ivory-backed clothes brush, an ivory-backed hair brush, various
    plain glass bottles with silver stoppers and an open red leather manicure
    set spoke to Johan's private preparations for the day. Of course she found
    Johan handsome and, despite his apparent carelessness towards her, still
    she longed to be in his arms again and quite understood what was to happen
    to consummate their union. But now, peeping round the door at these
    masculine items and imagining him applying them to his physical person, it
    struck her full force that Johan was corporeal and his male body was now
    part of her life. The idea confounded her as desire fought with distaste,
    rooting her to the spot.</para>

    <para>Just at that moment the main door to the room opened to the rattling
    of things on the tea tray. Paulina quickly turned back into the drawing
    room feeling as if she had been caught out like a naughty child. She
    expected to see a servant and was even more disconcerted to come face to
    face with Johan instead. Unbeknownst to Paulina, the little maid had taken
    the liberty, presuming upon their earlier dealings, to approach Johan and
    discretely inform him of Paulina's situation and the necessity for him to
    go to her. Realizing his oversight Johan had immediately gone to their
    rooms, just happening to arrive at the door just as the waiter with the
    tea tray was about to knock. He had hurried in ahead of the man, concerned
    to compensate for his laxity as a husband with solicitousness towards the
    wife he was not yet accustomed to having.</para>

    <para>"My dear, I missed you at the party downstairs and grew concerned.
    Tell me truly, are you feeling unwell?"</para>

    <para>Conscious that the servant might overhear them in their imperfection
    as a couple, Paulina waited until the door had closed behind him before
    replying;</para>

    <para>"I am quite well, thank you. Just a little fatigued but I shall soon
    be recovered."</para>

    <para>"I am so relieved to hear you say so. I was distressed to think that
    you had been taken ill and I was unaware of it. But, here you are and
    looking quite the picture of health!"</para>

    <para>She had tried to be cool towards him but now that Johan was back
    with her she found that she just wanted his arms about her and this had
    brought colour into her face. Seizing his advantage, Johan took her in an
    embrace whilst saying; </para>

    <para>"I took the liberty of asking for an extra cup and plate to be
    fetched so that we might take tea together and enjoy being alone. It has
    been a marvelous celebration of our marriage and I have revelled in every
    part of it but I am also looking forward to your private
    companionship."</para>

    <para>He broke off to kiss her neck and stroke her unruly hair before
    continuing;</para>

    <para>"Let us keep to ourselves for the rest of today. What do you say?
    Just an old married couple spending a quiet night together? "</para>

    <para>Before she could reply there was a knock at the door, which caused
    her to start and break away from Johan, and the waiter came in with the
    extra crockery and cutlery. Once they were alone again, she felt herself
    enveloped by Johan as he pressed her close and began gently kissing her
    neck then her cheek and finally her mouth. His affection had a calming,
    almost soporific, effect on her and she found the closeness of his body
    brought her a sense of comfort. Indeed, the feeling she had was
    reminiscent of the times when, as a child, she had been soothed and sent
    to sleep by snuggling up to her nanny. But Johan was a man with a man's
    urges, yet an experienced lover who knew to slacken his embrace before the
    urgency of his erection could be felt even through Paulina's thick
    petticoats. He knew that he must take care not to cause her any
    consternation as that would only make her more resistant to him when the
    time came. </para>

    <para>The distraction of taking tea was just what was required to soothe
    them both in their different ways and to reconcile them to the finality of
    their marital pledge. The social routine of an apparently normal evening
    provided just enough interest and activity to distract from the tacit
    prospect of their impending first sexual encounter. As there was only one
    suite of bedroom and dressing rooms and it would have been unthinkable as
    yet for both to occupy them simultaneously whilst changing for dinner, so
    Johan deferred to Paulina who summoned her maid and the two women
    disappeared into the private apartments. Paulina now saw what lay behind
    the door which she had earlier peeped round, finding that her maid had
    already unpacked her necessary things and laid out her new dinner dress on
    the bed. Paulina, with the help of her maid, took great care over her
    toilette not simply in order to please Johan but also as a way of taking
    the time to calm herself in this rather thrilling but slightly alarming
    new situation through the slow performance of familiar routines.</para>

    <para>At last she emerged and accepted Johan's admiration of her
    appearance. He had not been idle during her absence having provided a
    selection of newspapers and magazines for her to peruse. He had also
    ordered Champagne and, in case she might prefer it, Paulina's favourite
    red vermouth and some seltzer water all of which were ready for her to
    make her selection of beverage. Johan settled her in a chair with all that
    she said she required readily to hand before bending to kiss her once more
    prior to taking his leave to get changed. In his absence she sipped some
    seltzer water and looked through the newspapers for anything about
    Haastrecht or anyone of her acquaintance but, since there was very little
    to arouse her interest, she began a desultory examination of the
    magazines. </para>

    <para>She was on the point of having to admit to herself that she was
    simply waiting for Johan to return when the bedroom door opened and he
    rejoined her, looking very smart in his dinner clothes and smelling of a
    pleasingly light and fresh cologne. Johan uncorked the Champagne but she
    declined his offer of a glass and he did not entreat her. He did, however,
    help himself before drawing his chair close to hers and taking his seat.
    They both confessed to being glad to be rid of their bulky and hot outdoor
    clothes. It had been an unusually hot day for late summer, which Paulina
    felt had blessed their wedding day although she could see that Johan would
    have been more affected by the heat in his thick uniform clothes than she
    was in her relatively light gown. Johan amused her with an account of how
    uncooperative he had found his ceremonial sword, leaping to his feet to
    re-enact some of his less adroit moments as he found it necessary to
    remove and re-attach this willful prop at several points during the day.
    Laughing conspiratorially with him made her feel that they were sharing a
    secret which must serve to bring them closer together.</para>

    <para>Johan proposed that they should dine in their rooms, to which she
    readily assented feeling that she had been in the public eye quite enough
    for one day. Having first solicited her approval, Johan then took charge
    of ordering a selection of dishes that he thought to be her favourites and
    which he believed that the De Zalm chef could execute to a high standard.
    She found it pleasing that he showed himself to be aware of her tastes in
    food and honoured that he was so desirous of ensuring that his knowledge
    of the hotel kitchen could be applied to making sure that the best
    available fare was placed before her. She was delighted by the sumptuous
    array of elegantly presented plates that were placed before them and was
    eager to sample them all. Oddly, her appetite somehow deserted her and she
    found that she could only manage the first mouthful of each thing on her
    plate, delicious though everything tasted. She was grateful for Johan's
    consideration in that he did not push her to eat or drink more than she
    chose to although she noticed that he ate heartily himself as well as
    drinking the whole bottle of Champagne.</para>

    <para>Once their repast had lost its appeal and the evidence of it had
    been cleared away by the servants they found themselves alone again.
    Paulina felt a brief flash of awkwardness but Johan soon dispelled any
    strangeness between them with his attentiveness and she quickly found that
    they were chatting away quite comfortably and finding themselves in accord
    on anything and everything. She was charmed by Johan using endearments
    without committing the error of being overly familiar. She also found him
    quite enchanting in the way he added the frisson of a little touch here
    and a kiss there to the rapport developing between them. He knew exactly
    how and when to suggest that they prepare for the night so that it seemed
    the most natural thing in the world that they should find themselves alone
    together in the bedroom after her maid and his man had been dismissed. She
    found that he also knew just how to tantalize them both with glimpses and
    assurances, kisses and caresses so that she willingly joined him in the
    big hotel bed. But once they were between the sheets with the lamps
    extinguished the night did not pass quite as either of them might have
    predicted.</para>

    <para>Maybe Johan had drunk too much Champagne. Perhaps Paulina had become
    overheated by his long, slow seduction. Possibly he had been too
    proficient in his conquest. Certainly both were overwrought after the
    hectic and tiring few weeks leading up to this climax of their nuptials.
    It could be that Paulina had shed her sexual inhibitions along with all
    the other strictures placed upon a woman of her station in life. What was
    certain was that Johan, who had been prepared to coax and cajole his way
    into her in the belief that patrician women were not by nature sexual
    beings, shrank in the face of her frank interest in his genitals. She, in
    turn, was somewhat discomfited that her knowledge of how these matters
    proceeded, which had been largely gained in the stables and farms with
    little ameliorating advice from her mother, did not lead to the
    deflowering she had imagined would follow naturally. She found that Johan
    now started to flounder about whilst her efforts became increasingly
    fraught and useless until she simply gave up then fell into a fitful sleep
    that left her both exhausted and unsatisfied when she woke the next
    morning. Her cherished hope of a honeymoon pregnancy now took on the
    appearance of a fading dream.</para>
  </section>
</chapter>
