<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter version="5.1" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
         xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:xila="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude/local-attributes"
         xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
         xmlns:trans="http://docbook.org/ns/transclusion"
         xmlns:svg="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"
         xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
         xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
         xmlns:db="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
  <title>New Year 1871</title>

  <section>

    <para>They had travelled to Haastrecht to join the big family gathering at
    her parents' house, which Paulina still thought of as 'home', for the
    celebration the start of a new year. Aggie and Theo were there with their
    brood of eight children as was Uncle Otto and Adelaide with their six.
    Next to her own family the le Fevre de Montigny's made a sorry
    contribution to the numbers with just one child between them, Gillis and
    Mary's small son now aged three. The total of fourteen children whose ages
    ranged between two and twenty three along with the mix of adults who
    brought with them a variety of ill-concealed tensions made the assemblage
    a somewhat complicated one. The more grown up offspring tried to be part
    of the adult festivities unaware of ther undercurrents to the rather
    strained atmosphere so innocently adding their contribution. The six
    little ones became rather rowdy in the excitement of a game of
    hide-and-seek in the favourably rambling old
    <emphasis>familiehuis</emphasis>. The four younsters who were neither
    children nor yet grown up didn't quite know what to do with themselves so
    roamed about feeling awkward, especially since they were divided equally
    between two different family groups so did not know eachother very
    well.</para>

    <para>Paulina had some sympathy with those who seemed out of place among
    the party. It was at times like this that she felt something of an odd one
    out herself having failed to produce a child after sixteen months of
    marriage. She was acutely self-aware that the others were noticing her
    barrenness and negatively judging her marriage or, more precisely, her was
    distressing and only served to intensify the pain of her unfulfilled
    longing for children. She wished that she could tell someone, her mother
    maybe or, better still, Aggie, what her situation was but it was too
    private a matter to be spoken of. Besides, there had been some sort of
    cooling towards her on Aggie's part since she married Johan which she
    suspected had its origins in Theo's unspoken but evident disapproval of
    her choice of husband.</para>

    <para>If she could have spoken out, she would have reassured them that all
    was normal with her monthly cycle and that marital relations were not
    lacking. Indeed, following the rather disappointing first night their
    honeymoon had proved a singular success on all fronts with the exception
    that she had not conceived. They had set out from Gouda to take the train
    down through Germany where they embarked on a Rhine steamer at Koblenz for
    the passage upstream to Mainz through the stunning and romantic scenery of
    the Mittelrhein gorge with its vine-clad slopes and skyline of medieval
    castles . The passage was a slow one but not without charm and periods of
    danger and excitement. Just above Koblenz the steamer encountered a vast
    raft of hundreds of tree trunks being swept downstream towards its
    destination at Andernach where it was to be separated into batches for
    dispersal all across the north of europe. Even such an experienced sailor
    as Johan was taken aback by this enormous platform of timber so vast that
    the hundreds of men required to navigate it had built a village of huts on
    top of it to shelter them on their long journey north from the upper
    reaches of the great river. The pilot of the steamer had a delicate task
    to peform in order to avoid the timber raft, which had very little
    steering, whilst keeping his ship in the narrow channel cut through the
    sharp rocks of the river bed.</para>

    <para>No sooner was the encounter with the raft safely behind them than
    they had cause to marvel again at the pilot's skill as he threaded the
    steamer between the many barges transporting their cargoes up and down the
    river. Only a small proportion of these commercial vessels were powered by
    steam so those under sail on the downstrem run wove and tacked across
    their path, bourne down upon the current. Going their way, steam tugs with
    their lengthy tows of barges crept upstream impeding the progress of the
    faster passenger ship, itself battling upstream against the strong
    current. The dogged pounding of the steam engine found its echo in the
    progress of Paulina and Johan's physical relationship as they persevered
    with the consumation of their union. The strain on their relationship at
    last relieved during an overnight stop at Sankt Goar, they were able to
    enjoy being on deck the next day to admire the Lorelei rock around which
    the river was forced into a trecherously sharp bend causing notoriously
    dangerous whirlpools. Soon after this excitement they came upon the
    Pfalzgrafenstein castle moored out in the river like ship of stone whose
    purpose had been to exact tolls from river users until just two years
    previously. They joined in with the spontaneous cheer that went up from
    the passengers as the note fo the ships' engine relaxed once a line from a
    hauling engine on the bank had been attached to pull them up through the
    rapids to their next halt at Bingen.</para>

    <para>They finally quitted the Rhine steamer at Mainz to travel on by
    stagecoach to Metz . This soon brought them into the still disputed border
    between Germany and France following the recent Franco-Prussian War whose
    legacy of refugees and the grim evidence of military action was
    distressing to Paulina creating the need for the comfort of Johan's arms
    at night. Moving into more peaceful territory, they took time to enjoy the
    French coutryside as well as the cities of Nancy, Langres and Dijon before
    arriving at Lyon where they embarked on another river steamer, this time
    going with the current of the river Rhone which carried them south through
    Arles and the Camargue to the Medditterranean. The season was now turning
    from summer to autumn and they were glad to be journeying into warmer
    southern climes where the freezing of the rivers would arrive somewhat
    later than at home.</para>

    <para>Their passage down the Rhone was quite unlike their earlier Rhine
    trip. This time it was the speed of the river that made it thrilling,
    compounded by the ever-preesent risk of running aground as a dry summer
    had reduced water levels. Although the steam vessels on the Rhone could
    make the trip from Lyon to Arles in a day, Johan had arranged for them to
    break their journey at Vienne to see the Roman buildings and at Avignon
    for the Palace that was once the seat of Popes. Johan had booked a cabin
    for the leg of their voyage between these two stops feeling that because
    the evenings were lengthening towards winter they would appreciate having
    somewhere to retire to for the evening.</para>

    <para>After embarking again at Vienne Paulina and Johan went out on deck
    to enjoy the warmth of a sunny autumn afternoon as the ship gathered speed
    towards the looping curves in the river at Les Roches de Condrieu. Caught
    up on the fast flowing current as she took the outside of the tightest
    bend it seemed as though the ship was being swept out of control to only
    avoided coliding with the right bank butress of the bridge by dint of good
    fortune. Paulina clung to Johan as she felt the danger mounting and was
    surprised to find that, beneath his calm exterior, she could sense that
    he, too, was excited and thrilled. No word needed to be spoken as they
    made their hurried towards their cabin and, once inside, made haste to
    assist eachother out of the layers of clothing put on against the chill
    river airs. Buttons, ties and all manner of fastenings were dealt with as
    sleeves, skirts, trousers and linnen undergarments were made to obey the
    force of gravity with embarrassment now giving way to laughter and
    boisterous delight. They tumbled together in a tangle of strange bedding
    within the narrow confines of their box-like bunk until both were
    exhausted and completely sated. They had fallen into a serene doze when
    the steward knocked on the door to inform that dinner was soon to be
    served, causing them to realize that they were parched and
    ravenous.</para>

    <para>They emerged on deck to the sad sight of the scoured vinyards
    following the devastating phylloxera infection which had its origins at
    Roquemaure a little to the north of Avignon which Paulina later took to be
    a portent of her own barrenness. The warmth of the Medditterranen creeps
    up the Rhone valley to temper the climate of Avignon and kept the
    passionate connection she had found with Johan alive. This honeymoon
    spirit lasted all through their time at Arles but, by the time that they
    turned north to climb up into the mountains to Gap, Grenoble, Annecy then
    into Switzerland, she knew that she had not conceived. Hope and longing
    cooled with the mountain air and the arrival of October. The change of
    landscape, archtiecture and a whole way of life mirrored the calming and
    cooling between Paulina and Johan as intensity and heat gave way to less
    sensual and more regulated emotions.</para>

    <para>With Johan at her side she was able to recapture her facsination for
    the flora and fauna of the mountains which had had such a profound effect
    on her during her first visit in 1865. Together they admired the glaciers
    in the Swiss Alps, especially the vast Rhone glacier at Valais and gazed
    out over Lake Geneva from the balcony of their hotel room in Lausanne.
    Feeling the majesty of the towering mountains and fathomless water and
    ice. Then it was time to make the last leg of their journey back to Den
    Haag through the familar territory of Germany and The Netherlands to the
    anti-climax of a house that was serviceable but still required some work
    to bring it up to scratch and the realities of day to day married
    life.</para>

    <para>Now, more than a year on, they had become accustomed to inhabiting a
    house that still wanted for its final polish and to their relationship
    which had settled down to the comfort of the habitual. Yet, there were
    times when they were undeniably at odds with eachother in some way which
    neither of them seemed able to fathom or put right. Whilst Paulina's mind
    could accept that Johan was free to continue his own life just as she was
    still continuing her own occupations and activities just as before their
    marriage, there were times when her head could not rule her sensibilities.
    She had come to associate her periods of discomfort with the glimpses she
    would catch of a strange man who seemed to appear as if out of thin air
    and disappear again just as mysteriously. This man had the effect of
    causing Johan to immediately order his bags packed for travelling,
    pleading business interets that urgently required his presence. He would
    leave without giving any indication of where he was going or how long he
    expected to be away. Sometimes he returned quickly but occasionally he was
    away for some weeks with no word being sent to her and no means of her
    being able to contact him. On his return her never spoke of where he had
    been, who he had seen, what he had done or why he had been gone yet he was
    evidently glad to see her and resumed their intimacy with some
    urgency.</para>

    <para/>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title/>

    <para>Paulina found herself prey to feelings of boredom and malaise on
    being left alone in the house during Johan's unpredictable and secretive
    absences. As a seasoned letter writer she longed for a correspondence with
    Johan such as she had enjoyed during their brief courtship, at first
    continuing to write him letters that were destined to languish unsent in
    her bureau drawer. Eventually she gave up this abortive attempt at
    correspondence only to fall prey to a need to find some plank of certainty
    to support her across the void between them. On one particularly grey and
    empty afternoon she found herself loitering outside the door to Johan's
    rooms. Although she knew that she was alone in the house which, in any
    case, she was mistress of, Paulina still had to struggle against the idea
    that trespassing on Johan's private affairs would somehow cojour up
    someone on the other side of the door who would catch her in the
    act.</para>

    <para>Suddenly she was in Johan's drawing room with her back to the door
    she had hastily but quietly closed behind her. listening intently for any
    disturbance to the silence of the empty house. She had been in this room
    often so now her eyes roved around it looking for what was new, what was
    missing or any clues to the riddle of his absences. She was well aware of
    the fact that many married men took mistresses but it was painful to think
    that Johan might be straying so soon after marrying, she believed, for
    love and whilst their own passion was not yet spent. Was he was seeing
    another woman or even, and this was an excrutiating thought, did he have a
    family hidden away somewhere? Of course, she would have to turn a blind
    eye, before which she would need to know what it was she must not
    see.</para>

    <para>The first time Paulina entered Johan's rooms she did not dare to
    make more than a cursory inspection of his personal items, not caring to
    attribute to herself the judgement she would have passed had she caught
    someone else prying into his privacy. However, as her visits became an
    established habit so the voice of the moral other gradually quieted, a
    danger repeated assuming the safety of a commonplace. She began by looking
    inside drawers and cupboards, then would remove and inspect their
    contents. Eventually, she crossed the line between curiosoty and
    investigation so that the more hidden the item the greater the frisson
    gained by removing, inspecting then replacing things exactly as she found
    them. She read every paper she could unearth however trivial until it was
    unclear whether the challenge of spying had suplanted the need for
    certainty in driving her on.</para>

    <para>In any case, what she found made no sense. Sometimes his naval
    things were missing and she felt secure in the belief that he was at sea
    until it occured to her that his life mght be in danger. At other times,
    nothing seemed to have been taken apart from the bare minimum required by
    a gentleman on the move. His papers mostly referred to business dealings
    which her sharp mind for such matters told her were all above board and in
    good order. Such items of personal correspondence as he appeared to have
    kept mostly related to exchanges of letters with his brother, her father
    and, reassuringly, herself. Not a hint of anything that she could latch
    onto for an explanation for where her husband was or what he was
    doing.</para>

    <para>Then, out of the blue, something intruiging to her came along, not
    through her snooping, but in the post. She found a letter addressed to
    Johan mixed up with her own letters on the silver post tray brought to her
    by the maid. Usually Johan's correspondence was sorted from hers and left
    on the hall table where Paulina was in the habit of checking for anything
    unexpected when she was sure she was not being observed. On this occasion
    something out of the ordinary had been literally handed to her on a plate.
    She tried to ignore it and attend to her own business but the tiny
    envelope with a Rotterdam postmark drew her attention away from everything
    else. Had the maid left it on purpose? Would the maid see her mistake and
    try to retrieve the letter? Paulina made sure that she kept the stray item
    out of sight whenever she thought she might be disturbed, sneaking looks
    at the envelope whenever her curiosity had to be answered. It seemed a
    long day until the maids went home and Paulina was alone with what had by
    now grown into a great mystery. But how to discover the contents of the
    envelope without detection?</para>

    <para>Remembering that they had a Gazeteer of Rotterdam in the library,
    Paulina fetched it and set about interrogating the postmark for clues as
    to the business of the area from which the letter had been dispatched.
    From what she could gather, the district around the post office indicated
    was comprised mainly of the residences of professional people some of whom
    had their business rooms as well as domestic quarters at the same address.
    She looked at the writing on the envelope for signs of a legal hand, for
    example. Oh, but what did she know of such things! Next she tried to match
    the initials on the wax seal with those of the house occupants but this
    produced a list of a dozen possibilities. Among the lawyers, university
    professors, doctors and others on her list one name stood out because it
    alone belonged to a woman.</para>

    <para>Alone and with no occupation to distract her and nothing else to
    give her mind exercise, Paulina began to torment herself with visions of
    Johan in the arms of this unknown woman. As night's dark silence spread
    throughout the house she could no longer curb her imagination. It became
    imperative that she should discover the secret inside the envelope. But
    how to break the wax seal? Would it be better to apply heat to melt the
    wax or cold to harden it? Heat might leave tell tale smears of red and
    blunt the original sharpness of the impressed initials. Cold could only
    come from the employing ice which might melt and leave water marks unlike
    those naturally left by exposure to rain, and in any case it had been dry
    for several days.</para>

    <para>As Paulina turned the envelope over and over in her hands she
    noticed that the edge of the wax seal was slightly detached. Had someone
    else been tampering with it, she wondered? If so, why? The possibility
    that she was not alone in having an interest in the contents of the
    envelope served to fuel Paulina's desire to open it. She placed it on the
    silver plate again then held this over the flame of a candle, thinking to
    protect the paper from smoke yet soften the bottom of the wax seal just
    enough to be able to remove it. Almost immediately the tray got too hot
    for her to hold comfortably so she had to give up on that approach.</para>

    <para>Then it occured to her that, just as the letter had been delivered
    to her in error, so was it believable that she could have opened it in
    error having unthinkingly failed to check that it was, indeed, addressed
    to her. Paulina was pleased with this idea, and in no small measure
    because it would immediately gratify her curiosity. This plan also had the
    benefit of not requiring her to reassemble the letter or conceal that she
    had opened it. Acting upon the impulse, she broke the seal, opened the
    envelope and soon found herself holding the paper it had been protecting
    in her fingers.</para>

    <para>It took a while for her to comprehend what she was looking at, so
    strong had been her conviction that she would find a lover's note. What
    she struggled to make sense of was that this was not, in fact, a letter
    but an account for services rendered. The amount was quite modest so not
    in itself of any significance to her. What more a source of consternation
    was that the name on the paper's heading was that of a doctor and the
    account was for a consultation and the provision of medicines as
    prescribed. But Johan wasn't ill, she felt sure she would have seen signs
    of it if he had been and that he would have consulted their usual doctor
    in Den Haag. Yet, the account brooked no other interpretation. Johan's
    name and address were on it and whatever ailed him had required immediate
    treatment. The fear of johan's infideltity now seemed trivial in
    comparison to the fear that he might be concealing a grave illness from
    her.</para>

    <para>In an instant Paulina's own health worries paled into
    insignificance. Her failure to conceive had led her to consult any and
    every medical person who might be able to find a cure for her empty womb.
    She had submitted to all sorts of unpleasant examinations that had not
    spared her blushes or her discomfort. She had been made to answer
    questions of a most personal nature concerning her relations with Johan,
    including his performance and its outcome. She had received many
    assurances that there was nothing wrong with her and no reason why she
    should not conceive. Unless, one doctor implied, Johan was at fault. To
    her absolute horror, this doctor made the improper suggestion that he
    might father her a child himself. Needless to say, she never returned to
    that particular person.</para>

    <para>Recently she had heard of a new form of treatment at the Zander
    Clinic that was soon to open in Amsterdam. She had made an appointment to
    see Dr Zander in the hope that he would deem her suitable to become one of
    his patients. To her immense relief she found him less concerned than
    other doctors with the details of her marital relations. Instead, he asked
    a lot of questions about her daily routine her answers to which seemed to
    cause him to nod wisely, although he himself said very little and offered
    no diagnosis.</para>

    <para>Instead, at the end of their interview Dr Zander set out a regime of
    exercises using his range of machines that were designed to be suitable
    for ladies since there was no need to remove clothing or become over
    heated. Dr Zander had explained that his course of treatement would
    strengthen the relevant muscles, and here he was mercifully not explicit,
    necessary for ease of reproduction. She was shown photographs of ladies
    demonstrating the machines, appearing to be comfortably seated inside the
    wooden-framed contraptions which, she was assured, were gentle despite
    their size. It all seemed so sensible and straightforward that she was
    looking forward to starting her treatment and hopeful of its
    efficacy.</para>

    <para>Now her hopes for Dr Zander and his machines were as nothing when
    weighed in the balance against her horror at the kind of serious illness
    that could take away Johan's life. Paulina spent the hours of a sleepless
    night re-living every moment of her life with Johan looking for any signs
    of illness. Then she went over it all again for indications that he had
    been unwell but concealed it from her. Throughout their honeymoon he had
    been almost constantly in her company and gave every sign of being in the
    best of health. Since then, when he was at home he had given every
    appearance of rude health leading her to conclude that if he was
    concealing something then he was taking such great pains about it that it
    had to be a terrible thing. Was this the explanation for his
    absences?</para>

    <para>Why was Johan keeping secrets from her? She understood that his
    naval work might require him to be circumspect in what he divulged.
    Secretly she found the possibility that he went on some sort of important
    and covert missions gave him an added aura of masulinity and importance
    that she found arousing. It pleased her to perpetuate this illusion rather
    than the alternative one of another woman, although she knew that there
    was no sound basis for either interpretation of his absences. Now faced
    with concrete evidence suggesting a third possibilty which did not bode
    well for their future, Paulina found herself completely at a loss as to
    what to think, say or do.</para>

    <para>By opening the letter she had burned her bridges and must now
    confess what she had done to Johan. She could try to convince him that she
    had realised her mistake and not read the letter once opened, but even a
    cursory glance would have been enough to give the game away that Johan had
    been seeing a doctor. There was now no going back from a confrontation
    with him on the matter of his health. Now she needed to formulate a plan
    of what she was going to say to him upon his return home and when the
    right moment to say it might be.</para>

    <para>Johan had returned home just before Christmas but so far Paulina had
    not found the right moment to hand him the doctor's account and to make
    her carefully rehearsed speech to him. At first she had not wanted to
    spoil their delight at reunion, then they had become caught up in the
    celebration of Christmas and a round of social engagements that was now
    culminating in a grand party to give thanks for the year departing and in
    anticipation of all the blessings in the year to come. Yet Paulina felt
    burdened with worries that she had been unable to lighten by sharing and
    which left her feeling alone in the midst of company.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title/>

    <para>It did not escape Marcellus that hiis daughter was somewhat distant
    from the mood of the festive party. An ebullient person himself, he had
    usually been able to lift her out of her tendency to melancholy by the
    generous application of his own good humour. But they had grown apart a
    little since her marriage and she has come to have concerns that were
    private from him. She now found that she was unable to respond to him as
    she once did, which was painful to her as she could see that he was at a
    loss as to how to change his bantering to suit the inevitable shift in
    thie relationship now that she was a married woman. What was more, Paulina
    could tell that Marcellus was distracted by cares of his own that even his
    well-practiced public persona could not conceal from her.</para>

    <para>The source of these cares was not hard to find. There was no getting
    away from the fact that Oma was failing and, looking back on the last
    year, had been increasingly prone to sudden falls although, mercifully,
    she had never injured herself seriously. Yet each time she had taken
    longer to recover from the bumps and bruises, relying more and more on her
    nurses to get through each day. Her mental world had shrunk as much as her
    physical world so that now her attention could only be persuaded to focus
    on her own immediate concerns and a few accounts of past events that were
    worn to word perfection in the repeated telling. Nobody appeared able to
    distract, much less interest her, to the extent that Paulina sometimes
    wondered if Oma really knew who she was any more.</para>

    <para>May God punish her for the thought but old people perish and Paulina
    wished for Oma's end to be soon, swift and easy rather than a long,
    drawn-out decay as the remaining strength of her body fought to keep
    captive the last whisp of a spirit that had already largely departed.
    Surely her father was preparing himself for whatever course Oma's last
    weeks and months might take and the inevitable conclusion. Unless Paulina
    was very much mistaken, her father had something more serious on his mind
    irectly upon their returnthan old Oma's health.</para>

    <para>The reason for her father's disquiet soon became apparent to Paulina
    as she took Johan's arm to follow her parents into the Grote Salon for
    dinner. This was the first time for a long while that she had really
    looked at her mother and was shocked to see how old and worn out she had
    become and how she seemed to need to lean on her father for physical
    support. A great wave of anxiety passed over Paulina as, on top of all her
    other worries, she now understood that there was something amis with hreer
    mother's health. She had been half expecting Oma to be showing signs of
    her mortality but for her mother to be treading the same path did not bear
    thinking about.</para>

    <para>What Marcellus could see and Paulina could not was the toll that
    Paulina's marriage and Oma's decline had taken on Maria's health. Without
    Paulina's constant presence and able assistance the extra work Maria now
    undertook in the management of their business and estate affairs was
    gradually draining her strength. That he had married a woman some years
    his senior who was now herself becoming elderly was making itself evident
    as she tired more easily and seemed to be losing the sharp edge of her
    aptitude and acumen in managing their affairs. Yet she was still as able
    as ever at organising the social events that were such an intergral and
    important part of his political career. But even in this sphere she was
    under added pressure now that his mother's decline was putting her in the
    way of extra work and worry in the management of the household.</para>

    <para>He had lain awake at nights trying to come up with a way to give his
    wife an easier life. Every plan that he had contrived so far had involved
    Paulina's return to he family house. He had entertained the hope that
    giving him a grandchild and heir would rouse in her the sort of familly
    feeling that would make it easier for him to persuade her to come back to
    Haastrecht. Now he was starting to consider what else might prove
    incentive enough to persuade her away from city life in Den Haag. Of
    course, it wasn't just Paulina that he had to take into consideration but
    also Johan, a man whose lifestyle was a mystery to him being so very
    different from anything Marcellus could relate to. He searched his mind
    for anything they might have in common on which to attempt to build an
    alliance. This train of thought at least had the advantage of giving him
    the feeling that there was something he could do to achieve the end he
    desired, even though he did not yet know what it might be.</para>

    <para>Had Paulina but known it, Marcellus had a lift to his shoulders as
    he led the way into dinner as a result of feeling that he had some measure
    of control over the worrying developments in his domestic life. More
    usually of late he had exhibited an air of dejection about his posture
    which would have further upset Paulina had she witnessed it.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title/>

    <para/>

    <para>Before she and Johan left to return to Den Haag Paulina made sure
    that she found an opportunity to speak privately with her father. He did
    not take much persuading to share his anxiety about the state of her
    mother's health and they fell to discussing remedies for the overwork
    which they both thought was at the bottom of her physical decline. Paulina
    quickly pledged to spend more time at Haastrecht in order to relieve her
    mother of as much of her work as she would allow. Johan would understand
    and her romantic steak envisaged that their letters and his visits might
    bring reawaken the internsity of their courtship.</para>

    <para>As well as a permanent lightening of her duties, father and daughter
    also agreed that Maria would need some period of rest and recuperation to
    restore her to her previous state of health. Their discussion moved on to
    how to persuade Maria to take a complete break from her duties, something
    which she was unlikely to do, or be given the peace to do, unless she was
    away from home and and all its demands for a while. They considered which
    of their relatives and friends might be able to give Maria the peace and
    tranquility she would need for her recovery and who she would not mind
    being lodged with. It went against the grain for either of them to think
    of asking a favour of even the closest of relations and they knew that
    Maria would hate to be put in the position of self-invited guest, nomatter
    how weighty the reason behind it. Then Paulina recalled hearing talk of
    the benefits to be gained from visiting the mineral spas in Germany whose
    names all seemed to begin with Bad. Her father greeted this suggestion
    with enthusiasm and undertook to speak to their doctor about which of the
    many cures he would recommend for Maria.</para>

    <para>Directly upon their return to Den Haag Johan and Paulina went to
    their separate quarters to await the announcement of dinner, as had become
    their domestic habit. However, on this occasion Paulina soon came to the
    conclusion that she would have to instigate some sort of discussion with
    her husband about the several matters that were weighing heavily on her
    conscience. The couple were not accustomed to sitting down together for
    the purposes of having a serious conversation about the state of their
    private affairs as a result of which a joint view or mutually agreed
    course of action might emerge. Instead, they each went their own way, as
    Paulina had envisaged they would, only informing each other of what they
    were doing as a matter of courtesy and only when necessary at that. Now
    Paulinia had to overcome her anxious state and find a way to take the
    initiative in engagaing Johan in a conference.</para>

    <para>She sent her maid to set out a tray of drinks in the salon in order
    to tempt Johan into accepting her invitation to join her there. Having
    dispatched her maid with this invitation, Paulina did her best to smooth
    her appearance and cool her head before going to the salon to wait for
    him. Johan found his wife's invitation slightly odd but he did not
    hesitate to rise to what he decided to take at face value as being a
    social approach with the added bonus of alcohol on offer. He arrived at
    the salon to find his wife looking more ill at ease than welcoming.</para>

    <para>Paulina struggled to keep her composure and not show her impatience
    as Johan fussed over glasses, decanters, bottles and cigars whilst making
    easy small talk. At last they were seated either side of the fire place in
    the apparent ease of a settled married couple and Paulina looked for an
    opportunity to shift the ground of their encounter and reveal the motive
    to her invitation. Taking advantage of a lull in Johan's chatter as he lit
    a taper from the fire and applied it to his cigar, Paulina gathered
    herself and began the speech which she had carefully prepared
    beforehand.</para>

    <para>"My dear, there are some matters about which we should have a
    serious discussion. Mainly they concern my mothger's health - and
    yours."</para>

    <para>Her last two word suddenly caught Johan's attention, an expression
    wavering between guilt and bewilderment passing across his face. Without
    pausing to give him a chance to speak, she produced the letter containing
    the doctor's bill from her skirt pocket as she continued;</para>

    <para>"Let us take this latter concern first, then. This letter addressed
    to you found its way among correspondence sent to me and I confess to
    opening it in error, not having read the envelope carefully enough. I find
    its contents rather disturbing."</para>

    <para>Handing the item in question over to its rightful recipient, she
    continued;</para>

    <para>"Disturbing on two counts. First, that you are ill and, second, that
    you have hidden this fact from me."</para>

    <para>Here she deliberately paused to give Johan time to open and read the
    doctor's invoice then come up with a response to her raising of the
    matter. She waited longer than was entirely comfortable as it seemed to
    her that Johan was visibly struggling to compose himself.</para>

    <para>"I am deeply ashamed that you have caught me out in a small
    dishonesty in concealing this from you. But, in my defence, the
    consultation alluded to in this invoice revolved around such a trivial
    ailment that it must have slipped my mind to tell you of it."</para>

    <para>"so, my dear, whatever is the matter that you could not see our own
    doctor?"</para>

    <para>"let me assure you that there is nothing sinister about my action.
    Merely the convenience of going to a doctor well versed in the disorders
    common among memebers of the marine. Something that I contracted during my
    time at sea sometimes threatens to recurr and did so whilst I was visiting
    Gillis so I sought out a medical man I had consulted in the past who is
    familiar with such problems and their treatment. Please be ressured that
    it signifies nothing at all serious or of any danger to you."</para>

    <para>Paulina was a bit thrown by the gravity of his last remark but did
    not question it as she was preoccupied with her own pressing
    concerns.</para>

    <para>"I have to ask: Might it have a connection to our failure to produce
    children, and does it have anything to do with your absences from home
    about which you tell me so little?"</para>

    <para>This double question came as a challenge to Johan, its boldness
    aiming directly at two matters of such a private nature that he found
    himself suddenly off guard and on the defensive. The first question was
    simply too intimate and threatening to his masculinity for him to be able
    to take in, never mind address thoughtfully. The second question defaulted
    as the lesser of two evils but still defied his considered reply. Instead,
    Johan found that he had made a snap decision to trust his wife's
    discretion if he confided in her the reasons for his secretive absences
    with not a little desire that this would distract her from persuing and
    answer to her first, and simpler, question.</para>

    <para>"What I have to tell you must not be divulged or even hinted at to
    another living soul. Before I begin, do you swear to me that you will
    never betray the confidence which I am about to put in your discretion,
    not even to allude to what I am about to tell you when you write in your
    journal?"</para>

    <para>"Oh my goodness! This sounds grave indeed!"</para>

    <para>"Do I have your word?"</para>

    <para>"The swear it!"</para>

    <para>"Johan, you are frightening me!"</para>

    <para>"I have good reason for this. Do you swear secrecy?"</para>

    <para>"Yes, then, I swear on my life that I will keep what you tell me
    hidden inside and not whisper a word of it."</para>

    <para>"Good. I am sorry to upset you but you will soon see why it was
    necessary.</para>

    <para>I am often called away on matters of importance to our country and
    its international affairs. I can give no better illustration than what is
    about to occur. But before I go any further, may I ask if I am correct in
    surmising that you also wish to talk to me about your mother's health and
    your desire to spend a good eal of time in Haastrecht with the aim of
    easing her burden of work?"</para>

    <para>Paulina nodde in assent, realizing that her account of her talk with
    her father which she had given to Johan during their journey home would
    have made him aware of the topic she was hoping to broach with him
    later.</para>

    <para>"I should tell you that I, too, have to be away from home and that
    my business may take some time. You may have heard or read in the
    newspapers that Prussia is likely to defeat France in the current war
    between them. This will result in the unification of all the German states
    creating a lengthy border between us and them. Feeling empowered by their
    success over the Fench, it is feared that their attention may next turn to
    encroaching on our territory.</para>

    <para>As far as my involvement goes, there is a fear that the Prussian
    navy will make an incursion into the Friesian Islands and threaten our
    trade routes to the Zuiderzee and north coat ports, perhaps even beyond.
    As we speak, I am awaiting a summons to join the Dutch fleet bound for the
    waters off Denmark."</para>

    <para>Paulina interrupted with a question she just had to know the answer
    to;</para>

    <para>"Will the summons come in the shape of that peculiar little man I
    catch sight of fromn time to time? He never looks the same twice running
    but you alwaysnseem to go away just after I glimpse him."</para>

    <para>"Yes. he is an agent of the Rpyal Family and usually so discrete as
    to barely visible. It was extraordinarily observant of you to notice him
    and clever of you to connect him with my departures."</para>

    <para>"Johan, I have been so anxious about what clandestine purposes lie
    beneath these brief desertions that I have become extremely vigilant for
    any sugns that might point to an explanation of what is going on."</para>

    <para>"Such as a letter? Or going through my things?"</para>

    <para>Now it was Paulina's turn to feel embarrassed.</para>

    <para>"Oh, my love, please do not concern yourself! It isflattering and
    reassuring that you still care so much since our marriage has had its
    disappointments for you, I know. I admire your initiative in spying on me
    and your bravery in confronting me today. I like you the better for
    it."</para>

    <para>There was a brief lull in their talk as each adjusted their
    understanding of the other and took in the shift to a more open basis to
    their relationship now that things had been said which were previously
    left unsaid. Johan took a long draught of his drink and a pull on his
    cigar as he ordered his thoughts and considered how best to
    continue.</para>

    <para>"I have a special talent which the marine has serious need of.
    Although I left the service some time ago, I am honour bound to answer the
    King's call whenever it comes. This is how I remain entitled to still wear
    my uniform whenever I so choose.</para>

    <para>Oh, don't look so surprised, my dear. I know that I must seem a dull
    wit when held up to the men in your family, but I am not totally lacking
    in intellect. I have a gift with maps: reading them, interpreting the land
    and sea scape depicted by them and for making maps which others can easily
    comprehend. This is of strategic importnace for the defence of our country
    and for the conduct of international affairs.</para>

    <para>My next mission will involve me in a detailed survey and mapping of
    the area at risk from the Prussian navy. The aim is to determine where a
    fleet might penetrate our defences, where a ship might hide itself close
    to land, where a boat might land a spy or armed forces, and so on. My
    cartography is needed in these matters and is of importance in deciding
    how we might deploy our own forces defensively."</para>

    <para>Paulina hardly dare ask the obvious question;</para>

    <para>"Will you be in danger?"</para>

    <para>Johan paused before answering, briefly pondering how truthful he
    should be, not wanting to worry Paulina then realizing that she would
    worry nomatter how he played down the risk.</para>

    <para>"I will be honest with you, my love. Yes, there will be some danger
    involved over and above the usual perils of the sea. As I said, there is a
    war and both Prussia and France have their spies about who will use force
    against anyone seen as thwarting their efforts at gaining advantage. There
    is always a chance that we will run into trouble despite our best efforts
    to be clandestine and cautious. I am not a reckless man so I shall be as
    careful of myself as is consistent with achieving the desired
    ends."</para>

    <para>"And will this work require you to be away from home for
    long?"</para>

    <para>"Again, I'm afraid that I must answer in the affirmative. There is a
    lot of coast and sea to map with many islands, sandbanks and complex tide
    lines to be accurately rendered. Some of these are subject to alteration
    by the action of the sea so will need to be charted again and again to
    maintain accuracy. Our mission also involved reporting on any unusual
    vessels or activity, which will also keep us at sea for long periods. You
    will by now appreciate that all of this means that I shall be unable to
    send word to you or receive any of your dear letters.</para>

    <para>So, it is for the best that you go to Haastrecht where you will be
    occupied and thus somewhat distracted from concerns about me. You will
    have the comfort and support of your family and friends ad the
    satisfaction of knowing that you are doing all you can for Maria and
    Oma."</para>

    <para>A rapid succession of thoughts and feelings swept through Paulina as
    she grappled with a new understanding of her husband and an altered
    appreciation of her marriage. Now that Johan had explained everything she
    found that she felt less rather than more anxious. Now that her suspicions
    about his infidelity had been laid to rest she felt a sense of relief that
    their marriage was not under threat. More than that, she found her
    feelings for her husband were strenghthening now thathe was turning ouit
    to be a gifted man who was engaged in important work in the service of
    their King and country. It must be admitted that her pride in being his
    wife was starting to tarnish as he had every appearance of lacking any
    occupation. Being raised to hard work as a duty it had been hard for not
    to think less of him for his seeming idleness. She was overcome by a
    sudden rush of love and desire for him that reminded her of their
    courtship and the best parts of their honeymoon.</para>

    <para>Johan, of course, discerned the subtle alteration in his wife which
    signalled the re-awakening of her desire. He rose and fetched her a small
    glass of the red vermouth she had a afondness for, taking the opportunity
    to lean close to her as he handed her the drink. He rested his hand
    lightly on her shoulder for a few seconds, laying the groundwork for later
    intimacies.</para>

    <para>The tie for deep conversations thus reached its conclusion without
    further concerns surfacing. Paulina would have liked to return to the
    theme of their childlessness but feared that crossing the bounds of
    delicacy, even between husband and wife, might destroy the atmosphere of
    closeness which had developed between them during the course of the
    evening. The prospect of a prolonged separation, entailing Johan's absence
    from her bed, was setback enough to her hopes of motherhood, although she
    knew that this could not be helped.</para>

    <para>On Johan's part, he was all too willing to let the subject of his
    medical situation drop. It had given him a nasty moment when Paulina
    produced the doctor's bill and he had had to think on his feet to come up
    with some sort of plausible explanation for it. He hadn't exactly lied in
    what he had said, but he hadn't been entirely honest either. But, a risk
    of discovery past is a risk forgotten so his mind focussed on managing a
    smooth progress towards bedding Paulina.</para>

    <para/>

    <para/>
  </section>
</chapter>
