<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd">
<chapter version="5.0" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
  <title>Summer 1876</title>

  <section>

    <para>Theodorus and Cornelis were going at each other hammer and tongues,
    oblivious to the audience they were attracting. The new batch of workmen
    who had been taken on in an effort to speed things up were looking on with
    some anxiety, somehow intuiting that they were the focus of the
    disagreement and hoping that it was not going to lead to their dismissal
    with the consequent return to poverty and idleness. The old hands,
    however, just shrugged and rolled their eyes, barely pausing in their
    work. The tension between the two bosses had been building for some time
    culminating in a storm that would blow itself out before the end of the
    day. No need to worry, they advised the new men, just get on with your
    tasks.</para>

    <para>It was, indeed, the arrival of the gang of new workers which had
    been the catalyst for the rather public venting of anger by the two
    overseers. They and their attendant problems were not the direct cause but
    consequent upon the approaching deadline for completion of the house which
    had been imposed by the <emphasis>burgermeester</emphasis>. Marcellus
    Bisdom van Vliet had his heart, and his <emphasis>gilders</emphasis>, set
    on being able to celebrate his 50 year anniversary as
    <emphasis>Burgermeester</emphasis> of Haastrecht from the new house which
    had been commissioned specially for this occasion. The whole village had
    involved themselves in grand plans to honour him, suddenly making concrete
    the date by which the house should be finished.</para>

    <para>August 23rd - and there was such a lot left to do!</para>

    <para>Much had been accomplished so far. Once the old house had been
    raised to its foundations, these had needed strengthening with new
    brickwork onto which the heavy timbers for the floor joists had been laid.
    Once the shell of the house had been built using thousands upon thousands
    of bricks it was time for the hard work of lifting and fitting the roof
    beams and trusses. The complex structure and area of the upper floor of
    the house made for a cats cradle of necessary wooden supporting structure
    which would be strong enough to take the Fries flat pan tiles of the roof.
    Meanwhile windows and doors were created and installed so that the
    building was weather proof and the interior work could begin.</para>

    <para>All of the heavy construction materials had to be brought along the
    river by barge. The craft were sized to fit the confines of the waterways
    they operated on and were each crewed by a single family who lived on
    board. To maximize cargo space the living quarters were squeezed into the
    stern with cooking, eating, washing and sleeping all vying for space.
    Boards laid across the space served as beds and had to be taken away
    before the day's domestic activities could begin. Families with many
    children crowded together so disease was rife, as was malnutrition as
    parents struggled to fill mouths on their meagre income. Yet more babies
    easily came along but many died before they were old enough to walk. It
    had not been unusual to see the wife harnessed to a line ashore pulling
    the laden barge whilst her husband, worn out by the effort of lading and
    unloading cargo, stayed on board and steered from the tiller at the stern.
    Wind and current were not always favourable to these folk and horse power
    often beyond their means. These were weatherbeaten and hard-muscled folk,
    old before their time with lives often prematurely ended by illnesses
    which the doctors were too busy to diagnose or treat, scrawling the word
    "exhaustion" when registering their death.</para>

    <para>At least the carters who then brought the finer timber for interior
    work and all the necessaries for plasterwork and decorative finishes could
    go home to a roof over their heads, however mean a hovel they called home.
    They worked their horses hard but Paulina, who had a strong interest in
    matter equine, made sure that the animals were not ill treated or
    underfed. Some said that she showed more care for the welfare of the
    horses than their handlers.</para>

    <para>Since Theodorus could not manage the building work and do the
    plasterwork himself, he had engaged FPC Schild to undertake the massive
    amount of skilled work in plastering the ceilings and all the decorative
    plasterwork of the interior. Herein lay the source of the argument between
    Theodorus and Cornelis. The plasterwork was falling behind schedule
    because other work, which needed to be done first, had not been completed.
    Hence the influx of new workers. However, both Theodorus and Cornelis had
    laid claim to these men and set them on competing tasks. Given the tense
    atmosphere created by time pressure, it was perhaps understandable that
    the conflict erupted into an angry exchange. Once some steam had been let
    off, both men were able to regain their usual level headedness and their
    usually excellent working relationship was able to reassert itself so that
    the next time men looked in their direction they saw the tow men briefly
    embracing each other then shaking hands with smiles on their faces.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title/>

    <para>Theodrus and Cornelis shut themselves up in the makeshift office and
    let it be known that they were only to be disturbed in case of dire
    emergency. Any knocks on the door or timid calls were ignored. Their
    agreed strategy was to take an imaginary walk through the house, compiling
    lists of unfinished work in each room as they went. They also had a draft
    of the plans for the day of Marcellus's 50th anniversaryas burgermeester
    celebrations.</para>

    <para>The obvious place to start was with the ingang/entrance and
    vestibule which it led into. Placed in the centre of the the six bays on
    the ground floor, the large, sturdy wooden door was already in place.
    Although it opened as a single door, a central column decorated with vines
    and grapes gave the impression of double doors. Symmetrical panels were
    glazed and decorated with wrought ironwork. Above and below each inset
    glass were carved panels, oblong below and circular bosses topped with
    semi-circular arches above. The rich colour of the wood and the
    multi-faceted carving were pleasing to the eye and the whole was sturdy
    and clearly designed to offer protection to the valuable contents which
    would eventually be contained within. Cornelis was proud of it and
    Theodorus thought this was rightly so.</para>

    <para>But, they couldn't linger in admiration as there was a long way to
    go and both agreed that the impressive entry needed no improvement. Once
    inside the door. An entrance hall led up to the doorway into the inner
    hall or gang at the end with a door leading off either side to a small
    salon on the left and a reception area on the right. In order to create
    symmetry, two false doors, one either side, had been created with a
    central bay of plasterwork between them. Since this was the first
    impression visitors, not to mention Marcellus, would have it needed to
    show how important and wealthy the occupants of the house were. The
    decoration of the vestibule was, therefore, designed to provide an opulent
    impression but only as a backdrop for the displays of valuable items and
    family crests destined to be placed there. So, whilst the ceiling rose,
    cornicing and the headers above the doors involved complex plaster
    mouldings which had been delicately painted in muted creams, the central
    panels were relatively plain with a touch of blue in places to set off the
    blue of the Chinese plates destined to be hung nearby. A marble floor
    provided the finishing touch to this relatively small but hugely important
    space. </para>

    <para>The first room off the vestibule was the speekkamer or reception
    room. This would be where the maid who answered the door would take
    visitors to wait whilst she conveyed messages to and fro the occupants of
    the house. Tradespeople would wait here to be paid and more important
    callers to be admitted to the grote salon through the far door. A
    relatively plain room, then. Even so, it was yet to be finished as the
    expensive red flock wallpaper from England, chosen as a foil for the gilt
    framed paintings destined to be displayed against it, remained to be hung.
    Again, concerns about keeping the decoration clean came to the surface as
    flock wallpaper was notorious for attracting dirt. Since the guests
    admitted to the house for Marcellus's celebration were by invitation only,
    it was agreed that the completion of this room could be assigned a low
    priority.</para>

    <para>The same could not be said of the kleine salon through the second
    door off the vestibule. This was where Marcellus planned greet his guests
    and provide refreshments. </para>

    <para>Again, all the work had been done but the challenge was to keep it
    in pristine condition despite the mess being created by work in progress
    in the rest of the house. Use of the front door had been banned with
    everything and everyone coming in through the kitchen and garden room
    entrances. The doorway at the end of the vestibule marked the transition
    from the public to the private areas of the house and, to mark the
    importance of this, had been built to double thickness to accommodate two
    doors,one after the other. To create a further barrier, provision had been
    made for a heavy curtain to span the width of the wall at the end of the
    vestibule. A temporary curtain had been hung here then both doors closed
    with the door on the family side sealed.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title/>

    <para/>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title/>

    <para/>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title/>

    <para/>
  </section>
</chapter>
