<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd">
<chapter version="5.0" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
  <title>Vroeg August 1869</title>

  <section>
    <para>Johan was enjoying himself hugely. If he had been the sort of man to
    reflect on life then it would have come as a surprise to him that he was
    so pleasurably engrossed in his courtship of Paulina Maria. But he was not
    that sort of man so spared not a second on such thoughts. Instead, he gave
    himself up to the feeling of exhilaration that was the nearest he had ever
    got on land to those times at sea when the ship was creaming along on a
    running sea, sails full and it was his hands on the wheel.</para>

    <para>To begin with he had been a reluctant suitor, already set in his
    bachelor ways at the age of twenty eight. Feeling himself firmly steered
    by both families onto his present course his independent spirit threatened
    to rebel, to fight against their control, with the inevitable result that
    the whole enterprise would have foundered. Disaster was averted, however,
    when the warm winds of flattery swelled his ego and he came round to his
    present and surprisingly comfortable heading. The realisation that he was
    deemed worthy to have his name associated with that of Marcellus Bisdom
    van Vliet, a man whose social stature and good name in business were
    recognise the length of all the Great Rivers, puffed up his pride by
    virtue of association.</para>

    <para>Yet there was more to this change of tack in his courtship of
    Paulina Maria than could be accounted for by mere flattery. Something in
    her response to his attentions spoke directly to a need deep within him,
    although he could not have said what this was. He had simply been going
    through social motions of courtship until a means of extricating himself
    presented itself, but Paulina Maria had been so receptive, so open and so
    guileless in her reception of him that he had been quite won over by her.
    Her obvious delight at everything he said and did drew him to her in
    anticipation of an unbounded and uncritical love such as he had not
    experienced since he was a boy at his mother's knee. That first feeling of
    being loved so completely had ended abruptly upon the birth of his sickly
    younger brother who survived to distract their mother with the burden of
    his care. The untimely death of his father left her an impoverished widow
    struggling to bring up three sons in a manner which befitted their station
    in life. She had precious little emotional energy left for her needy
    second child who was dispatched to school in Hilversum and then into the
    Marine as soon as possible. Only now was that unacknowledged abandoned
    child within the adult Johan awakened to bask in the glow of the generous
    outpouring of adoration lavished upon him by Paulina Maria.</para>

    <para>There had been a lot of women passing through his life since Johan
    entered the Marine as a youth but the pleasures of their company had
    rarely left any lasting impression on him. If he had ever been drawn back
    to any of them it could largely be accounted for by the ease of their
    virtue. Indeed, one of the more pleasant aspects of his residence at the
    Hotel De Zalm was the sweet and available maid-of-all-work who was willing
    to help him unmake his bed in return for the small change he left for her
    on the dresser. But nothing had ever recaptured for him that feeling of
    being loved and wanted without qualification or demands that he had lost
    so early in his life. Until now, that is, and with this most unlikely of
    women who held no more physical attraction for him that which was solely
    due to her sex.</para>

    <para>Again, if he had been a man to ponder such things, Johan would have
    been amazed at himself for the longing he felt for Paulina Maria's
    company. Such was the soothing quality of his time spent with her that,
    had he been able to name the emotion felt upon parting from her, he would
    have called it grief. Paulina Maria never left him to suffer the agony of
    loss for long, however, as she sent him a continuous stream of long
    letters to which he eagerly responded. He often enclosed a new photograph
    of himself in his uniform as he knew this would please her and draw forth
    favourable comments in her next correspondence.</para>

    <para>Thus it was with a glad heart that he viewed the prospect of
    spending several days in her company at the Bisdom van Vliet house in
    Haastrecht. He had arrived on the first Thursday in August to find that
    Marcellus was away from home and not expected back until dinner time the
    next day. Maria Elizabeth was, as usual, much taken up with the affairs of
    the family's local properties and village interests. Paulina Maria
    normally helped her mother with these tasks but had been released from
    most of her duties in order to entertain their guest. The only call on her
    time was the management of the household during Johan's visit, which she
    said it was her pleasure to perform.</para>

    <para>The weather was good on that first afternoon so he spent several
    happy hours with Paulina Maria on his arm as they wandered through the
    <emphasis>overtuin</emphasis> across the lane from the house. They admired
    the new planting which had been done, held imaginary conversations with
    the impressive statues of Hercules and Neptune beside the lake, fancied
    themselves explorers discovering the grotto on its island, then paused to
    look at their reflections in the water and admire the view over the farms
    to the windmills along the Vlist. Turning back towards the house, they
    peeped in at the indoor plants being propagated in orangery but found it
    much to hot and steamy inside to linger there for long.</para>

    <para>They cooled down by taking cordials with Oma under the shade of the
    old copper beech tree in the formal garden behind the house. The old lady,
    now in her eighty-fourth year, had developed a tremor and Johan watched
    tenderly as Paulina Maria helped the old lady to drink from her cup
    without spills. Despite this physical sign of her advanced age, Oma seemed
    keen to show an interest in him and soon got him telling stories about his
    naval exploits. When the couple rose to leave Oma took advantage the
    social <emphasis>largesse</emphasis> granted to those of advanced years
    when delivering her parting shot to the couple,</para>

    <para>"Now don't leave it too long, will you? We need children to keep the
    family going!"</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title/>

    <para>As he lay alone in the old-fashioned cupboard bed in his room in the
    <emphasis>familiehuis</emphasis>, old Oma's words came back into Johan's
    head. Up to this point he had only been dimly aware of the connection
    between courtship and marriage, having taken more notice of scandalous
    relationships than the more conventional ones. His courtship of Paulina
    Maria seemed to be a thing in and of itself its destination lost on the
    hazy horizon of the future. Suddenly the mists cleared and he saw with
    crystal clarity that everyone expected him to marry her and father her
    children.</para>

    <para>Gilles had laid out clearly for him the expected progression from
    first meetings to formal application to pay court followed by the
    courtship itself leading up to the making of an offer of marriage. The
    actual goal of being married had, however, remained vague. Johan
    understood that a wedding marked the transition from the groom being an
    unattached bachelor to being a husband bound to one woman for life.
    Perhaps Gilles had rashly assumed that his brother comprehended the state
    of matrimony as well as he did himself, especially as Johan was a frequent
    visitor to Gilles and Maria's home where he could directly observe the
    well-regulated conduct of married life taking place. It might have
    appeared that no further elaboration of the duties and obligations
    involved in being a husband and father was required.</para>

    <para>Thus it was that without a trace of hesitation or doubt Johan
    decided that, yes, he could live permanently with the way Paulina Maria
    made him feel! More than that, he could no longer contemplate life without
    her, the very thought of which now made him rather panic-stricken. Having
    reached the conclusion that he wanted her for his wife, Johan's certainty
    about her feelings for him suddenly began to slowly ebb away allowing the
    reefs of his insecurity to emerge. He drew comfort from the agony of
    uncertainty by snuggling down into a nest of soft mattress, feather
    pillows and voluminous covers. He resolved to ask for her hand as soon as
    an opportunity arose, before she had time to cool towards him. Yes, that
    is what he must do!</para>

    <para>Having resolved on taking this course, Johan's thoughts moved on to
    the topic of children. The connection between sex and unwanted pregnancy,
    not to mention certain unmentionable diseases, had long been familiar to
    him. The link between marriage, sex and the inevitability, and even
    desirability, of procreation was something new for him to contemplate. Now
    he began to toss around the notion of sex for insemination rather than
    simply for pleasure and relief. He began to try to imagine what it would
    be like having conjugal relations with Paulina Maria. It was difficult for
    him to think of her in that way but Oma had made it clear for him that he
    was to stand stallion for the Bisdom van Vliet blood line. He exercised
    his highly developed libidinous faculties to conjure up a vision of what
    lay beneath the chaste layers of Paulina Maria's clothing. He anticipated
    the feel of her naked breasts under his hands, finding them just as he
    liked breasts to be, large yet firm. His member, already tingling
    pleasurably, now stiffened as his imaginings shifted to the warm, moist
    cleft between her legs which promised to welcome him inside. Now
    thoroughly aroused but with no opportunity for casual female company, he
    had no other recourse than to seek the seaman's release.</para>

    <para>Waking sometime later he climbed down from his bed, put on his
    dressing gown and slippers then went in search of the night servant to ask
    for brandy and a cigar to be brought to him. Thus provided for he settled
    into an arm chair set before the open window and shutters. Johan tried
    again to focus his thoughts on marriage and paternity as the night air
    cooled his feverish imagination. He might have reflected upon the
    suffering he witnessed as his parents buried yet another small coffin in
    the Oude Tonge churchyard. Or recalled the distress of his brother,
    Gilles, who could only wait impotently as Maria screamed for a whole night
    and most of the following day to bring his namesake into the world. Or he
    might have brought to mind the young life of his vibrant cousin,
    Elisabeth, cut short in childbirth. As it was he reflected on none of
    these sad events, nor did his lips form a smile at the recollection of the
    joy children could also bring.</para>

    <para>What actually came to his mind was the comforting thought of how
    little the arrival of young Johan Jacob had altered Gillis's daily life.
    He was still able to go about his affairs and travel from home without
    hindrance. His prospective father-in-law was also a re-assuring case in
    point, being hardly ever at home, or so it seemed. Johan would have been
    loathe to curtail his activities for the sake of any child he might
    father, finding it difficult to rest in any one place for long. His
    resolve to marry Paulina Maria would have wavered had he felt his freedom
    of movement might be in any way curtailed. Johan was thus able to
    re-assure himself that he was not about to give up his liberty in any real
    sense but, rather, was about to gain a secure emotional future and a ready
    supply of sex whilst placing himself in an advantageous social position
    into the bargain. Becoming fuddled with alcohol and tiredness, he burrowed
    back into the surprisingly comfortable old bed and was soon snoring fit to
    raise the roof.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title/>

    <para>The following day dawned fine and warm, offering Johan the prospect
    of again spending much of it out of doors, as was his preference. He
    missed being on board ship, if not the discipline of life at sea. The day
    was especially full of promise as he was to have Paulina Maria to himself
    for several hours before they would be obliged to join her parents and Oma
    for a family meal. Paulina Maria had appeared at breakfast wearing a light
    gown with a rather lower neckline than was usual for her. The flimsy dress
    in combination with the sheer, almost transparent, fabric of the modesty
    scarf which covered the gap from <emphasis>decolletage</emphasis> to neck
    was enticingly suggestive of the ample bosom beneath, a choice of attire
    which he regrettably attributed entirely to the hot weather and not at all
    to a desire to raise any passion in him.</para>

    <para>Once their coffee and bread had been taken, Paulina Maria announced
    that she wanted him to accompany her to the stables in order to inspect
    the new carriage horse that had been her birthday gift from her parents.
    She suggested that afterwards they might have the horse harnessed to the
    <emphasis>sjees</emphasis> and take a drive along the dyke-top to the
    village of Willige Langerak on the banks of the River Lek. It soon became
    clear to him that horses and horse-drawn transport was a keen interest of
    hers, but unfortunately one that he did not share.</para>

    <para>Perhaps conditioned by his father's ill-humoured old nag, Johan had
    grown up distrustful of horses, finding them alarmingly large, powerful
    and unpredictable. The movement of their gangling legs made his feet ache
    at the very thought of them getting caught between iron-shod hoof and hard
    earth. Their strong jaws and massive teeth threatened to wreak havoc with
    his flesh as their long necks seemed able to rotate their huge heads in
    every conceivable direction, offering little hope of escape. He fancied
    that their bulging eyes followed his every move with nothing but evil
    intent in them, especially when the whites showed. Altogether, he regarded
    the horse as a beast of wilful malevolence which he could not believe
    capable of human subjugation and was thankful that they had no place at
    sea.</para>

    <para>With Paulina Maria's firm grip on his arm, Johan found himself
    propelled towards the stables at a pace which brooked no hesitation.
    Fortunately for the course of their courtship, his equine anxieties soon
    evaporated with the moral heat created by the motion of Paulina Maria's
    breasts which were thrust upwards by her corset and barely concealed by
    the flimsiest of summer fabrics. Not only could he snatch surreptitious
    glimpses of her magnificent <emphasis>decolletage</emphasis> but he could
    also relish the sensation of an occasional brush of clothed breast against
    his upper arm, not to mention the insinuation of a sturdy thigh against
    his as she strode along beside him despite the thickness of her horsehair
    petticoats . All in all he found himself rendered incapable of uttering
    anything coherent, let alone negative, on the subject of horses, being so
    distracted that he could barely follow the thread of her bright chatter.
    In his not trivial experience of women he had learnt that they were all
    too aware of the physical signals they were sending through these slight
    contacts and glimpses of barely concealed flesh. To his delight, Johan
    took Paulina Maria to be flirting with him sexually!</para>

    <para>Once they had arrived at the stables Paulina Maria bade the head
    ostler lead out her new horse. Emerging from the gloom of her stall, the
    animal started at the brightness of the external world causing Johan's
    heart to lurch. The ostler soon calmed the mare with soft words and a
    gentle hand then began to lead her up and down the yard for the admiration
    of her visitors. The animal's coat gleamed in the sunshine, emphasising
    the toned muscles that underlay her supple movements. The delicate way in
    which she placed her feet and her responsiveness to the lightest touch
    from the ostler began to entrance Johan. A tattoo beat out from the man's
    clogs and the beast's iron shoes striking the cobbled ground as the mare
    was put through her paces: walking, turning, trotting and turning to walk
    past them again. Johan began to be mesmerised by the sounds, by the
    oneness of man and mare, and by the sheer beauty and grace of the
    animal.</para>

    <para>Finally the ostler brought the horse to a halt before them making
    her stand so as to be presented to best advantage for their inspection.
    Following Paulina Maria's lead, Johan ran his hand along the animal's
    neck, thrilling to the feel of her firm flesh beneath the warm, velvet of
    her coat. He was given carrot and apple pieces to hold out on the palm of
    his hand for the mare to take. The horse's breath was warm on his skin as
    her soft lips delicately felt for the food before gently lifting it from
    him with a watchmaker's precision. He found himself fascinated by the fine
    skin and few long whiskers of her muzzle, by the pulsating and deep
    nostrils that softly inhaled and exhaled, and by her unfocused brown eyes
    which suggested nothing so much as a benign character. Unable to resist
    exploring her face further, he ran his hand over her forehead, ears, and
    mane before his enchantment was broken by the ostler's discrete
    cough.</para>

    <para>As the mare was led away to be put into harness, Johan turned to
    Paulina Maria and offered her his arm for the return walk to the house. He
    found her gazing into his eyes and smiling contentedly. His heart filled
    with such joy that he could barely stop himself from acting without
    decorum. He wanted to shout, to laugh loudly and to catch Paulina Maria up
    by the waist and run with her. Self-control was necessary as their path
    soon crossed with that of three servants traveling in an open cart with
    whom greetings and cheery waves were exchanged. Paulina Maria explained
    that a picnic was being sent on ahead and would be laid out ready for them
    to take lunch when they got to her father's<emphasis> jachthuis</emphasis>
    in Willige Langerak. What a miracle of organisation she was, thinking of
    everything and arranging it just so! He must have her as his wife!</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title/>

    <para>Johan's high spirits soon suffered a knock, however. He readied
    himself to drive out then joined Paulina Maria to wait in the vestibule
    for their transport to be brought to them, Paulina Maria having changed
    into a different and more decorous outfit to suit the upcoming activity. A
    clearly expensive and very ornately decorated <emphasis>sjees</emphasis>
    appeared with a uniformed groom leading the magnificent mare, who was now
    between the delicate shafts of the carriage. Johan found himself fervently
    hoping that he would not be required to take the driving seat. He could
    see that the light, two-seater conveyance had no box for a coachman nor
    was there a pair of horses to suggest that a postilion might appear and
    ride the leader. Johan could barely sit a horse much less drive one so the
    prospect of being put in charge of such a refined and costly rig as that
    drawing up before him filled him with horror. Would Paulina Maria consider
    it unmanly of him were he to decline to take the reins? Could he avoid the
    shame of discovery if he were to conceal his shortcomings behind an
    exhibition of bravado in the driving seat? Images of every sort of
    carriage accident known to him passed before his mind's eye causing his
    courage to take flight. A paralysis seized him such as he had never known
    even in the worst of conditions at sea.</para>

    <para>It was with a not inconsiderable measure of relief that Johan
    realised that Paulina Maria was heading determinedly for the left seat in
    the <emphasis>sjees</emphasis>. Hastily mastering himself, Johan helped
    her up into the carriage then walked round to the right side and climbed
    in himself. Once they were settled, sitting close together as dictated by
    the lack of space, Paulina Maria signalled to the man at the horse's head
    that they were to set off. Soon they were on their way through the village
    and onto the Vlisterdijk road towards Shoonhoven and it was only then that
    she explained the rather unconventional seating arrangement as only
    prudent with a relatively untried horse which had never pulled a
    <emphasis>sjees</emphasis> before or been driven by anyone in the
    household apart from herself and her father. She wished to spare Johan the
    responsibility of driving in these circumstances and hoped that he would
    not be offended. He was not, he assured her, managing to present a
    graceful acceptance of the imposed circumstances which avoided his having
    to confess his shortcoming as a suitor.</para>

    <para>As they passed slowly and sedately along the Hoogstraat, the men
    they passed doffed their hats and women dipped little curtsies. Johan was
    unaware of it but their route out of the village carefully avoided the
    poorer dwellings to the east of the Grote Haven in favour of passing the
    best houses and the thriving businesses. Just beyond the village they came
    in sight of an octagonal windmill which Paulina Maria named for him as
    Boezemmolen Number Six, which seemed a rather prosaic name for the
    gracefully curved structure with its reed thatch top coat and almost
    rakish 'tail' ladder. Looking ahead Johan could make out six or seven more
    windmills along the River Vlist, although these were of a smaller, simpler
    design. He remarked that the land below the dijk seemed still quite
    waterlogged, even after the recent dry spell, voicing some surprise that
    none of these drainage mills had their sails turning despite a reasonable
    breeze having got up. Paulina Maria explained that one of the other duties
    of the servants in the cart ahead of them had been to instruct the millers
    to stop the sails until their <emphasis>sjees</emphasis> had passed. The
    Gouda to Schoonhoven Post Coach had also been held back to let them go on
    ahead of it as well as any vagrants or beggars cleared out of their
    path.</para>

    <para>The way having been prepared for them, the journey passed most
    pleasantly. Johan had all the mills and farms named for him and anecdotes
    told about the local characters who inhabited them. It soon became clear
    to him that Paulina Maria and her mother not only controlled all that he
    could see with a firm business hand, they also took an interest in the
    lives of their tenants. Families suffering sickness and hardship received
    assistance so that none should be destitute through no fault of their own.
    Although Paulina Maria did not talk about this, he soon deduced for
    himself how delicate the balance between water, wind and land was. As high
    tides and heavy rainfall raised water levels in the River Vlist, which ran
    between the larger rivers of the Ijssel and Lek and drew water from both
    of them, the land would flood. If the wind to turn the mills did not come
    then it would not be possible to pump the water off the land so it would
    remain waterlogged. Animals would die, crops would fail and diseases
    thrive in the stagnant water so that all who drank from it risked illness
    and even death. Being at the mercy of wind and water was something he
    could understand and came as a welcome antidote to the earlier social
    shortcomings he had felt. It was just a pity that the mill arms had their
    canvasses rolled up as he would have enjoyed hearing the rush of the sails
    as the wind gave up its power to them and the wood of the mill structures
    creak and groan in response to the motion.</para>

    <para>His equilibrium restored, Johan now took advantage of their close
    physical proximity and the time on their hands to pay attention to his
    courtship of Paulina Maria. He began with the usual compliments on
    appearance: the colour of her carriage dress bringing out the colour of
    her eyes, the attraction of the fineness of her complexion, the inviting
    shape and colour of her lips, and so on. He leant close to her so that he
    could speak softly into her ear whilst considering how to slip his arm
    around her waist, a liberty which would allow him to explore the corsetry
    beneath her dress for its hints about the flesh beneath. She seemed to
    accept his attentions with some warmth yet she did not respond physically
    as he had anticipated she might, so he held back from pressing her too far
    for fear of rejection. He fancied that Paulina Maria was only feigning her
    concentration on driving out of decorum, regarding himself as fortunate
    that she had her hands full with the horse's reins and was constrained to
    be close to him by the confines of the carriage.</para>

    <para>Passing what seemed to be the last mill before coming to a village,
    Johan rallied his interest as Paulina Maria told him about it. His
    attentiveness was part courtship ploy as well as a half genuine enquiry
    and turned out to be successful on both counts as the mill's long history
    was recounted with some enthusiasm. The current Bonrepasmolen, he was
    told, was the latest to be built on the site of the earliest mill in South
    Holland, with the collapse of the access bridge and loss of wind dogging
    the one attempt made to re-locate the mill to the opposite side of the
    Vlist. Hearing them approaching, Miller Prins came out of the
    reed-thatched pyramid of a house that he and his family occupied beneath
    the wooden cap of the mill and proudly held up his baby son, Arie, for the
    lady and her guest to admire. Paulina Maria caused the
    <emphasis>sjees</emphasis> to be halted briefly, producing a coin from
    some concealed place in her skirts which she instructed Johan to give to
    the miller. This achieved, they continued with their journey and, to his
    joy, Paulina Maria leant conspiratorially towards Johan. This was for
    nothing more romantic than to quietly explain that she wished to
    discourage Miller Prins from presenting the child at the house since he
    was unlikely to resist using the occasion as an excuse to petition her
    mother and herself for money to enlarge the mill's house to accommodate
    his growing family. It was the view of her parents that the miller was
    lucky to have work and a home so should be grateful not greedy. Lacking
    any grounds to contradict her, Johan joined the whispered conspiracy
    against the miller as the only way he could see to pursue his
    courtship.</para>

    <para>Their destination was soon in view as the Vlist swung round to pass
    the village of Willige Langerak to their right. Leaving the dijk, they
    turned down beside the church before taking a narrow lane to their left
    and halting the <emphasis>sjees</emphasis> before the door of a long, low
    house. An elderly man appeared from within, followed by the three
    Haastrecht servants, all four lining up to welcome them. Johan hastily
    stepped down from the carriage and hastened to assist Paulina Maria ahead
    of the waiting staff. Although the <emphasis>sjees</emphasis> was
    extremely well sprung and deeply upholstered he was relieved to be able to
    straighten his body and stretch his long legs. Paulina Maria introduced
    the old man as Jan de Gier who acted as caretaker of the
    <emphasis>jachthuis</emphasis> then invited Johan to enter the house with
    her. Once inside Paulina Maria disappeared into a distant room along with
    her maid and he was shown to his own room where Jan de Gier's son was on
    hand to help him to make himself comfortable and clean after the dusty
    journey.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title/>

    <para>The refreshment provided with lunch was most welcome and Johan
    partook of several glasses of an excellent Spätburgunder with which to
    wash down a hearty serving of cold meats, cheeses and filled breads from
    the buffet awaiting them. He noticed that Paulina only drank seltzer water
    but made up for this abstemiousness with a hearty appetite for the food,
    especially the sweet dishes which were brought in once they had finished
    with the savouries. By the time they had eaten their fill they had been
    more than an hour and a half at table, the time being consumed in no small
    part by the passage of easy conversation between them. Nevertheless Johan
    was starting to feel restless and was pleased to follow up on a talking
    point by suggesting a stroll to the nearby church.</para>

    <para>On leaving the <emphasis>jachthuis</emphasis> they turned right
    along the lane for the short walk to their destination, glad of the shade
    of the few trees at the edge of the gardens as the heat of the day reached
    its mid-afternoon intensity. The low body of the church was painted white
    with the addition of a short, square, tower at its western end built in
    grey stone, the whole looking very neat and well-kept. As they approached
    the portico over the entrance hall the Pastor, having heard them coming,
    appeared round the corner from the graveyard with the intention of opening
    the doors for them and assisting them in any further way they might
    require. However, Paulina Maria deftly dismissed the man saying that she
    was sufficiently familiar with the interior of the church. Johan was
    thankful for her tact as he so desperately wanted to have her completely
    to himself at last with nothing to distract her from his
    attentions.</para>

    <para>In the cool of the interior they made a brief tour of inspection of
    what little there was to see in this simple place of worship, relaxing
    some of their social guardedness in response to the calm atmosphere that
    often characterises old churches and is so soothing to the spirit. Johan
    chose a bench by the wall and drew Paulina Maria to sit beside him where
    they were companionably and contentedly silent for a while. Then Johan
    gently took her hand and lifted it briefly to his lips before
    asking;</para>

    <para>"Would you do me the honour of considering becoming my wife?"</para>

    <para>He had not exactly planned to propose in this place and at this
    time, but it had been on his mind to speak to Paulina Maria as soon as he
    had the opportunity. He rather fancied that she might wish to take time to
    consider the matter especially as he was starting to realize that there
    were differences between them. He worried that she might reject him since
    it was becoming obvious that their lives took different paths with his
    being so unlike that of her father that she might not be able to
    accommodate his ways. Although he badly needed to make certain of her, he
    was actually somewhat unnerved by her immediate acceptance of his offer of
    marriage. Had she really thought the matter over? Would she change her
    mind later and break their engagement on further reflection?</para>

    <para>Johan now sought to ease his insecurity by suggesting that their
    nuptials should take place as soon as possible, a course of action to
    which Paulina Maria instantly agreed. He and his new fiancée sat together
    in the old church, talking together in hushed tones as they planned how to
    make their important announcement and when the wedding should take place.
    Everything went smoothly as Paulina Maria knew exactly what was needed and
    soon put her organisational skills to work, relieving him of much of the
    detailed decision-making, for which he was ill-equipped anyway. By the
    time they left the church Johan knew exactly what he was to do and when in
    making the announcement of their forthcoming marriage to their respective
    families and friends.</para>

    <para>Although the success of his suit brought an immediate feeling of
    relief and even satisfaction, he still felt a vague sense of unease. It
    would seem that Paulina Maria had already secured the blessing of her
    family in anticipation of his proposal yet he wondered why they had not
    found a better match for her than his unworthy self. Somehow it had all
    been too easy, leaving him with the suspicion that he had overlooked some
    flaw in the Bisdom van Vliet's in general or Paulina Maria in particular.
    Or was it simply that they had not seen through him despite their worldly
    wisdom? A new anxiety began to form in his mind to replace his earlier
    fear of rejection. As the couple made the return journey to Haastrecht by
    <emphasis>sjees</emphasis> the notion slowly crystallised in his kind that
    Paulina Maria's family were about to give him a place among them solely by
    virtue of their own misguidedness. If they knew him for the undeserving
    wretch that he really was then he would not be about to occupy the exalted
    position of Paulina Maria's husband. He had secured entry to their
    patrician family through marriage but was unworthy of it and now felt the
    cold fingers of insecurity again reaching for his heart.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title/>

    <para>As the Bisdom van Vliet family gathered before dinner on Friday 6th
    August Johan was pleased to announce that he and Paulina Maria were to be
    married as soon as everything could be put in place. Her family were
    delighted although the women were at first somewhat perturbed that there
    was to be no formal period of engagement with all its associated social
    and sartorial benefits, not to mention the jewelery. Then Marcellus voiced
    the view that the couple were old enough to know their own minds and any
    undue delay would serve no useful purpose - a view no doubt bolstered by
    the brisk and businesslike approach he and Maria had taken towards their
    own wedding. Soon all concerns were put aside and a toast made to the
    betrothed pair.</para>

    <para>The discussion during the meal concluded with an almost military
    plan of action having been drawn up. Throughout that evening and the
    following day messengers came and went and the house bustled with constant
    activity and buzzed with hasty consultations. Johan found himself swept
    along on the tide of activity, collapsing exhausted into his bed that
    night with no energy left with which to worry about anything. There seemed
    very little that he could actually contribute apart from his general
    enthusiasm for all that was going on around him and participation in any
    necessary formalities. His only personal task was to write to his brother
    with the good news and an invitation for Gillis and Mary to dine at
    Haastrecht that Sunday evening. Their hearty congratulations and
    acceptance of the dinner invitation came by immediate return.</para>

    <para>In what seemed like no time at all the official procedures began
    with a visit to the Raadhuis for the Huwelijksafkondigingen which publicly
    proclaimed their wedding in writing. There was some urgency in doing this
    as it was required that their should be two weeks for any objectors to
    come forward before the actual wedding day itself. The next day they
    attended Sunday morning service in the Hervormde Kerk for the announcement
    of their wedding to the congregation. The Pastor was a friend of
    Marcellus's so had already visited the house and, over refreshments, a
    relaxed and happy discussion of the detailed wedding arrangements had
    resulted in Johan and Paulina Maria emerging with a clear idea of what was
    to happen. Being the Burgermeester, Marcellus himself had organised the
    civil marriage ceremony in the Raaadhuis that would precede the Church
    wedding, the date set for both ceremonies being August 20th.</para>

    <para>Although Johan was familiar with the exterior of the church, whose
    brick tower topped with a three-tiered white belfry dominated the village
    skyline, he had never been inside. The family had explained that this was
    not the original building as this had been destroyed by fire and rebuilt
    twice since its 13th century foundation. The last reconstruction in the
    17th century had left the old choir section outside the walls which
    resulted in an unusual T-shaped interior. He had been shown the base of
    the choir walls and the grave stones covering its vaults which were now
    open to the elements and to public use. Now, as they entered the church,
    Marcellus and Paulina Maria took him aside in order to show him the Bisdom
    van Vliet family vault. Beneath the looping script and decorative
    curlicues carved into the stone covering the vault lay the remains of
    Paulina Maria's ancestors. The rather chilling thought that he could well
    join them was a rather sobering thought.</para>

    <para>As he joined the family in their accustomed pew Johan was acutely
    aware that he was the object of barely concealed scrutiny by the church
    goers gathered in the rows behind them. His presence at the house on
    Hoogstraat could hardly have gone unremarked in such a small and
    close-knit community as Haastrecht and the gossip surrounding himself and
    Paulina Maria must have been rife. So, when the Pastor made the
    announcement that their marriage was to take place in less than two week's
    time a breaking wave of whispers and rustling clothing broke across the
    congregation. Johan felt their eyes upon him as he turned towards Paulina
    Maria and they exchanged smiles. Once the service was over the Bisdom van
    Vliet family party were the first to leave the church but nevertheless
    found themselves waylaid by well-wishers and the just plain curious,
    causing them to be considerably delayed on their return to the
    house.</para>

    <para>After a hasty lunch everyone but Johan resumed their busy wedding
    preparations. Lingering at the table with a much-needed glass of wine to
    hand he struggled with a cross-current of emotions. He had been caught up
    by the general excitement of the wedding announcement and the press of
    people outside the church but now found that the celebratory mood this had
    induced in him seemed to be shared neither by his bride-to-be nor by his
    hosts who all now adopted a cool, businesslike demeanor. A sense of not
    being part of the whole process of organising the marriage - his marriage
    - and of being relegated to the side-lines was at odds with wanting to
    share his happiness. Soon he took his lifelong recourse from the feeling
    of being abandoned and went in search of some independent activity in
    which he could bury himself. Since Marcellus had offered him the use of
    his library and workroom it was to this secluded place that Johan
    retreated with a view to reading the newspapers for the day.</para>

    <para>At first he just skipped through the news without taking much in as
    he was not in a settled enough frame of mind to undertake the onerous task
    of reading about national and provincial politics. Suddenly his eye was
    taken by a small item that immediately captured his full attention since
    it concerned a lady with whom he had some acquaintance. Back in 1861 he
    had been serving on a ship making passage between Den Haag and Alexandria
    in the company of three ladies who, much to the irritation of the officers
    and crew, they had been ordered to convey in the best possible comfort.
    The youngest, Alexine Tinne, had attained some notoriety as a pioneering
    photographer and fearless traveller. She was also among the wealthiest
    women in the Netherlands. Accompanied by her widowed mother, her maternal
    aunt, their several maids and a vast amount of luggage, accommodating them
    had caused serious disruption on board. Although only a few years his
    senior and not unpleasing to look on, Vrouw Tinne did not attract him in
    the usual way. For one thing, her mode of dress was nothing short of
    bizarre and for another she had about her a steely determination to go her
    own way in the world which quite threatened the young officer.</para>

    <para>Much had been forgiven her, however, when she began to enlivened
    dinners in the officers quarters with her vivid accounts of her
    experiences whilst travelling through Egypt, Palestine and Syria as well
    as of her time living in Beirut, all of which were regarded as territories
    too dangerous for a woman to enter. The officers were all enchanted by her
    description of her planned expedition in search of the source of Nile, a
    feat attempted by few men let alone by woman, and one which they all
    secretly wished they could undertake. Once back in Holland he had hastened
    to acquire the maps and charts which would enable him to see where she was
    about to venture, spending endless hours trying to work out her possible
    routes and imagining the hazards and wonders she would encounter along the
    way. Over the next few years he bought every book and paper published
    about her expeditions and pieced together a dismaying tale of abandoned
    hopes as the river proved unnavigable and illness struck. Vrouw Tinne's
    mother, aunt and two of her maids died during her second attempt to
    penetrate the heart of Africa and she had been very ill herself. Privately
    he considered it a tribute his idea of feminine correctness that they had
    continued to keep up their Dutch standards of toilette and domestic
    routine in the face of such a hostile environment.</para>

    <para>Now he was disturbed to read that Vrouw Tinne had disappeared during
    her latest expedition, along with two Dutch sailors who were part of her
    <emphasis>entourage</emphasis>. Her caravan had set out some weeks
    previously with the intention of crossing the Sahara desert in order to
    encounter the nomadic Tuareg tribes. She seemed to have made contact with
    some tribal leaders upon arriving safely at Marzuk but since then nothing
    had been seen or heard of her. She had failed to make contact with a
    fellow explorer in the area who had set up a rumour that fleeing survivors
    from her caravan told of an ambush and many deaths. Vrouwe Tinne's safety
    was feared for, in short. Johan wanted to see for himself what kind of
    geographical location she might be in and the physical challenges she was
    facing. He got up and began to look through the cupboards and bookshelves
    in the hope of an atlas to help him in his quest.</para>

    <para>At the fourth try he opened a cupboard to find the welcome sight of
    three rows of the familiar tubes of twenty or so rolled-up maps which
    Marcellus had neatly arranged inside. Johan reverently lifted them out one
    by one, unrolling each in turn on the top of the large table in the centre
    of the room, holding down their four corners with convenient small, heavy
    objects. Thus he took stock of the treasure he had found, carefully
    rolling each map up and replacing it in the cupboard as he finished with
    it. There was, of course, nothing on Africa but instead a wealth of
    material relating to Holland in general and to the Krimpenerwaard in
    particular, some of it familiar from his own collection and even some of
    the work of his grandfather. Several river charts took his interest as
    either very old or for their obvious use as working documents which had
    been annotated in the process of taking water management decisions. After
    some deliberation, he chose one from among them for closer
    scrutiny.</para>

    <para>He reverently laid out what he recognised as a hand-coloured print
    on paper made from a copper engraving of the original chart as drawn by
    Melchior Bolstra in the middle of the last century. He knew that it was
    one of a set of seven sheets which covered the whole of the River Lek,
    part of a mapping exercise which covered all the rivers of Holland. This
    particular sheet showed the reach of the river that passed Willige
    Langerak, a village which now held sentimental interest for him. Only
    forty or so copies of Bolstra's maps had been produced, their ownership
    restricted to officials of the Hoogheemraadschap van Rijnland and the
    local river and polder boards. None had been allowed into general
    circulation and many were now lost from sight. Marcellus's forbears had
    clearly been involved in the making of important decisions about the
    management of the Lek which were to prove successful in preventing the
    repeated flooding that had occurred since the Spyk dyke breach in 1740.
    The map had also been used in their deliberations about work on the bed of
    the river which would ensure that it remained an efficient navigation
    route for shipping.</para>

    <para>Bolstra had undertaken a meticulous survey of the Lek between 1750
    and 1754, following the principles introduced by Cruquius which combined
    rigorously gathered quantitative data with the usual cartographic drawing.
    Unlike Croquius, Bolstra did not keep his data in separate tables but
    integrated it into the chart itself to produce an accurate representation
    of the river bed and the other topographical elements of the fluvial
    environment. Johan knew that, although Bolstra had amassed data concerning
    the depth of the river and the shape of the river bed, he was yet to
    develop the system of contour lines. He was also aware that the results of
    Bolstra's research into river flow were never applied to the chart,
    although they had been available in manuscript form. Rather less of a
    shortcoming in Johan's view was the lack of detail included about the land
    beyond the river and its banks and dykes, a focus on navigation by water
    which showed the map-maker to be of like minds with himself.</para>

    <para>After some moments in silent appreciation of the history of the
    chart before him, Johan delved into the breast pocket of his coat and
    removed a square pouch made of soft leather from which he carefully slid
    his folding brass magnifying glass. He opened the glass out so that it
    rested on its frame with the lens at just the right height to bring the
    details of the chart into focus. Now he bent to the happy task of reading
    the old chart before him, as others might read a sheet of music or a good
    book. In his blood ran the gift of visualising mere lines on paper as the
    very thing that they had been made to represent. So, the territory mapped
    rose in his minds eye as a three-dimensional landscape, coloured and in
    motion as nature and man had made it. Not only that but he could move
    about in this inner world: altering course here and altitude there,
    compensating for wind and current, avoiding the precipice and finding the
    track most economical of effort. Then, at will, his perspective would
    shift back to the drawing before him and a course to run would appear to
    him as clearly as if the line to follow had already been drawn upon the
    paper.</para>

    <para>Now he saw, as if he were there, the river gently curving to port
    before him as it flowed towards the sea, the low water lazy at the turn of
    a neap tide and depleted by the summer sun. To starboard he perceived the
    pattern of ditches, walls and triangular bastions that made up the
    six-pointed defensive star that protected Nieuwpoort against artillery
    attack. Ahead and to port rose Schoonhoven's larger,
    eight-pointed<emphasis> trace italienne</emphasis> fortifications beyond
    which the river made a turn to starboard before evaporating at the western
    edge of the chart. He could see that, as well as protecting against attack
    by man, these ramparts would save both cities from floods, the harbours
    and shipyards tucked behind them providing refuge for shipping.</para>

    <para>Having looked around him in a general way, Johan now turned his
    attention to the north bank just before Schoonehoven where the village of
    Willege Langerak lay tucked behind a shallow dyke. He passed across the
    shallows at the edge of the river and floated up and over the dyke to the
    gratifying sight of the church with its tower ahead of him looking almost
    exactly as it had a century later on. The gentlest of smiles warmed his
    face at the recollection of the day that he had spoken to Paulina Maria
    within with such a happy outcome. Turning to look at what was now
    the<emphasis> jachthuis</emphasis> he found instead two ramshackle
    cottages and was reminded of the Bisdom van Vliet's wealth which had
    enabled these mean dwellings to be transformed into the well-appointed
    hunting lodge and stables that he had visited.</para>

    <para>Having made his sentimental journey to Willige Langerak he floated
    over fields and dykes to Schoonhoven itself where he became engrossed in
    exploring the harbour and waterways that were so much a part of the old
    city, losing himself in how life was before the steam engine and the river
    improvements. The weight of a hand on his shoulder roused Johan to the
    present and to Paulina Maria beside him.</para>

    <para>"We thought we had lost you, nobody has seen you for hours! I'm glad
    that we could provide you with something to occupy you and only sorry to
    have to disturb you, but it is time to dress for dinner. Your brother and
    our other guests are expected shortly."</para>

    <para>Johan took his watch from his waistcoat pocket and looked in
    disbelief at the time.</para>

    <para>"Thank you for coming to find me, my dear. I shall just replace this
    chart then go to make myself ready for our celebration dinner."</para>

    <para>He took Paulina Maria's hand and raised it to his lips, causing her
    a slight giggle at the tickle of his moustaches, then turned to roll up
    Bolstra's chart. Paulina Maria filled with a warm glow as she took in the
    curve of his strong back bent over the table. Next he went about the
    business of placing the chart among its fellows in their cupboard. She
    could barely resist reaching out to touch his beautiful dark hair. Order
    restored to the maps, he turned towards her and they fell into an
    unpremeditated mutual embrace, heedless of the possibility of being
    observed.</para>

    <para/>

    <para>Paulina Maria was wearing her new Bride Dress for the first time
    that evening. As Johan returned to her side, dressed for dinner and ready
    to receive the congratulations of their guests, he complimented her on it
    fulsomely, although privately he wondered at her choice of such a bold hue
    which was a surprisingly fashionable choice for her. Although her
    complexion could stand up to the colour, the gown itself was so busy with
    every form of adornment that it quite swamped even Paulina Maria's robust
    frame and owed its design to no form of fashion that he knew of. He
    suspected Paulina Maria's own whims had steered its creation and quailed
    somewhat at the thought that she would be wearing this same garment to all
    their engagements between now and the end of the honeymoon, and that it
    would live on in perpetuity in their wedding photographs. He would now
    have to reconsider wearing his full dress uniform for their big day as
    Paulina Maria's gown would undoubtedly distract everyone's attention from
    it.</para>

    <para>As the guests for their dinner party began to arrive and assemble in
    the Grote Salon Johan was introduced to Marcellus' brother, Otto Braet
    Bisdom van Cattenbroek, and his wife, Adelaide. Paulina Maria's uncle, who
    was called Braet by everyone, seemed a rather dull old chap compared to
    the cheery and sociable Marcellus. Despite being Marcellus's younger
    brother by four years Braet's hair was quite grey. His heavy eyelids
    drooped as though weary of looking at the world and his mouth came to rest
    with its corners turned down in lamentation of his lot in life. From the
    conversation amongst the Bisdom family Johan gathered that Uncle Braet was
    an Advocate of some importance in the city of Utrecht and had taken the
    van Cattenbroek name from his lands a few miles upstream along the
    Hollandse Ijssel near the city of Montfoort. It seemed to Johan that Uncle
    Braet had got himself out from under the shadow of his prominent sibling
    by removing himself from South Holland to Utrecht and its Province,
    altering his name to simply Braet van Cattenbroek and seeking prominence
    in a different public sphere.</para>

    <para>By contrast, Vrouw van Cattenbroek appeared to be much younger being
    possessed of an open, round face which displayed few signs of a care-worn
    personality. Her buxom figure and straight brown hair were simply dressed
    giving an air of motherliness about her. Just as Gillis and Mary had named
    their first-born Johan Jacob after him so Braet and Adelaide had named
    their firstborn after Paulina Maria. This youngest Paulina Maria was now
    in her twenty-first year so it seemed a shame that she had not been
    invited that evening. He lost count of their other children who were
    mostly girls with the only boy he registered being ten-year-old 'Freddie'.
    He found all the talk around him was of children which was rather tedious
    and he idly wondered if his view of them would change when his own arrived
    on the scene. For now, though, he was reduced to making polite noises as
    his mind attempted to desert to more interesting matters. He had even more
    of a struggle to keep up appearances when the women of the party began to
    make admiring comments about Paulina's Bride Dress and invited him to
    agree with them. He was never so grateful as when the butler announced
    that dinner was to be served.</para>

    <para>A few glasses of wine and he began to feel more relaxed, although he
    felt he could contribute little of substance to the dinner table talk.
    Everyone wanted to know the details of the wedding, the wedding party, the
    honeymoon and where they planned to establish their home. On most topics
    he was as uninformed as all the other guests and learned a lot from the
    Paulina Maria's account of what was planned. It appeared was his task to
    arrange the honeymoon but it had come as quite a shock to him that he was
    expected to have this well in hand already when, in fact, he had given it
    no thought until now. He tried to hide behind a wish to keep it a secret
    from Paulina Maria but nobody believed that such a thing was possible so
    he was forced to make a plan on the spur of the moment. He remembered
    Paulina Maria showing him her albums from the coach trip she had made
    through the Alps to Italy and how enthusiastically she talked of the
    water, flora and fauna she had seen along the way. Inspired by the notion
    of water, he broadly hinted that they would be visiting the Mediterranean
    in the South of France before passing through to the lakes of Italy and
    Switzerland. To his great relief this suggestion clearly pleased and
    excited Paulina Maria so met with general approval. He only hoped that he
    would be able to make good on what was now taken to be his promise.</para>

    <para>Paulina Maria and Marcellus were had already compiled a list of
    guests for the wedding party to which Gillis and Johan had contributed as
    many of names of family, friends and professional that they could think
    of. The Tivoli in Utrecht, owned by another of Marcellus's friends, had
    been chosen as the most suitable venue for this prestigious event. The
    city had good water, rail and road links across the Netherlands, Germany
    and Belgium with plenty of respectable accommodation to be had. The Tivoli
    consisted of an attractive park within which a grand hall had recently
    been built as an improved venue for the concerts that the gardens were
    known for. The replacement of the old wooden concert hall with a larger,
    stone-faced building now meant that this Grote Zaal had attained a
    reputation for hosting grand events, such as the 50th anniversary
    masquerade of the Utrecht university in 1868. Thus it was considered by
    the family to have the right pedigree for such a significant occasion as
    the marriage of Marcellus and Maria Bisdom van Vliet's only daughter which
    needed to be socially conspicuous.</para>

    <para>A scheduling problem had then arisen because the guest list was so
    long that it would require two separate sittings in order to accommodate
    everyone. Paulina Maria had therefore decided that two identical wedding
    parties would be held on consecutive days but this was not easy to arrange
    as the hall had other bookings and the caterers needed time to prepare. In
    the end she arranged that the wedding parties should take place on the
    Monday and Tuesday preceding the formal ceremonies scheduled for Friday
    the twentieth. She anticipated that they would depart for their honeymoon
    on Saturday the twenty-first, an idea which Johan did not disabuse her of.
    Once again, Johan was impressed be her ability to organise matters,
    especially as she already had preparations well in hand for the dual
    parties which were now only just over week away. Uncle Braet roused
    himself to give his blessing to the choice of the Tivoli venue and to
    offer the family accommodation for the duration of their stay in Utrecht
    as well as volunteering his wife's local knowledge of the best catering
    suppliers.</para>

    <para>By the end of the meal Johan's head was swimming with information,
    as well as the various wines and spirits which he had sampled. It was no
    wonder that the house had been such a hive of activity since he and
    Paulina Maria had made their announcement. He could now see why Paulina
    Maria had made no time for him and could appreciate what a remarkable
    amount she had achieved in only a short time. He was now to return to Den
    Haag with Gillis and Mary and he was glad of some quiet time alone with
    his own people, finding it was relaxing to be able to be calm with them as
    a respite from the whirlwind of the dinner party. They were concerned that
    matters were moving too fast for him, despite wishing to see the match
    settled in short order. Johan confessed that his head was spinning at the
    scale and speed of what felt like a military operation set in train to the
    end of a rather more splendid wedding than he could ever have envisaged,
    but he did not want to change anything. He could adjust to the situation
    and was already starting to think about how he could play his own,
    distinctive part in it all.</para>
  </section>
</chapter>
