<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter version="5.1" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
         xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:xila="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude/local-attributes"
         xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
         xmlns:trans="http://docbook.org/ns/transclusion"
         xmlns:svg="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"
         xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
         xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
         xmlns:db="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
  <title>Summer 1872(3)</title>

  <section>
    <title/>
    <para>The arrival of Theodorus Hooft caused something of a stir amongst
    the inhabitants of Haastrecht. There had, of course, been rumours that a
    new family had taken a house just beyond the sluis which could be
    interpreted as indicating that they are clearly not patrician or even
    simply wealthy. On the other hand, they were not simple folk who tended to
    live even further out along the dyke in dwellings which could only be
    described as basic or even hovels. The labouring population was almost
    entirely made up of folk born and raised in the village or who had married
    into these local families, but the Hoofts were clearly incomers, thus of
    great concern. The consensus among the watchers had to be that newcomers
    fell somewhere in between the Bisdom van Vliets and the common folk,
    likely the man of the family would be some sort of tradesman.</para>

    <para>Grist to the rumour mill came from the Straver family of carpenters
    who had let it be known that they had been approached by 'building
    interests in Den Haag' with a view to engaging one of them in a 'grand and
    important' local construction project. Details of the Den Haag end of
    things were few and far between, the Straver family being more exercised
    with spreading it about that young Cornelis Straver, at the age of only
    18, was to be given the honour of being a senior journeyman on this
    project. Details of the who, what, when and where of the putative
    construction remained the subject of much inventive conjecture. Thus, as
    soon as a stranger, accompanied by a woman and child, came into view on
    the dyke top word soon spread and people materialised at every vantage
    point to inspect the newcomers and their cart load of possessions as they
    steadily made their way towards their new home.</para>

    <para>As soon as the cart had come to a reliable halt, Theodorus stepped
    down and and raised his arms to help his wife safely down to earth, an
    especially delicate task since, as all could plainly see, she was
    pregnant. Next came a boy of about four who seemed less than keen to
    explore his new home, clinging to his mother's skirt thumb in mouth.
    Having secured his horse, the carter made haste to uncover his cargo and
    carry a chair into the house in order that Mevrouw Hooft might sit and
    recover after their long, uncomfortable journey from Den Haag. A box of
    toys followed in the hope that the young boy might be entertained and not
    get in the way of the men as they unloaded the rest of the family's goods.
    This latter task was arguably facilitated by the many volunteers from
    amongst the curious crowd who would later benefit in the way of kudos,
    taking material form as free food and drink, when disseminating their
    accounts of the family and their things in every detail.</para>

    <para>At last, Theodorus paid the carter and closed the front door on the
    intrusive helpers who had been reluctant to leave. It had been a long day
    indeed! Maria Francina had wanted to supervise the unloading of their
    kitchen equipment, linens and clothing but he had been quite stern about
    making her stay sitting down. Hendrik Willem had been fractious and clung
    to his mother and attempted to do the same to his father, which was rather
    less than convenient He had more than enough to cope with managing the
    location of every unloaded item, especially when people were crowding into
    the small house carrying anything they could lay their hands and requiring
    Theodorus to be in several places at once. He was, frankly, exhausted but
    the day was not over yet as he needed to make a site visit to check on
    progress and make his presence felt among the labourers. It was a
    considerable relief to him when a thoughtful gesture by
    <emphasis>Burgemeester</emphasis> Bisdom van Vliet materialised in the
    shape of two maids who stepped into the middle of the chaos and set about
    making up beds and organising basic kitchen and toileting
    facilities.</para>

    <para/>

    <para/>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title/>

    <para>Paulina had never felt so perturbed in all her life, not even when
    she met Johan Jacob. Her uncommon disquiet was compounded by the sensation
    that she was about to be overwhelmed and suffer an uncharacteristic and
    disgraceful public emotional collapse. She desperately cast about for some
    sort of refuge from being exposed to social humiliation. Although she
    would have preferred solitude, nevertheless she was so glad to see her
    friend, Cornelia Droost, making haste in her direction. Allowing herself
    to be guided by Cornelia's hand under her elbow, Paulina entered the cool,
    calm quiet of the Droost house where she was passed into the enveloping
    wings of a plush armchair. Tea was ordered and Helena sent for.</para>

    <para>As the disturbance of her arrival died down, the Droost house tried
    to regain its usual deep silence only punctuated only by the ponderous
    tick of the long case clock in the hall. But not today and a miserable
    Paulina realized that she could still hear the commotion outside from
    which she so badly wanted to escape. Granted, the clamour of destruction
    was now muted by the fabrics and furnishings of the house, yet the sounds
    of wrecking that filtered through retained the power to unsettle her
    spirit. It was incomprehensible yet it manifestly true that the home she
    had grown up in, which had seemed so solid, secure, immutable even, was
    being reduced to unrecognisable chunks of stone and wood accompanied by
    clouds of dust. Oh, so much commotion and chaos! Horrified, she could feel
    herself about to swoon in front of other people, even if they were her
    oldest and best friends.</para>

    <para>When her father had first put forward his scheme to demolish the old
    <emphasis>familie huis</emphasis> his idea was clearly a bold one but, the
    way he presented it, seemed to make sense. His vision was to replace the
    existing arbitrary assemblage of buildings with a single, modern and
    stylish property. Part of his argument was that the old house was woefully
    lacking in domestic comforts and innovations, yet this was true of so many
    properties built by 17th century patricians. Many wealthy families had
    stuck to the Dutch way and periodically made additions and adaptations to
    their old houses thus giving them a new lease of life. It was obvious to
    Paulina and others that something more than replacing an old house, which
    was not exactly falling into ruins, was at work here. Marcellus's next
    point was incontestable. A new house was the way he wished to mark the
    anniversary of his fifty years as <emphasis>burgermeester</emphasis> of
    Haastrecht, which was undoubtedly a momentous achievement worthy of some
    grand gesture. But knocking down buildings which could have been the basis
    for a perfectly good house then to replace them with a completely new one?
    The family were puzzled and dismayed, although they attempted to hide this
    from the proud and elated Marcellus.</para>

    <para>With the utmost secrecy, Marcellus had set about finding an
    architect who was familiar with the new style of houses currently the
    fashion in Den Haag. He wanted something that had the same character as
    Paulina and Johan's new house, on the subject of which he had
    surreptitiously quizzed the couple and received glowing reports. The
    architect paid a site visit to Haastrecht early in 1972 which resulted in
    the advice to build the new house on the footprint of the old one. This
    strategy would avoid the trouble and expense of putting in new wooden
    piles for the foundations since the existing ones were still in good
    condition. It also had the virtue of keeping to the size of the original
    plot thus obviating the need to negotiate ownership of more land from
    adjacent properties. With his brief clearly established, the architect
    soon had a set of plans for the new Bisdom van Vliet house available for
    the perusal of his client.</para>

    <para>Marcellus was delighted with the look of his new house so set about
    finding suitable master craftsmen to build it. He preferred to use local
    men where at all possible, but the architect championed a talented young
    mason and plasterer, Theodorus Hooft, who had experience in the modern
    building techniques currently in demand in Den Haag. Marcellus was
    impressed by Heer Hooft when they met, finding him amiable yet polite.
    They were soon collaborating effortlessly in making a refinements to the
    original plans so as to better fulfil Marcellus's aspirations. The young
    man was also willing to uproot his wife and young son from their home in
    Den Haag and move the family to Haastrecht in order to be near his client
    and his place of work.</para>

    <para>Then came the day when Marcellus, Heer Hooft at his side, called
    together family and friends for a somewhat theatrical unveiling of his
    radical project. He was so delighted with himself and his vision of the
    future that nobody had the courage to challenge his decision, and Heer
    Hooft seemed such a nice young man who had clearly committed so much to
    the project and worked so hard on behalf of his client. In short, the two
    men put up a united and unassailable front.</para>

    <para>Once the cat was out of the bag the gossips got to work. In parlours
    and kitchens all over the Province of South Holland the mention of
    Marcellus was heard to provoke phrases such as:</para>

    <para>"<emphasis>Hier kan je je ei kwijt ...</emphasis>"</para>

    <para>as a ringleader would invite those around them to openly share their
    opinions on Marcellus's grand plan and "loose their egg here", allegedly
    in private.</para>

    <para>Then someone would venture that,</para>

    <para>"<emphasis>Hij heeft een klap van de molen beet!</emphasis>" or
    "<emphasis>Een klap van de molen gehad hebben!</emphasis>"</para>

    <para>to convey the view that he was not acting very wisely as though he
    had been "hit by one of the sails on the windmill" and has lost his mind
    as a result of it.</para>

    <para>In his defense would come the reply,</para>

    <para>"<emphasis>Leder kaasje heeft zijn gaatje!</emphasis>"</para>

    <para>to caution that "every cheese has its hole" so nobody's
    perfect.</para>

    <para>The dismayed would retort,</para>

    <para>"<emphasis>Als de herder verdwaalt dolen the
    schapen.</emphasis>"</para>

    <para>"If the shepherd gets lost the sheep just wander around." In other
    words, if the leader goes off in a wrong direction then other people don't
    quite know what to do.</para>

    <para>Or,</para>

    <para>"<emphasis>Nu breekt mijn klomp!</emphasis>"</para>

    <para>"Now my clog is breaking!" I am totally amazed and I certainly
    didn't expect that!.</para>

    <para>More colourfully,</para>

    <para><emphasis>"In de nesten zitten of werken!</emphasis>"</para>

    <para>"He is sitting on a nest!" A country expression referring to the
    important task that millers have in keeping the area where the top rollers
    are free of birds nests. If birds get in there and build their nests then
    the rollers to turn the cap of the windmill jam resulting in a complete
    mess. So, the more thoughtful gossips have realized that Marcellus finds
    himself confused and not quite knowing what to do.</para>

    <para>The less kindly, or more jealous, counter that,</para>

    <para>"<emphasis>op grote voet leven!</emphasis>"</para>

    <para>He is wealthy, or "living on a big foot", so can afford to spend a
    lot of money on whatever he wants,including a new house.</para>

    <para>Those who envy his social position chip in with,</para>

    <para>"<emphasis>Hij laat de wereld op zijn duim
    draaien!</emphasis>"</para>

    <para>"He lets the world spin on his thumb", implying that he has too much
    power!</para>

    <para>Countered by,</para>

    <para>"<emphasis>Je wordt geleefd!</emphasis>"</para>

    <para>"He is being lived by life" rather than living life and is so busy
    that his life is out of control.</para>

    <para>"<emphasis>Hij heeft het zo druk als de kippen voor
    Pasen!</emphasis>"</para>

    <para>"He is as busy as the chickens before Easter!"</para>

    <para>One thing all agree on is that,</para>

    <para>"<emphasis>Hij staat vast in zijn schoenen.</emphasis>"</para>

    <para>"He stands firmly in his shoes" so he knows his own mind and stands
    his ground.</para>

    <para>Inevitably the village chatter reached Paulina, who came to
    appreciate that the general view was that her father has upset people by
    not doing what they expected him to do. Whilst some shared her own thought
    that his recent personal losses and his hectic work schedule had clouded
    his judgement, all acknowledged that it had to be accepted that a man as
    wealthy, powerful and sure of himself as her father was not likely to
    question his chosen course of action or examine the reasons for it. Nor,
    she would add, is he likely to consider the impact on his daughter of
    seeing her childhood home razed to the ground.</para>

    <para>So,once she had grasped it, the opportunity that the Droost sisters
    provided of being able to unburden herself to good and trusted friends
    afforded Paulina some much needed relief from her private distress. But
    then she heard something which cast a new light on the situation and upset
    her once again. Helena and Cornelia, feeling that they may also speak
    freely to their friend, offered an additional insight concerning
    Marcellus's motivation behind the new house. By overhearing the talk
    around the building site, they had come to the view that Marcellus hopes
    to lure Paulina back to live with him permanently by building her a house
    in the style to which he fancies she has become accustomed in Den Haag. In
    addition, it seems that he hopes that such a grand property, coupled with
    the rise in status through association with himself, might overcome any
    reluctance on Johan's part to settle in Haastrecht. His strategy seems
    aimed at removing any conflict his daughter might feel between her duties
    to her husband and to her father by locating both men in the same
    place.</para>

    <para>Paulina was astounded by this perspective on matters. Her father had
    been astute only in so far as he recognised how torn she was between her
    life in Den Haag and her ties to her former home, however much she had
    hoped to conceal this from him. Since her mother's death she has felt the
    burden of management of the family's fall entirely onto her shoulders
    whether she wanted this or not. It would not be easy to find someone else
    to assist her father in matters which were second nature to her after a
    lifetime of involvement in the Bisdom van Vliet estate. There would be a
    lot for an incomer to get to grips with, not to mention the time it would
    take her to initiate them into the ways things should be done. Then there
    was the question of security and being able to trust an outsider with
    matters of business and politics which they would not wish broadcast.
    Perhaps her father had everyone's best interests at heart after all, but
    did it have to involve so much destruction!</para>

    <para>Paulina was distracted from her bewilderment and distress by a
    sudden outburst of excitement from Cornelia who had been punctuating their
    discussion with trips to peek around the lace curtain at the big bay
    window to their first floor salon from which vantage point she could look
    down into the street.</para>

    <para>"Oh, Paulina! Have you met Heer Hooft yet That's him outside now!
    Isn't he handsome! Oh, Paulina, do let's go down so that you can introduce
    us all. If you make as if to leave our house it would seem quite
    natural!"</para>

    <para>Clearly Cornelia had been smitten by the builder! Feeling that no
    good could come of encouraging her friend in yearning after a married man
    of unknown provenance and unsuitable social standing, Paulina made the
    quite legitimate excuse of not feeling up to such a demanding social
    encounter and wishing remain quietly where she was for a while longer.
    Besides, the three women still had many snippets of news to share and mull
    over.</para>

    <para/>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title/>

    <para>At last the clamour outside seemed to have died down to a tolerable
    level as the working day came to an end. Paulina rose and bade her
    grateful farewells to the Droost sisters before availing herself of the
    opportunity to venture outside again in relative calm. She was to join her
    father for dinner with their Pastor who had insisted that the temporarily
    homeless Marcellus lodge in the first floor corner room of his
    Kerkstraat<emphasis> pastorie</emphasis>. The two men were lifelong
    friends and very easy in each other's company so Paulina was looking
    forward to a relaxed visit and, since the weather was fine, enjoying the
    short stroll on the way there.</para>

    <para>Her mind on the pleasures to come, Paulina failed to notice the man
    about to cross her path so was brought back to the present with a jolt
    when Heer Hooft slowed to a halt in order to avoid a collision. He raised
    his hat to her with the clear intention of doing more than just politely
    greeting her before resuming his journey. Indeed, he made plain that he
    knew who she was and begged her indulgence as he introduced himself. It
    seems that he had noticed her visit to the building site earlier on and
    how distressed she had been by what she had found taking place there. He
    graciously expressed his concern for her and enquired as to how she now
    fared. She sensed his empathy with her feelings at seeing her family home
    and all its memories and associations reduced to a pile of ugly and
    useless rubble.</para>

    <para>Now having the opportunity to take him in, Paulina found that he
    was, indeed, a handsome man who was surprisingly young-looking to hold
    such a responsible position. He told her that he had just moved his
    household to Haastrecht from Den Haag so as to be more closely involved
    with her father's project. Paulina enquired after his family and
    discovered that he had a son, Hendrik Willem, who was approaching his
    fourth birthday and that his wife was expecting their second child in a
    month or so. Paulina remarked that she had moved in the opposite
    direction, leaving Haastrecht for Den Haag upon her marriage a few years
    earlier. She found him easy company and that their encounter was not the
    socially strained affair that their difference in standing had led her to
    anticipate. So, their first conversation came to a well-orchestrated and
    amicable closure with both going their separate ways having made positive
    comments on the almost certainty of their meeting again. As they parted,
    she caught out of the corner of her eye the twitch of a lace curtain at
    the Droost first floor window!</para>

    <para>From another first floor window, her father had been watching for
    her arrival so was waiting on the steps of the pastor's house before
    Paulina had reached the door. He greeted her enthusiastically before
    sweeping her inside to be taken under the wing of the pastor in his salon
    where his wife was waiting to serve refreshments to the small party.
    Marcellus was keen to hear Paulina's impression of the work on his new
    house but Paulina didn't have the heart to tell him how awful she had
    found the whole thing. Her father was more animated than she had seen him
    for a long time and looked in good health. Clearly the new venture had
    given him a fillip, whatever she might be feeling about it.</para>

    <para>As her visit progressed, Paulina came to understand that her
    father's rejuvenation was at least partly the result of the good food and
    congenial company he was enjoying at the pastor's house. The temporary
    hiatus in his own domestic affairs, since there now was no household, had
    also lifted some of the burden he usually carried. Paulina felt a rush of
    guilt as she realised that her father had been starting to fade away and
    it would not have been long before his health began to suffer. On top of
    the revelation that the new house was, in no small part, designed to lure
    her back to Haastrecht, she suddenly saw how much her father needed her.
    By contrast, she had to admit to herself, however, painfully, that Johan
    only came alive when he was away from home. Indeed, he seemed to shrink
    into himself when confined to the routine behaviours expected of a man of
    his social standing. She had much to think about on her carriage journey
    back home.</para>

    <para/>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title/>

    <para>Paulina was next in Haastrecht when her presence was requested at a
    meeting between her father and Theodorus Hooft. By this time the roof of
    the old house about to be removed. The tiles would be sorted and neatly
    stacked ready for re-use on other buildings in the area, discarding any
    that were too fragile or already broken. The money from the sale of the
    old tiles would go at least a little way towards offsetting the cost of
    the new roofing materials. By the same token, the wood from the supporting
    timbers would be kept for building purposes if it was sound, or cut for
    firewood if it was rotten, wormy or damaged in removal.</para>

    <para>Theodorus had a gentle soul in spite of the tough exterior required
    to do his job. This was why he had wanted his clients to see the old house
    whilst it still resembled a habitable dwelling, conscious of the
    associations it would have accrued through a lifetime of memories. He
    understood the form of grief that was in store for them. Once the roof had
    been taken away, the next stage in demolition would be removal of the
    ceilings, at which point the interior would be open to the elements. The
    rooms where the routines of daily life and the outstanding significant
    events of their times had taken place would be crudely exposed to public
    view. Prying eyes would make gossip over the rain sodden wood, plaster,
    paper and fitments that once graced the public and private chambers of the
    Burgermeester's family. For the two remaining members of that family, the
    shell of their home would be shorn of all their human activity. The old
    house would be dead and lost to them forever. Just simple lumps of
    material on a building site, as it already was for him.</para>

    <para>"I respectfully requested that you join me here today because I have
    had an idea which I wanted to put to. I realise that this destructive
    phase of the new house project is very hard for you both. So, I have been
    entertaining a notion which might make the wrench with the past a little
    easier. Perhaps if we could carry forward something of the old house to
    incorporate into the new one then you would be comforted by a sense of
    continuity."</para>

    <para>He paused in order to gauge how his idea was being received.
    Encouraged by their apparent openness to his proposal, Theodorus
    continued,</para>

    <para>"I wondered if there might be some discrete, structural part of the
    interior which hold special meaning for you and which would be suitable
    for relocation. If you can bear it, take a look around inside whilst it is
    still safe to do so. You might bid farewell to each room whilst having in
    mind the selection one fixture, such as door and frame or fireplace, in
    the old house which you would like me to transplant into your new home.
    Take care to choose something you both like and gives you pleasant
    feelings just to look at it. But also bear in mind that I need to be able
    to ensure that it can be removed intact and that we can find a place for
    it in the new design where it will look natural. If you approve, I will
    leave you to look around by yourselves but will be on hand should you need
    me and when you are ready to discuss your choice."</para>

    <para>With that, Theodorus bowed politely then withdrew to continue his
    supervision of his workmen. Out of the corner of his eye he saw his
    clients regard each other for a long moment then exchange a few words
    before the Burgermeester gave a quick, decisive nod and they turned
    towards the open door and slowly made their way inside the house that was
    no longer their home.</para>

    <para>He has expected it to take them a considerable length of time to
    tour the property and reach a decision so was taken by surprise when,
    barely fifteen minutes later, he noticed one of his men hurrying in his
    direction with a message from the Burgemeester requesting his attendance.
    He located his client and Mevrouwe le Fevre de Montigny by almost bowling
    them over as he entered the lage huis voorkamer. Both were calmly
    contemplating a large section of wooden screening which incorporated two
    doorways and a number of etched glass panels. It was rather larger than
    Theodorus had foreseen but he could see the attraction as it was both
    decorative and functional with the benefit that it met his needs as a
    builder. It was an easy assumption that the screen held some significance
    for his clients since they had agreed upon it so rapidly. So, before
    matters went any further he needed to make a detailed inspection to make
    sure that this quite delicate installation could be removed without peril
    and that it was sound in itself. The last thing any of them would want
    would be to introduce a pest, such as woodworm, into a brand new building.
    However, on the face of it, they had made an excellent choice. So much so
    that he wondered why he hadn't spotted its potential himself!</para>

    <para>Bidding farewell to his clients with the promise of letting them
    know his verdict next day, Theodorus set about his inspection but not
    before he had instructed his men to make haste to remove the roof since
    the upper floors were not involved in the preservation of the screen.
    Although his initial impression of the soundness of the piece was
    favourable, he had a secondary motivation in taking time to reach a final
    decision. He wanted to test out the local man appointed as his second in
    command.,Cornelis Straver. Cornelis came from a long line of timmermen,
    carpenters, by trade from a well respected village family and was assumed
    to have some expertise to bring to the matter at hand. However, he was
    only nineteen years old and had never been involved in a big project
    before. Theodorus wanted to take the opportunity to test Cornelis out and,
    all being well, begin to forge good working elations with him.</para>

    <para/>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title/>

    <para>Cornelis was employed on the carving of a sturdy, oak door for one
    of the high street houses when the messenger from Heer Hooft reached him.
    He wasn't due to begin work on the Bisdom van Vliet new house until
    construction started and wondered why he had been called upon now. His
    father looked up from his work and, with a slight smile, nodded that it
    was alright for Cornelis to leave the job he was doing, saying,</para>

    <para>"Go! But best clean yourself up a bit first!"</para>

    <para>All the family knew that it was important that Cornelis make a good
    first impression on Heer Hooft. He put away his tools in their proper
    places in the workshop, as was the disciplined habit of his trade, then
    crossed the yard and went into the family's cottage. In the kitchen he
    took one of the buckets of water his mother had lined up after she had
    filled them at the river that morning. He filled a basin at the sink,
    removed his shirt and splashed himself in the cold water down to his
    waist, drying himself off on the discarded shirt. His mother had fetched
    him a clean shirt and a comb for his hair.</para>

    <para>Aware that it would have been easy for the young carpenter to be
    overawed by a man old enough to be his father as well as well versed in
    the construction of Haagse style houses, his mother sought to calm his
    nerves before this sudden and unexpected meeting. As she fussed round him
    she reminded him that,</para>

    <para>"Your father never had much regard for plasterers, it being an
    inferior trade to ours. And you know what they say about Haagenars? All
    show and no substance."</para>

    <para>"Oh, mother! I'll be alright! After all, he's just a man like any
    other!"</para>

    <para>With that, he headed back outside, collected his satchel of basic
    tools from its peg in the workshop, slung it across his body and set off
    to see what Heer Hooft wanted. Arriving at the site, he was directed into
    the Lage Huis where he found Heer Hooft examining a painted and glazed
    screen. Cornelis removed his hat, stuffing it in his bag, before taking
    the hand stretched out towards him. After exchanging pleasantries,
    Cornelis remembering to congratulate his senior on the recent birth of his
    daughter and been assured that mother and baby were thriving, they got
    down to the matter at hand.</para>

    <para>Cornelis understood that his carpenter's knowledge to be applied to
    forming a judgement as to the viability of removing the screen intact with
    a view to using it in the new house. Both men applied themselves to a
    close scrutiny of the state of the wood, Cornelis begging leave to scratch
    away the paint in places in order to be assured of the integrity of the
    raw wood concealed beneath. Having concluded their survey, both agreed
    that there were no signs of infestation on rot which would preclude the
    introduction of the screen into a new construction.</para>

    <para>Next, Cornelis investigated the means by which the screen had been
    inserted into its current position. After a while, he turned to Heer Hooft
    with a question in mind,</para>

    <para>"Do I understand correctly that this building is to be otherwise
    demolished?"</para>

    <para>Receiving an answer in the affirmative, he continued,</para>

    <para>"This screen is an original dating back to the time of King Louis XV
    of France and was put in place when the Lage Huis was built by Theodorus
    Bisdom in the middle of the 18th Century. This means that the screen is a
    classical piece and the it is important to preserve it if at all possible
    In addition, as you probably know, Burgermeester Theodorus Bisdom used his
    wealth to expand the family home and acquire the Slot van Vliet and
    surrounding lands. It was his investment that gave the Bisdom van Vliet's
    their full name as well as establishing them as important patriarchs. So,
    screen is a reminder of the rise of the family so not only an good choice
    for what it is in itself but also what it means to the current family
    members."</para>

    <para>Heer Hooft expressed his surprise at the significance of what he
    heard and complimented Cornelis on his knowledgeableness. Cornelis
    returned to the thrust of his original question,</para>

    <para>" The only way such a delicate and old piece can be safely removed
    is by careful removal of its surrounding structures. In other words, it
    will need painstaking excavation rather than the usual level of care
    applied to demolition work."</para>

    <para>Heer Hooft acknowledged what he was being told and that it would
    mean slow, painstaking and, of course, expensive work the cost of which
    would need to be put to Burgemeester Bisdom van Vliet in balance to the
    significance of the screen. Cornelis had proved his worth and impressed
    his senior with his confidence and maturity during their first working
    encounter. This encouraged Heer Hooft to further include Cornelis in the
    next phase of the screen project, namely where, and how, in the design of
    the new house the screen could be put to use. In order to further this
    discussion, he conducted Cornelis to his makeshift office where the plans
    for the new house were unrolled onto a large, plain wood table, the
    corners weighted down with fragments of complex plasterwork.</para>

    <para>Both men poured over the ground floor plan, each suggesting
    possibilities but rejecting them all. Cornelis was concerned that there
    should be no structural load on the delicate, if not quite fragile, screen
    and Heer Hooft raising matters of the utility of the public rooms,
    possible privacy issues and the undeniable fact that they just did not fit
    with the modern architectural style. Cornelis found it increasingly easy
    to voice his thoughts as they occurred to him and that he could accept the
    older man's sometimes opposing views without feeling diminished. In short,
    the two men seemed to have got off on a sound footing.</para>

    <para>Turning to the plan of the upper floor, there developed an
    optimistic atmosphere. The architect had divided the floor into two,
    separate appartments: one for Burgermeester Bisdom van Vliet and another
    for his daughter and her husband. So, whilst the public rooms were shared,
    there were private quarters upstairs for the two generations of Bisdom van
    Vliet. Since each apartment had a separate entrance from the spacious area
    at the top of the main staircase, they came to the resolution of dividing
    the screen so that part formed the entrance to one apartment and the rest
    the entrance to the other.</para>

    <para>Now Cornelis needed to look at how the screen might be divided
    whilst Heer Hooft persuaded the architect to alter his plans. The latter
    proved easier than anticipated since the architect had harboured some
    uneasiness about the upper hall, worried that it was too dark. The only
    natural light in his plans came from a window at the head of the stairs
    which, although the same large expanse of glass as all the other windows,
    was really not enough to penetrate the centrally located space of the
    upper hall. The glazed and white painted panels he was being asked to
    incorporate into his design suddenly prompted a radical change of
    perspective. The theme of light paint and maximum glazing could be the
    answer to lighting up the whole area!</para>

    <para/>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title/>

    <para/>
  </section>
</chapter>
