<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd">
<chapter version="5.0" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
  <title>Summer 1871</title>

  <section>
    <para>Joahn's sea chest had stood next to Paulina's trunks and boxes in
    the voorkammer of Van den Boschstratt 12 as the couple made their
    farewells on a freezing January morning. Four months had now passed since
    that day when the Den Haag house had been shut up and Paulina moved back
    to the family home in Haastrecht. Paulina had gradually taken over her
    mother's tasks as Maria's poor health forced her to relinquish them bit by
    bit. Once settled back into her old room, Paulina had found it easy to
    fall back into the old routines and habits of the Haastrecht life she had
    led before her marriage. Indeed, she found that for long periods she could
    forget that she was married, especially with the added burden of all her
    mother's work. This state of affairs made it easier to bear the total
    absence of any communication for Johan and distracted her from her anxiety
    for his safety. From time to time she felt a pang of remorse at just how
    easily she had abandoned her recent life style which made her feel as
    though she had rejected her marriage to Johan.</para>

    <para>For all that, things at the Bisdom van Vleit house were not quite
    the same as they had been two years previously, and not just because
    Paulina herself had been changed by her married life (how?). She found her
    father to be even more busy with his Rotterdam business interests which
    were causing him some concern since profits were not holding up as well as
    he wpuld have hoped. At home, his political involvements were not pleasing
    everyone locally so he had found himself the subject of a number of
    ungrateful lampoons. His progressive ideas for land drainage did not meet
    with universal favour, especially his plans for the installation of steam
    pumping engines. He was encountering resistance to such technological
    advances so keeping this project moving forward required his constant
    vigilance and the devotion of both time and energy in chivying people
    along in order to get the work done.</para>

    <para>Once Paulina was installed and doing everything that was required it
    was time to arrange a spa cure for Maria, whose complaints were
    problematically hard to specify that the type of cure that would benefit
    her was not easy to identify. She said that she lacked her usual energy
    and certainly seemed to need to rest more than ever before. Her appetitie
    was sometimes slight so she was becoming thinner and suffered with
    irregularity in her habits. Climbing the stairs made her gasp for air yet
    she had no cough. The doctor could find no diagnosis and wondered aloud if
    she might simply be affected by a nervous disorder. Paulina thought this
    unlikely as her mother had always been a strong woman although she had to
    concede that her mother had been working increasingly hard, as her own
    experience of stepping into her shoes attested. Eventually they settled on
    Bad Ems as the solution beacause of its ease of access by train, spa
    waters efficacious for chest and digestive problems, stunning environment
    and social cachet. The end of the Franco-Prussian War in early May meant
    that travel across the border was once again reliable and safe So,
    preparations completed, Paulina and her father saw Maria and her entourage
    off with high hopes for the benefits of the cure before both returned to
    their duties.</para>

    <para>Paulina soon received a letter from her mother giving an account of
    the regime at her hotel. It did not sound either very appealing or very
    restful and Paulina was glad that she did not need such a 'cure'. The day
    began with a glass of water from the Kraechenbrunnen spring to aeraeted he
    mucous membranes of the respiratory tract and a glass from the
    Kesselbrunnen spring to stimulate the secretions of the digestive tract.
    The action of the latter was assisted by a gentle stroll beside the River
    Lahn whose real attraction seemed to come from the opportunity to spot the
    royalty and famous artists from europe and beyond who happened to be in
    town at the time. More water was drunk before lunch and in the late
    afternoon with further application of spa waters through inhalation and
    warm baths. Eating and socialising, it seemed, left little time to retreat
    to the quiet of her room. At the conclusion of her letter, Paulina's
    mother sought to reassure her that she was confident in the positive
    effects of the cure over the ensuing weeks.</para>

    <para>It was shortly after this letter that word reached Paulina and
    Marcellus that Maria had been unable to complete her stroll in the spa
    gardens despite the assistance of a walking stick and the support of her
    maid. A bath chair had been sent for and she had not felt up to leaving
    her room since having been helped back to the hotel. Paulina an her father
    made arrangements to go to Bad Ems to see Maria but felt no sense of
    urgency or gravity about their visit, each convincing the other that
    Maria's collapse was to be explained by the results of all her exertions
    at home finally catching up with her now that she could relax at last. The
    reality was that by the time Maria had arrived in Bad Ems it was already
    too late for her to recover.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title/>

    <para>Paulina and her father arrived in Bad Ems fully expecting to witness
    Maria making steady improvement as the cure combined with complete rest
    had their beneficial effects. Once Paulina saw the Bad Ems for herself she
    was even more convinced of its restorative properties. Here the River Lahn
    flowed through a steep, wooded valley between the Westerwold and Taunus
    mountains providing a magnificent backdrop to the town. A striking river
    frontage had been created by the architecture of the Staadsbad, Kursaal
    and Casino as well as the opulent hotels all aound. Grand villas were
    colonising the less sunny southern bank and churches of all denominations
    seemed to be springing up everwhere to cater for the varied spiritual
    needs of the shifting population. She quickly determined that such
    physical beauty combined with a tranquil ambience could not fail to
    restore her mother in both mind and body.</para>

    <para>Indeed, her mother rallied upon their arrival, managing to eat a
    little of the delicious food on offer as well as drinking the prescribed
    glasses of mineral waters. She seemed to rest peacefully in her room after
    meals, so Paulina and her father ocupied themselves with outings which
    took them increasingly further away from the hotel. At times, she even
    felt as though she were on an adventurous trip just like her excursion
    through the Alps or her honeymoon. She forgot about her mother's state of
    health for hors at a time so preoccupied was she with all the new
    experiences Bad Ems and its surrounding brought to her.</para>

    <para>At first, Paulina and her father took strolls around the town where
    everywhere they encountered fashionably dressed members of Europe's
    royalty, aristocracy and wealthy classes could be seen taking the air on
    the riverside promenades or exploring the many other attractions on offer.
    Paulina found herself even more fascinated by the less regal and more
    unusual residents of the town. Chatting with new acquaintances, she
    discovered that a number of well-known writers and artists were there to
    take advantage of the creative atmosphere and ready source of patronage.
    The lone, tall stooping figure of Turgenev, and the more attractive
    Dostoyevsky accompanied by his second wife, Anna, were pointed out to her
    as memeber sof the Russian crowd. However, most of the whisperings amongst
    her fellow guests related to craggy old Richard Wagner and his wife,
    Cosima, more than twenty years youger than him, and the scandal
    surrounding their previously adulkterous relationship and brood of
    illegitimate children. The rather gruff-looking Victor Hugo was said to be
    taking the cure to aid his recovery from near starvation during the
    Prussian siege of Paris during which, paulina was alarmed to learn, he was
    forced to eat animals from the zoo. She listened with mounting horror to
    the romantic story of the death of his favourite daughter when she fell
    out of boat into the River Seine and was drogged under the water by the
    weight of her sodden skirts, her young husband joining her in death as he
    entered the water trying to save her.</para>

    <para>Exploring further, they climber up to the Concordiaturm to enjoy the
    splendid view of the Lahn valley from the viewing platform atop the tower.
    Paulina found this excursion quite exhausting so was glad that the next
    trip was by boat along the river followed by a train journey further along
    the Lahn Valley Railway. The train took them to the city of lLmburg, the
    track winding along beside the river, halting at seven stations before
    their detsination. There was plenty of beautiful scenery to admire from
    the carriage window, but the elevn tunnels which interrupted the view
    provided a modicum of thrill also.At Limburg they hired a cab to drive
    them around the</para>

    <para>The Altstadt ("Old Town") boasts a fine cathedral and is full of
    narrow streets with timber-frame houses, dating mainly from the 17th and
    18th centuries. That's why it is located on the German Timber-Frame Road.
    Limburger Dom, one of the most complete creations of Late Romanesque
    architecture. It was printed on the reverse of the 1,000 Deutsche Mark
    note from the second series,[2] which was in circulation from 1960 to
    1989. The cathedral was recently renovated and painted to reflect its
    original appearance. Limburger Schloss, built in early 13th century by
    Gerlach von Ysenburg Burgmannenhaus, built about 1544; serves as a museum
    today St. Anna-Kirche (church), stained glass from third fourth of 14th
    century with eighteen scenes from the New Testament Old Lahn Bridge, from
    1315, place where the Via Publica (road) crossed the Lahn In the Old Town
    stand many timber-frame houses from the 13th to 19th centuries. One
    peculiarity seen among the timber-framed houses of Limburg is the "hall
    house" from the High Middle Ages, which has a great hall on the ground
    floor. When restoration work began in the Old Town in 1972, the houses
    were carefully restored. Among the best known timber-frame houses are:
    Haus Kleine Rütsche 4, narrowest spot on the historic trade road between
    Frankfurt and Cologne, whose breadth is written at the Haymarket
    (Heumarkt) in Cologne Haus der sieben Laster (“House of the Seven Vices”)
    at Brückengasse 9, built in 1567,[3] timber-frame house with carvings
    showing Christianity's seven deadly sins, namely pride, greed, envy, lust,
    gluttony, wrath and sloth Werner-Senger-Haus, a beautiful stone hall house
    with timber-framed façade dating from the 13th century Houses at the
    fishmarket. The square's name in the 13th century was still Fismart ("Yarn
    Market" or "Wool Market") in the Limburg dialect, and it was the Limburg
    wool weavers' trading centre[4] Römer 2-4-6, Germany’s oldest freestanding
    house; in the garden a mikvah was found Rathaus ("Town Hall"), built in
    1899 "Huttig" (town wall tower remnant) Former noble estate of the Counts
    of Walderdorff at Fahrgasse 5</para>

    <para>They recounted all their adventures to Maria who seemed interested
    in everything they did. Paulina suggested to her father that one of their
    local discoveries might be something that her mother could be persuad,
    Fench ambassador to Prussia, during their famed conversation in the Kupark
    the previous July. Otto Van Bismark's rather manipulative account of what
    was reutedly a very friendly talk was known as the Ems Dispatch, its blunt
    tone was generally regarded as having triggered the Francvo-Prussian was
    that had ended only a metter of days earlier. Maria's doctor was consulted
    about the proposed outing He pronounced that a short excursion in the warm
    summer air and with good company could only do her good as she seemed to
    be on the road to recovery. Paulina's father arranged a dog cart into
    which Maria was helped then, Paulina and her father walking alongside, was
    driven to the very spot where this diplomatic event took place. Now
    confident of the eventual her mother's restored health, Paulina felt
    relaxed and thoroughly entered into the spirit of the afternoon.</para>

    <para>Paulina and her father made arrangements for their return to
    Haastrecht on the following day. As soon as they had made their farewells
    Maria collapsed, exhausted by her efforts on behalf of her husband and
    daughter. She had not wanted them to see how weak and ill she felt as it
    would only cause them to worry and that was pointless as there was nothing
    they, or anybody, could do to change the situation. She soon became
    confined to her room, then took to her bed. The doctors and nurses could
    plainly see that she was slipping away, despite their best efforts and
    previous optimism. Paulina and Macellus had barely had time to settle down
    back at Haastrecht before a further summonds to Bad Ems arrived. Still
    unprepared for the gravity ofthe situation, they made no haste in
    arranging for their return to Bad Ems. On 7th June Maria died quietly and
    alone, aged 67.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title/>

    <para>If Paulina had thought herself busy before, then the death of her
    mother left her with not a second to spare in the day. Organising a
    funeral had the added complication of Maria's body being in Ems but her
    burial to take place in Haastrecht, some considerable distance away and
    across the border between two nations. It was agreed that Marcellus would
    return home in order to take up his duties there as best he could in the
    circumstances. Paulina was to remain in Germany to take care of
    formalities there before accompanying her mother's body back to
    Haastrecht. Before his departure Paulina had armed her father with a list
    of things he needed to do once back home but she rather suspected that
    pressing matters of other kinds would distract him from giving her
    instructions his full attention. She was fairly confident that her
    father's friendship with the Pastor and good business relationship with
    their lawyer would progress some matters. What was less certain was the
    commissioning of a new grave stone and the making of arrangements for its
    installation, not to mention the detailed preparations for the interrement
    itself. She would have to keep and eye on him if everything was to go
    smoothly.</para>

    <para>Paulina returned to her hotel room and the many tasks which now vied
    for her time and attention. Etiquette dictated that she should only appear
    in public wearing mourning clothes but she had nothing suitable with her.
    A local seamstress was summoned on the recommendation of the hotel
    manager. The woman gace assurances that she could produce sufficient
    garments to satisfy society by the next day. Measurements were taken,
    fabrics chosen and designs recommended with facilitating a speedy outcome
    in mind. Then the miliner arrived with a selection of appropriate hat and
    veils from which Paulina selected something that would sit as decorously
    as was feasible atop her unruly hair. Fortunately she had gloves and boots
    in black so did not need to trouble herself to acquire these. Attention to
    her appearance was but an irritating interruption to the constant stream
    of correspondence that flowed from Paulina's pen, including instructions
    for further garments and accessories from her own seamstress which were to
    await her arrival back home.</para>

    <para>Having sent out for a quantity of black edged notepaper and
    envelopes, she began the work of writing to all the names on the list of
    family and friends she had compiled, informing them of Maria's passing.
    Once she had word from her father of the date and time of the burial she
    could pass these details on to the close family members who would attend
    the house for prayer and meditation led by the Pastor before moving on to
    the burial itself. Although the family had a vault inside the church, a
    law passed in 1829 forbade further interior burials so Maria would be
    interred just outside the church walls in ground which was once the choir
    of the old church which burnt down in 1624 but was never completely
    re-buit. Hopefully, this would still give access to the family vault just
    the other side of the church wall thus meeting the need of the family
    whilst staying within the law. Oh, how Paulina wished that she could
    include Joahn in her letters! She would just have to make do with dashing
    off notes to her father as matters requiring his attention came to her
    mind.</para>

    <para>It was not all writing, however. There was a doctor to be seen in
    order to obtain a death certificate and medical documents necessary to
    transporting a corpse back to Holland. He did, of course, have to be paid,
    too. Then undertakers were summoned and the business of selecting a
    suitable casket (kist) gone through. Paulina tried to choose something
    which she though would have met with her mother's approval and which
    reflected the family's station in life. The undertaker semed to endorse
    the outcome before departing with haste in order to prepare the deceased
    for her last journey by suitable preservation, dressing her hair and
    applying the make-up which would lessen the waxy look of death and create
    the illusion of a living complexion. Lastly, with the help of his wife, he
    would clothe her in the garments and jewelery which Paulina had provided
    before arrangeing her in the casket and sealing it for
    transportation.</para>

    <para>This final journey itself necessitated a not inconsiderable feat of
    organisation but the undertaker was no stranger to the deaths of
    foreigners in Bad Emms so knew the ropes. First, a hearse and mourner's
    carriage would convey the parties to the railway station, a short distance
    but the proprietes of a glass hearse and black carriage both drawn by
    plumed black horses were observed. A floral tribute of suitable size would
    top the casket and must be made using the most expensive and rare blooms.
    Two chief mourners would walk before the funeral courtage and remain at
    the bereaved's disposal throughout the journey to Gouda where a local
    undertaker would receive the party. Pall bearers would follow the cortege
    ready to transfer the coffin from hearse to train, then between trains at
    Koblenz, Koln and Utrecht. These men would also stand guard outside the
    compartment containing the coffin to ensure the deased's privacy and
    safety. All these mourners would need to be provided with a compartment
    where they could take rest and refreshment on both the outward and return
    legs of their journey. Paulina's own food, drink and personal comfort also
    needed to be arranged. Things began to fall into place when her new
    clothes arrived and were to her liking. Up until now she had not left her
    room so, now that she was suitably attired, she was glad to go out for
    some fresh air and to receive and acknowledge in person the condolences of
    fellow guests. But she only began to properly relax once the travel home
    had all been planned down to the last detail, inlcuding the choice of her
    personal menus and stipulation of her meal times. There were even
    contingencies in place in the event of missed connections, inefficiencies
    on the part of railway staff or other unforseen delays.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title/>

    <para>It was a long, grim day for Paulina as she accompanied her Mother's
    casket (kist) back to Gouda during which she retreated into herself. Her
    habitual recourse of writing in her journal, composing poetry and writing
    letters to her friends was denied her by the jolting and swaying of the
    train which rendered even her large and fluid script distorted into
    illegibility. Even the diversion of reading was denied her as focussing on
    the unstable page brought on feelings of nausea, even were she in a frame
    of mind to concentrate on the story. So, she spent most of the journey
    gazing out of the compartment window without registering the changeing
    landscape or the towns and cities passing by.</para>

    <para>Finally arriving at Gouda, her wits were so dulled that she allowed
    herself to be scorted onto the platform by the Chief Mourner on duty and
    passed into the care of his opposite number from the Gouda firm. She felt
    herself being handed on to yet another man who had the boldness to put his
    arm around her shoulder. She suddenly jerked into awareness at this
    unwarranted intrusion upon her person, experiencing a moment of utter
    confusion as a familiar voice struggled for recognition and location in
    the man in such intimate contact with her. It was Theo! At last she could
    let go of the need to hold herself up under the burdens of the previous
    days, weeks and months and relinquish all to Theo's care. It was such a
    relief to find herself safely ensconsed inside The Haven.</para>

    <para>Paulina soon realized that Theo had in fact taken charge of
    everything at Haastrecht. He had taken Marcellus to The Haven and she was
    shocked to see him looking so worn and ashen, barely able to raise a smile
    at the sight of his daughter. It seems that he had been carrying out his
    business and public duties as usual, preferring to keep busy rather than
    sit and rhuminate on his loss.Paulina felt much the same, being of the
    opinion that life goes on and it does nobdy any good to simply succumb to
    emotion. Unfortuntaley, she found that this is just what Aggie had done.
    As soon as she saw her sister, Aggie fell against her in floods of tears,
    clinging to Paulina like a drowning woman. Reluctantly, Paulina put her
    arms around her step-sister and tried to summon the energy to comfort her
    whilst willing her to pull herself together. In the end it was Theo who
    gently detatched his sobbing wife, helped her to a seat in an armchair
    then wrapping her in a shawl and putting her feet up on a footstool. His
    solicitousness caused Paulina a sharp stab of regret that Johan was
    absent.</para>

    <para>As if reading her mind, Theo came to her with an account of the
    efforts which he ahd amade to try and reach Johan through his contacts,
    calling in some of the favours he was owed. Although nothing was certain,
    he had a feeling that a message had reached Johan's ship and that it might
    be possible, but not to raise her hopes too high, that he could be
    discretely landed somewhere. Clearly Thoe knew more about Johan's
    activities than she did, or he had previously divulged, but it did mean
    that he could give her good news about this welfare despite all the other
    uncertainties. For now, it was a relief to Paulina to be back among her
    family with her burden shared.</para>

    <para>Cook had prepared a selection of savouries and cakes for a light
    supper which the maid had laid on a small table in the salon. Theo pressed
    a small glass of sweet wine on both Paulina and Aggies before pouring a
    healthy measure of cognac for Marcellus and himself. The diminished family
    groupArranged themselves around the table then toyed with the food whilst
    managing to make small talk by dint of long-establishes social habit.
    Paulina soon felt her eyelids begining to droop and had to beg to be
    excused to her room. There she found that her own maid from home had
    already laid out her nightgown and prepared hot water so that she may wash
    away the soot of the trains and the grime of travel. Grateful to feel
    clean and be released from her corsets, Paulina was soon fast asleep in
    the arms of a large, soft feather bed.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title/>

    <para>In the early hours of the morning word had reached The Haven that
    Johan had arrived at his brother's house and had elected to rest there
    before making the journey to Gouda in time to join the funeral cortege for
    the journey to Haastrecht. Gillis had been shocked by the sight of his
    brother. Unsurprisingly, Johan was salt encrusted, sooty, and generally
    dirty but he also smelled rather repulsively of rancid fish oil, not to
    mention neglected bodily hygeine. But more than this, he looked far more
    unhealthy than could be accounted for by his arduous journey home or the
    rigours and deprivations of life at sea. He had lost weight but that
    wasn't the worst of it. His face beneath the beard growth was covered in
    small ulcers and scabs which he passed off as salt burns from the lashing
    of sea spray whilst on deck. He vehemently denied feeling ill saying that
    he just needed time to recover himself.</para>

    <para>By the time Johan presented himself to Paulina later that morning he
    had bathed, shaved and was dressed in his good, black clothes. A faint
    fishy odour hung about his person despite the liberal application of
    cologne in an attempt to cover it. He had also tried to conceal the mess
    that was made of the skin on his face by shaving across a rash of small
    scabs and lesions by the application of pigmented ointment but this hadn't
    been entirely successful as it created a complexion of a most unnatural
    colour and texture. Furthermore, beneath the fumes of cognac on his breath
    there lurked a rottenness from within. Paulina had expected to fall into
    his arms after so long a separation but found him rather repulsive. He
    didn't force the matter, either, creating an atmosphere of strained
    politeness between them. Paulina wondered just how much he was hoping to
    keep hidden from her than was necessary and despite his protestsations of
    opennes when she had broached the subject of his secrecy back in Den Haag.
    Indeed, she was quite distracted from the purpose of the day, having to be
    shephered through it all by Johan and Theo.</para>

    <para>During the carriage journey to Haastrecht Paulina sat between
    Marcellus and Johan in what promissed to be a leaden silence because of
    the straied atmosphere and the Marcellus's growing morbid pre-occupation
    with the hearse in front of them and the the casket it contained. Then
    Johan suddenly decided to entertain father and daughter with a lively
    account of his tortuous journey back to Gouda. This began with a hazardous
    transfer from his ship to a small, local fishing boat in a rolling sea,
    followed by an uncomfortable run to the fishing port ofZoutkamp on the
    coast to the north of Groningen,. This gave him the opportunity to explain
    away the state of his face by means of a dramatic enactment of being
    repeatedly stung by salt water spray. Once ashore, he had engaged in canny
    negotiations with the skipper of a Tjalk (?) conveying smoked eels to
    market in Groningen before he was granted passage. Keen to be under way,
    the skipper had frustratingly elected to wait for the most favourable run
    of the tide to assist the sails in carrying them along the Reitdiep. Johan
    feared that being in close quarters with the smoked eels for such a length
    of time might have left him with an unfortunate fragrance, a point with
    which father and daughter could only tacitly concur. From Groningen he
    could reached Rotterdam by train but a badly timed conncetion meant that
    this seemed to take forever. After just a short time with his brother, he
    had needed to leave at the crack of dawn to make the train for Gouda in
    order to be in time to be with them before they left for
    Haastrecht.</para>

    <para>Grudgingly, Marcellus and Paulina had been distracted by Johan's
    recounting of his tale, which had managed to consume the whole of the ride
    to Haastrecht. Nevertheless, they were glad to arrive and gain release
    form the close confines of the carriage. The Pastor was waiting at the
    house to greet them, ushering them into the grand salon where Otto and
    Adelaide were waiting. Paulina registered their recoil at the sight of
    Johan in the instant before they regained control of their epressions. She
    surmised that they were thinking that he looked more embalmed than her
    mother, whose closed casket meant that they would not be able to make the
    actual comparison.</para>

    <para>Poor old Oma, who had not expected to outlive one of her sons much
    less her daughter-in-law, was wheeled in by bath chair to join the company
    as they sat round for the Pastor to lead their prayers and prompt the
    direction of their silent contemplations. Then, Oma having fallen asleep,
    was taken back to her room before the rest of the party set out for the
    churchyard. The Pall Bearers hoisted Maria's casket onto their shoulders
    and the Chief Mourner led the sedate procession the short distance to
    where the grave had been opened ready to receive its offering. Judging
    from the most unpleasant smell hanging over the churchyard, the family
    vault had been penetrated allowing Maria to be lowered into the ground to
    join the Bisdom-van-Vliet's who had predeceased her. The Pastor led his
    congregation in the Lord's Prayer before the funeral party turned to
    return to the house allowing the gravediggers to cover the coffin with
    earth and seal in the smell of the stinking rich. Before the family went
    their separate ways to resume their daily lives marcellus laid before them
    a substantial meal accompanied by plenty to drink in order to to sustain
    them for the start of their journey.</para>

    <para>Once Marcellus, Paulina and Johan has bade farewell to the rest of
    the funeral party, a sense of emptiness and malaise afflicted each of
    them. They shared the anti-climax at having no focus for their activities
    and attention now that the event for which they had expended so much
    energy in preparation was over. Now what should they do with themselves?
    Marcellus would ordinarily have gone back to his work but desisted so as
    to honour of the memory of his wife. Paulina was also thinking of what she
    needed to do in order to catch up with the management of the house and
    estates which had surely been neglected during her absence. Mostly,
    though, she was pre-occupied with trying to make sense of the state that
    Johan had got into. As for Johan, he sought to avoid for as long as
    possible the inevitable questioning by his wife, ideally until his skin
    had a chance to heal so that there was no outward sign to give force and
    direction to her inquiries. He wanted to be alone with a few good,
    Haastrecht cigars and a bottle or two of Marcellus's best Cognac.</para>

    <para>After a period of desultry conversation all three agreed that they
    should retire in order to begin the process of recovery from their
    exertions with a period of uninterrupted rest and, hopefully, a good
    night's sleep. Johan took his leave of father and daughter with an almost
    unmannerly haste then shut himself up in his quarters in a way that
    clearly signalled that he did not wish to be disturbed. Marcellus and
    Paulina exchanged glances registering their surprise at Johan's departure
    but they neither discussed nor commented on his motivation. Instead, they
    spent a quiet half hour in reminiscing about Maria whilst permitting
    themselves a few tears for the loss of her. Then, having released the
    tensions of the day, they took their individual thoughts off to
    bed.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title/>

    <para>Maria was barely cold in her grave before the churchyard beside her
    was disturbed in preparation for Oma's burial. Once again, the family
    gathered in prayer and reflection at the house. Once again, they stood in
    the churchyard to watch the small coffin containing Oma's shrivelled and
    shrunken corpse being lowered into the foetid extension of the family
    vault. Once again, they dined until replete before going their separate
    ways. But this time there was no subsequent sense of a void left by the
    person now gone. Instead, a sense of relief that was only be tinged with
    sadness. At the age of 84, it had been Oma's time. The force of the woman
    who had ruled the household in the wake of her husband's untimely death,
    had continued to make her presence felt after Marcellus's marriage brought
    another woman into the house and then gone on to hold her own in the trio
    of mother, wife and daughter that followed had long dissipated as she
    became increasingly frail and infirm then, for the most part, confined to
    her room. They had gradually become accustomed to her absence but not
    innured to the growing suffering from which only death had the power to
    relieve her.</para>

    <para>Another difference between Maria's funeral and Oma's came later in
    the day when Paulina and Johan shared the same bed. Over the six weeks
    that intervened between the two funerals Johan's skin had returned to its
    normal condition, he had regained a healthy-looking physique and regained
    the confidence to tackle the demands of marital intimacy, both physical
    and otherwise. The odours about his person had returned to their usual
    combination of cologne, cigars and cognac in various stages of staleness,
    contributing to his person being generally more approachable. Paulina had
    not quite recovered from the horror of the realzation that the skin rash
    attributed to salt burns had, in fact, covered all of his torso as well.
    She was astute enough to see that he had been trying to pass it off as
    something far more trivial than it actually was, and to form the view that
    only some contaigious disease could have led him to keep her at arm's
    length for several weeks. His complete recovery allowed her enough
    optimism to conclude that whatever the illness had been, it was now a
    thing of the past. She could not quite ignore the nagging recollection of
    that invoice from a strange Rotterdam doctor and Johan never quite
    regained even the semblance of his earlier interest in his wife.</para>

    <para>In fact, nothing was ever be the same for the Bisdom van Vliet's
    after Oma's death. Paulina and Johan would soon return to their home in
    Den Haag leaving Marcellus to wander the empty rooms of the old familie
    huis trying to escape the fact that he was now all alone there. Of course,
    it was only right that Paulina should return to her own house, espeially
    now that Johan seemed to have retrned from his duties at sea. Now that
    there was no possibility of Maria ever returning, more permananet
    arrangments had been put in place to cover her roles in managing house and
    estates. A man of business had been engaged for the latter and seemed to
    be keeping on top of things. Marcellus had also taken on a housekeeper
    after interviewing many suitable women but rejecting them all until he
    finally could find no possible grounds on which to continue to deny that
    he needed the services of such a person. So far, these new arrangements
    had been to his satisfaction. Not that he cared much for his domestic
    comfort now that he was bereft of family, but that the management of the
    lands and estates was no longer to be conducted at the grace and favour of
    his daughter came unexpectedly as a relief.</para>

    <para>Paulina was glad to be released from the heavy burdens of filling
    her mother's shoes. She had plenty to manage on her own behalf now that
    her mother's will had been enacted. Maria had bequeathed her five houses,
    two warehouses, two farms, five orchards, a mill, a stable and meadow and
    hay lands so she was a woman of property in her own right now, although in
    a modest way compared to her father's property and lands. She felt that
    she had neglected her friends over the past months and wanted, neigh
    needed, to see them again to gain succour from their amity. before they
    left Haastrecht she took the oppportunity to spend some time first with
    Mientje Blanken, whom she considered to be her very best friend, then with
    Helena and Cornelia Droost. Their sympathy with her loss gave her much
    succour which itself helped her to put her worries about Johan into some
    sort of perspective, although she did not divulge any hint of her marital
    situation to her spinster friends.</para>

    <para>All too soon, Paulina and Johan departed for Den Haag leaving
    Marcellus feeling very alone in the rambling, old familie huis. In a
    matter of a few months he had gone from feeling his life complicated by
    the presence of three women in his home to missing their company and the
    civilising touches a woman brought to the house. He wandered through the
    rooms now devoid of human occupancy since even the servants kept away,
    there being little for them to do most of the time, almost feeling a
    stranger in his own home. It was as if the house no longer belonged to him
    and he began to see it as an outsider might. The old rooms were now so
    outdated that they could almost be museum exhibits. Even the new part of
    the house seemed slightly shabby and old-fashioned as the sunlight through
    the windows threw a spotlight onto every little scuff and stain. He took
    his meals alone, as he had done many times recently, but now he knew there
    was no Oma dozing in her room and no Maria to return to him from an erand
    or visit. Only Paulina remained a possible companion. Whilst she had been
    living back at home he had grown used to her companionship despite her
    morose temperament. Now she had gone back to her life as a married woman
    and some else's companion. He felt bereft.</para>

    <para>His natural recourse in times of personal disquiet was to seek the
    creative upslift he got from his work, from seeing a project through from
    the first idea to the final product. Normal duties were a distraction,
    yes, but now her needed more so he turned his attention to his latest
    grand scheme - the pump house which would keep the polders of Lopikerward
    drained. Marcellus had been working in partnership with Lopik's
    burgermeester to apply a modern solution to the flooding problems in this
    area caused by the conjunction of sinking peatlands and rising river
    levels. The mills had been coping by pushing water into a holding pond
    behind Haastrecht then discharging it into the Hollandse IJssel through
    small locks into the harbour then onto the river. But the mills now needed
    some help, especially when the wind did not blow to turn their
    sails.</para>

    <para>Marcellus had joined a party of dignitaries on a visit to the new
    Cruquius pumping station, one of three that had been built to drain the
    vast Haarlemermeer lake to the south west of Amsterdam. It had been a
    truely inspirational visit, not least because the drainage was the first
    project to be accomplished, not by the use of windmills at all, but soley
    by the use of steam powered pumps. Quite a departure for Dutch drainage
    engineers for which they had the English to thank with their advanced
    steam technology. Once the lake had been enclosed by a retaining dijk, the
    three pump houses had taken moved all the water out into a ring canal in
    just a little over four years. A feat which, until he saw The Hydraulic,
    as they called it, for himself, had seemed impossible to Marcellus and
    made his own battles with flooding polder seem puny in compariason.</para>

    <para>AS the barge conveying the party approached Cruquius along the canal
    their first impression was of a sort of castle but with the addition of a
    tall chimney. The engineer leading the tour explained that the boilers
    were housed in the hall which they could easily have mistaken for a
    medieval great hall, whilst the pumps themselves occupied a crenelated
    round tower beside it. However, the tower had eight great legs sticking
    out evenly around it which moved up and down in a manner that was
    disconcertingly like a vast spider on the move. Of course, the tower stood
    still and these legs were, in fact, the driving beams and piston links.
    The tour of the inside of the pumping station compounded the impression of
    animus as the boilers and steam engines roared, hissed and snorted. The
    amount of water that this working monster could move with the combined
    efforts of the eight pistons would have beggared belief had Marcellus not
    seen it with his own eyes. He found the whole experience exhilarating to
    the verge of frightening. It did, however, open his eyes to the power of
    steam which he now championed as the solution to the local problems back
    at home.</para>

    <para>He could not as single-mindedly apply steam engines to the drainage
    of the troublesome polders of Lopikerward as the engineers of
    Haarlemmermeer had for a number of reasons. Marcellus realized that his
    own reluctance to abandon the use of windmills, which had been tried and
    tested across the centuries, would be echoes by the people of the Vlist.
    Replacing the mills for a new-fangled and alien mechanical contrivance was
    a risk to great to be contemplated by the ordinary man. The workings of
    the machinery would be unknown territory for them, alomost like a magic
    trick moving the water around - or something biblical. They would fear
    what they didn't undertsand rather than embrace it. The value of steam
    pumping needed to be demonstrated in action so that it might become
    commonplace and no longer a mystery. Although he had been assured of the
    reliabilty of these engines, what if the machine did break down? He would
    need to find at least one local man who would be willing to learn not only
    how to operate the engine but also how to maintain and, if necessary,
    repair it. Meanwhile, the current mill workers should be reassured that
    they were not about to be deprived of their livelihoods and homes in short
    order. There had been many reports of workers dispalced by machinery
    seeking terrible revenge on their masters and their infernal engines. The
    change to steam needed to be accomplished gradually and the support of the
    millers courted along the way.</para>

    <para>But now, in his bereavement, Marcellus threw his engeries into the
    Haastrecht steam pump project. He haunted the architects of the buildings
    which would house the pump and the man who would operate it. The pump
    itself was being made in Cornwall and he contemplated paying a visit to
    the engineering company there but, in the end, decided that it was too
    long a journey to make and would necessitate too long an absence from home
    so reluctantly abandoned the idea. Maps and calculations absorbed him as
    he went over the plan and the predicted benefits that it would deliver. He
    kept upwith his business and political interests yet the new drainage
    system was there to fill the void left by the absence of his three
    women.</para>

    <para>He was also prone to distracting himself with pondering the state of
    his daughter's marriage which he could easily have worked himself up into
    a state of worry over. She seemed unable to settle down to life in Den
    Haag despite her husband being home from his wanderings permanently, or so
    it would seem. Paulina seemed to be busying herself with social activities
    which her husband seemed not to share in. Marcellus found that he was none
    too keen on Johan, although he was hard pressed to put his finger on quite
    why this should be. The chap seemed friendly enough but there was
    something a bit off kilter about him. A recently received letter had
    brought this feeling of unease to the front of Marecllus's mind as it
    seemed to typify something vaguely distasteful about the man.</para>

    <para>For a start, Johan had addressed him as "Valued Papa" which seemed a
    little too familiar to Marcellus. Although Johan had lost his own father
    when just a boy and perhaps had a need for a father figure even now he had
    grown to a man approaching middle years, Marcellus felt uncomfortable at
    being thrust into his shoes. The text itself began with some talk of
    business in the form of the mortgage value of a polder near Middleburg,
    the ledgers relating to Hilletje and some matters concerning wills which
    left Marcellus wondering why he needed to know all this. What was of more
    interest was a passage reporting the couple's good health and the
    curtailing of their pleasure in Den Haag and Scheveningen by the inclement
    weather. It seemed that Paulina's friend, Jenny van Zijll, was visiting
    them but due to leave imminently. Johan said no more about her visit. More
    appositely, he made no concession to Marcellus's situation as doubly
    bereaved. In fact, Marcellus found it in rather poortaste that Johan went
    on to end his letter with ab extensive account of Utrecht gossip
    concerning a man marrying a beautiful girl 35 years his junior ( was that
    a hint to Marcellus to followsuit) and a couple who wed againts the wishes
    of her family which ended with the jilted groom trying to drown himself by
    jumping from the Hoornbrug (gain in bad taste considering Marcellus's own
    losses). Somehow Marcellus felt that the final salutation from "Your
    loving son" was rather overblown. However was his daughter faring in a
    marriage with someone so lacking in sensitivity to others and so keen to
    inflate his emotional connections to them?</para>

    <para/>
  </section>
</chapter>
