<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter version="5.1" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
         xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:xila="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude/local-attributes"
         xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
         xmlns:trans="http://docbook.org/ns/transclusion"
         xmlns:svg="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"
         xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
         xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
         xmlns:db="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
  <title>Juli 1869</title>

  <section>
    <title/>
    <para>The man waiting patiently at the edge of the room was quite
    unremarkable. He could neither be described as tall nor short, thick-set
    nor thin, dark nor fair and he wore clothes that were neither rough nor
    elegant. His features were unremarkable, his stance relaxed and confident
    without being in any way challenging. Like a moth on a wall at dusk, you
    would not notice him until, that is, he moved. Then his talent for mimicry
    displayed itself in far more complex and dynamic ways than were available
    to any insect. His movements and gestures could mirror those of the people
    around him, as could his voice, accent and expressions. Upon first meeting
    him almost anyone would feel the sort of rapport that presages a lifelong
    friendship, yet you could pass him in the street unrecognised within an
    hour of taking him into your heart – and confidence.</para>

    <para>His plain clothing concealed a muscular and agile body that was well
    able to deal with trouble of a physical kind, as well as a short-bladed
    knife and small pistol which he could apply with skill should the
    necessity arise. Fortunately, no such circumstance had arisen in the
    conduct of this particular case, yet, despite its apparently
    straightforward and safe nature, this matter had caused him some
    perturbation. Viruly was not his only client and there were more powerful
    interests with far fatter purses which had to be taken into account when
    presenting his report.</para>

    <para>As was usual in these circumstances, the man would give his findings
    verbally. He had previously ordered his thoughts on paper then, blessed
    with a photographic memory, destroyed any trace of written material before
    presenting himself before his client. The man's stoic wait was eventually
    rewarded when the door to the room opened and closed as Viruly entered his
    Den Haag office. Even so, it wasn't until Viruly had settled himself
    behind the desk that he became aware of the man's presence, feeling rather
    discomforted at being caught unawares. The man gave Viruly an arch look
    and continued to wait in silence until Viruly got up and crossed the room
    in order that an envelope of bank notes could be transferred from Viruly's
    inside coat pocket to that of the man.</para>

    <para>Viruly seated himself behind the desk once more and gestured to the
    man that he should take the visitor's seat opposite him but the man
    indicated that he preferred to stand. He moved forward into the spotlight
    of sunshine let in by the window as a signal that he was ready to begin
    his narrative. So far, not a word had been uttered by either party and
    Viruly was unwilling to be the one to break the oddly monastic atmosphere
    so, instead of speaking, he elected to open the palm of his right hand and
    extend it in front of him as an invitation to the other to start what was
    clearly set up to be an uninterrupted soliloquy. The account which
    followed was delivered without embellishment or dramatic interpretation,
    the man reading the words from the inside of his expressionless eyes. Its
    listener was left to interpret what he heard for himself and form what
    judgement he may of the individual it concerned.</para>

    <para>
      <quote>The subject, Johan Jacob le Fèvre de Montigny, is the second
      living son of Johan Jacob le Fèvre de Montigny, after whom he was named,
      and Petronella Henrietta Kleijn. His father was called to the ministry
      of the Nederlandse Hevormde Kerk as a young man and all his family
      practice that religion.</quote>
    </para>

    <para>
      <quote>He has one surviving older brother, Gillis Johannes le Fèvre de
      Montigny, named after his grandfather. This brother was born in 1837 in
      the village of Kwadijk in the Zeevang community of North Holland, his
      father being the pastor resident there. A second child, Bartolomeus,
      born in 1938, did not survive infancy. The family were quite short of
      funds at this time.</quote>
    </para>

    <para>
      <quote>In 1839 the family moved to Nieuwe Tonge in the community of
      Middleharnis on the island of Goeree-Overflakkee in South Holland. Here
      Johan Jacob junior was born in 1840 and another child, Henri Pieter,
      arrived some years later.</quote>
    </para>

    <para>
      <quote>Johan Jacob senior was predikant of the parish of Nieuwe Tonge
      for the remainder of his lifetime, his fortunes improving such that he
      was registered as a landowner at his death in 1849. It is said that his
      new parish was granted as the result of the application of both power
      and money on the part of his parents. Nieuwe Tonge was certainly an
      improvement on Kwadijk in both location, being close to his family, and
      in possessing an environment more favourable for both physical and
      financial health. However, his choice of profession is rather at odds
      with the occupations of the rest of his well-respected patrician
      family.</quote>
    </para>

    <para>
      <quote>The subject's grandfather, Gillis Johannes senior, married Lena
      van der Sluys in 1807 at Zwartewaal, near Brielle on the island of
      Voorne-Putten in South Holland. They had two daughters and two sons who
      survived into adulthood. The daughters, who are the eldest children,
      married well. Maria Johanna wed Arij Jacobusz Hogendijk, a shipowner and
      merchant, and lives in Vlardingen. The Hogendijks are a clan of
      shipbuilders and builders in the area of Krimpen aan den IJssel. Jacoba
      Elena wed Johannes Oudorp Kotebrant who was appointed mayor of Kralingen
      near Rotterdam in 1867. The Oudorp family also has connections in the
      East Indies. A fourth and youngest child, Jacob known as Jacques,
      requires money for his care and always lives with a family member. He
      was in the home of Lena van der Sluys until her death in 1859, some 38
      years after her husband, at Oudendijk. Jaques now lives with the
      Kralingen branch of the family but it has not been possible to discover
      what ails him.</quote>
    </para>

    <para>
      <quote>The subject's grandfather, Gillis Johannes le Fèvre de Montigny
      was born at Den Bosch in North Brabant in 1765 and died at Maasluis in
      South Holland in 1821. In 1776 he became a Kornet in the Regiment
      Oranje-Gelderland. By 1782 he had risen to the rank of Kolonel in the
      Korps Ingenieurs which became Korps der Genie in 1806 then the
      Koninklijk Korps der Artillerie en Genie in 1807. He is noted and
      respected for his work in map-making and, less so, for the design of
      defensive structures. In 1806 he was appointed examiner of surveys to
      the land register. The Koninklijk Korps der Artillerie en Genie closed
      in 1810 after French came to power but Kolonel le Fèvre de Montigny was
      one of the few to retain his rank in the French army.</quote>
    </para>

    <para>
      <quote>Thus from 1810 – 1811 the Kolonel was <emphasis>chef de
      battailion</emphasis> 1e Klasse. He was designated premier administrator
      to Hollandse cadaster which surveyed and mapped the Netherlands in order
      to create the land register which was to form the basis of new tax laws
      on property. He held this post until 1817 and is best known for the
      quality of his work and for taking a principled stand over
      standardization and detail in his surveys. This was deemed both costly
      and irrelevant by those in charge of the project but le Fèvre de
      Montigny stood fast and overcame this opposition to oversee the
      production of the first set of detailed and accurate maps of our
      country.</quote>
    </para>

    <para>
      <quote>The subject's grandfather had followed in the military footsteps
      of his own father, Johan Nicolaas le Fèvre de Montigny, who joined the
      Korps Ingenieurs as a Kornet 1776 and rose to the rank of
      Lieutenant-Kolonel in 1795. Johan Nicolaas became Directeur of
      Nederrijn- en IJssellinie defensive works, for which he produced the
      first accurate maps of Overijssel and Zeeland.</quote>
    </para>

    <para>
      <quote>To return to more recent events. The subject and two brothers
      were still minors in the care of their mother, Petronella Henrietta
      Kleijn, when their grandmother, Lena van der Sluys, died in 1857. At
      this point the three pastor's sons inherited a significant amount of
      money, being their father's share of the estate. The subject's
      grandmother owned a great deal of land around Brielle which was sold by
      her heirs and the proceeds apportioned between them. The subject's
      mother did not benefit from this inheritance and died some years later
      at the age of fifty three. I could find no trace of the younger brother
      after that event.</quote>
    </para>

    <para>
      <quote>At the time that he benefited from his inheritance the older
      brother, Gillis Johannes, was employed as a candidate notary in Den
      Haag. After his grandmother's death he moved to Brielle then, in 1864,
      gave up the law and went to live in Berkel near Rotterdam, having been
      appointed burgemeester of Berkel and Rodenrijs at the end of the
      previous year. Gillis Johannes has recently been appointed burgemeester
      of Hillegersberg and Bergschenhoek, which neighbours his previous
      constituency yet is more favourably located for development as a
      substantial centre of business and an elegant residential area. It would
      seem that the subject's brother has used his new-found wealth and his
      ancestor's influential name in order to progress a career in politics.
      In 1866 he married Maria Woutherina van Haaften in Den Haag. To date, he
      has one son, an infant given the family names of Johan Jacob. He has
      just built a substantial villa in Hillegersberg where the subject is
      also currently residing.</quote>
    </para>

    <para>
      <quote>As to the subject's biography, he attended a private elementary
      school in Hilversum then, aged 14, commenced training as a sea-going
      officer in the navy. The reasons for his taking this course of action
      rather than following the family preference for the military are not
      known. The Naval Training School in Den Helder did not exist at that
      time so our subject's training was arranged as a private matter between
      the family and appropriate sea captains. Perhaps the influence of his
      family background set him on the course of becoming a navigation
      officer.</quote>
    </para>

    <para>The man smiled wryly to himself behind his stony face as he examined
    his client for any sign that his little pun had been appreciated. He often
    played such a small trick at this point in his monologues in order to
    discover whether his audience had been, and still was, attending to all
    that he laid before them. It was frequently the case, especially in
    matrimonial affairs, that the client was listening for a particular piece
    of information and not taking in the whole picture. However, this employer
    evidenced himself to be a model of diligence by the merest lightening of
    his expression at the man's slight whimsy. Thus, coming to the meat of the
    matter, the man continued,</para>

    <para>
      <quote>The subject's first voyage of any length was as a Kornet on the
      Frigate <emphasis>Admiral van Wassenaar</emphasis> from 1855 to 1856.
      During another two-year voyage from 1857 to 1859, also on a Frigate, he
      was promoted to Adelborst. Then he served on the transport ship
      <emphasis>De Heldin</emphasis> which sailed from Hellevoetsluis to the
      West Indies, being promoted to Lieutenant ter Zee der 2e Klasse in 1859.
      In connection with his voyages, he has purchased many charts and maps,
      including of Java, the Batta countries and Sumatra in the East Indies,
      as well as inheriting many maps from his forbears.</quote>
    </para>

    <para>
      <quote>At the age of twenty two he left the navy and began to live
      variously in hotels in Den Haag, Amsterdam and Gouda as well as with his
      brother near Rotterdam. He has made substantial investments using the
      firm of Jonas &amp; Krugeman in Amsterdam, including a particularly
      successful venture in the Koninklijke Stoomboot Maatschappij. He is a
      member of Den Haag Freemason's lodge and The Amsterdam branch of the
      public welfare organisation Maatschappij tot Nut van het Algemeen. He
      has never married and no scandal attaches to his name.</quote>
    </para>

    <para>The man stopped speaking and looked directly at Viruly. An interval
    elapsed during which Viruly tried to formulate his thoughts for the
    response which was clearly expected. In the end he simply said,</para>

    <para>
      <quote>If I understand you correctly, Lieutenant le Fèvre de Montigny
      comes from a lesser branch of a notable patrician family. He is of the
      Nederlandse Hevormde Kerk protestant religion, possessed of some wealth
      and a member of suitably worthy organisations. He has never married and
      has no independent household.</quote>
    </para>

    <para>The man nodded his confirmation. Viruly continued,</para>

    <para>
      <quote>Does he have any particular friends?</quote>
    </para>

    <para>The man knew that not even the smallest grain of the truth must dust
    his answer,</para>

    <para>
      <quote>The subject has an easy social manner which has engaged many
      acquaintances but he has formed no particular friendships. His
      relationship with his brother has endured and indicates that he has the
      potential to form deep and lasting attachments.</quote>
    </para>

    <para>This answer had only skimmed the surface of Viruly's most serious
    concern so he felt that he must press further,</para>

    <para>
      <quote>You say that no scandal attaches to his name but you do not offer
      any more detailed assessment of his character. I should be interested to
      hear your opinion of him as a man.</quote>
    </para>

    <para>The man had prepared his answer, having expected such a line of
    enquiry. He knew that he needed to tread carefully in what he said but
    that say something he must if the fact of his manipulating his information
    were not to be suspected. To reveal too much would, however, put him in
    jeopardy of losing valuable clients and perhaps even put him in the way of
    a more physical sort of danger.</para>

    <para>
      <quote>The subject is a sailor and a bachelor who has been in the habit
      of going where he pleases and suiting himself. Many of his connections
      are people who share his charitable, business and religious interests
      and others are naval colleagues. He is accepted into polite society
      wherever he goes.</quote>
    </para>

    <para>
      <quote>I should perhaps mention that there has lately been an alteration
      in his usual behaviours which might be interpreted as indicating that he
      has come to a time in his life where he is ready to settle down and take
      a wife, should he find someone suitable. For instance, I have heard that
      he has very recently made enquiries as to the purchase of a house
      presently under construction in a fashionable part of The Hague.</quote>
    </para>

    <para>The man left his answer there, knowing that he had avoided the moral
    quagmire before him yet safely achieved the crux of the matter that
    occupied the client before him. He had subtly alluded to the suitability
    and availability of the subject for marriage to the Bisdom van Vliet
    daughter, which was all that Viruly had really wanted to know and what one
    of his other interests had wished him to convey.</para>

    <para>The man made a slight bow and was gone with hardly a disturbance to
    the air in the room. Viruly immediately took up a sheet of writing paper,
    pen and ink and wrote a short message to Marcellus using the form of words
    which they had agreed upon as a confirmation that Paulina's choice of
    husband was considered a suitable one. Sealing the letter, Viruly rang for
    a boy to take it to the post. Marcellus would have the news he was waiting
    for by the end of that afternoon.</para>

    <para>As soon as the message left his hand Viruly began to feel less
    certain of it's content. Now that the man had gone taking his stage
    presence with him, and Viruly had dropped his own guard of rationality and
    returned to being Theo, the concerned brother-in-law, some sense of unease
    crept over him. He tried to focus on what was bothering him but all he was
    left with were vague  suspicions too insubstantial to bear close scrutiny.
    Was the father a noble man who followed his religious convictions at the
    cost of wealth and power, or was he in some way the black sheep of the
    family? Is there some inherited family weakness behind the shadowy figures
    of the uncle known as Jacques and the younger brother, Henri Pieter? For
    all he knew, the latter might have had a dashing military career and been
    killed in action.</para>

    <para>Then there was the man himself. Theo had to admit that he just
    didn't like Johan and that this coloured his enthusiasm for the match with
    Paulina. Quite why his instincts told him to keep his distance from the
    dashing, young Lieutenant he couldn't fathom. Perhaps it was just his own
    fondness for the girl that made it hard for him to see any man as good
    enough for her. Then again, his political and business dealings had been a
    great education in the ways of men and he was well aware that the
    investigator had presented a well-manicured account for political reasons.
    Gillis had some of this skill, too, but Johan seemed to lack this
    political acumen, although he clearly had a head for business which Theo
    was able to appreciate. There was something else that motivated the young
    man in his social dealings, something that Theo felt was beyond his range
    of understanding. Something that was probably best left to the women in
    the family to fathom.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title/>

    <para>Once back at Haastrecht, preparations for the luncheon consumed a
    great deal of Paulina's emotional energies. Everything seemed to conspire
    against her, however, and she was often in an agony of anxiety that things
    would not be as she desired or, unthinkably, the invitation would have to
    be postponed or even cancelled. Firstly, her mama had to be persuaded to
    leave Aggie's side and return to Haastrecht for the occasion. It was not
    so much that Maria Elizabeth could not tear herself away from De Haven for
    even one day, although that was the impression that she gave. It was, if
    truth be told, a rather less noble sentiment that motivated her – she had
    moved heaven and earth to find a suitable husband for her youngest
    daughter only to be thwarted by this wilful child. Now, the girl had gone
    and found a man all by herself, putting her mother's nose well and truly
    out of joint. Since Paulina had made it clear that she was taking over all
    her mother's duties in her absence and brooked no interference, she could
    have the responsibility of organising her own luncheon party for all her
    mother cared about it.</para>

    <para>Paulina was delighted to have control of the event but suffered
    greatly until her mother relented and agreed to attend. Then she was on
    tenterhooks waiting for a formal response to their written invitations to
    Johan and Gillis and his wife which was delayed somewhat because the baby,
    Johan Jacob junior, was suffering from some childhood ailment and his
    mother could not bear to be parted from him. At last, the news came that
    all was well so the luncheon could go ahead as arranged. Now Paulina could
    get on with the tasks of planning and organising with which she was in her
    element.</para>

    <para>Wanting to make a good impression, she decided on a formal meal in
    the 'new' part of the house, that is to say the part built by her great
    great great grandfather when he came to Haastrecht in 1694. Usually more
    informal meals were taken in the original 'family house' adjoining it,
    parts of which dated back to the 16th century. Although the family house
    was more cosy and intimate, Paulina wanted her future husband to
    experience the style in which she expected to spend her married
    life.</para>

    <para>Her first task was to decide with the butler on the table setting.
    There was no doubt in her mind but that the Meissen porcelain dinner
    service should be used for she adored it's delicate pink floral pattern
    with a simple gold band around the rim. She had a fondness for porcelain
    in general, fashionably aspiring to a great collection of it one day. To
    accompany the dinner service she chose the solid silver Sheffield cutlery,
    of course. To dress the table she ordered vases of flowers and the
    bringing out the new silver and crystal glass garnishments which she,
    Aggie and Theo had bought for her parents on the occasion of their silver
    wedding anniversary a few years previously. Silver pedestals supported
    crystal fruit platters, compote dishes and
    <emphasis>bonbonnières</emphasis>, their edges dripping with crystal
    tear-drops which would shimmer in the candlelight from the best silver
    candelabra. The tiered centre piece would set off the whole ensemble to
    perfection and leave her guests in no doubt but that they were sitting at
    the table of a well-to-do family. Her next project was to decide on the
    food and wines that would garce her magnificent table setting.</para>

    <para>She hated relying on the staff for advice but soon realized that she
    had to do so. Paulina made a list of her favourite dishes and created an
    opulent but ungainly menu which made cook throw her hands up in despair
    when it reached the kitchen. Cook was not a woman to be beaten, however,
    so she took up her pencil and re-worked Paulina's offering to her own
    satisfaction. Dishes which clashed were separated and those involving
    unseasonable or unobtainable ingredients, as well as those which were
    time-consuming or likely to overtax even her skills, were amended or
    replaced. This revised menu was then taken to the young mistress for final
    approval, the changes being tactfully explained. Luckily, Paulina was
    delighted with the result and had no trouble accepting that she had a lot
    to learn about what went into the creation of a successful menu.</para>

    <para>When it came to choosing the wines to accompany the meal Paulina
    knew from the start that she was out of her depth. She understood that the
    wines served at a dinner were usually judged by the men at least as keenly
    as the table was by the women. The trouble was that she wouldn't know a
    good wine from a bottle of vinegar as she drank but little. In fact, she
    quite disapproved of alcohol but had so far kept this to herself. She had
    seen enough of the effects of drunkenness amongst the poor of the village
    to last a lifetime but was not yet able to disentangle the circumstances
    of poverty and the availability of cheap gin from the ease of plenty and
    the pleasures of fine wines. The only alcohol she allowed to pass her lips
    was the sweet, red vermouth she had been introduced to in Italy a few
    years previously. She realized that this version of a wine was an
    eccentric taste of hers and not something that she could expect her guests
    to drink throughout the meal.</para>

    <para>The French had left behind their habit of wine drinking when they
    retreated back within their own borders in 1815 but the notion of keeping
    a private supply at home had not taken hold with the Dutch. Unlike the hot
    and dry lands of wine-producing France, the wet soil of the Netherlands
    was not conducive to the undermining of buildings with cellars which the
    temperate climate, in any case, rendered unnecessary. Paulina summoned her
    father's favourite wine merchant to discuss placing an order. They went
    through the menu together, the merchant suggesting wines to compliment
    each dish. When the cost of the order was reckoned up Paulina was
    horrified and the whole process had to be gone through again but with an
    eye to economy this time. Somehow she just couldn't bring herself to pay
    the prices of some of the best wines, no matter how much she wished to
    impress her guests.</para>

    <para>All these preparations did not distract her from her duties to the
    family estates. She enjoyed keeping detailed and accurate accounts of all
    the incomings and outgoings, keeping a tight grip on all the monies
    brought to the house by a constant stream of tennants as well as carefully
    monitoring the household expenses. There was also the business of sending
    written instructions to the various tradesmen who were required to make
    repairs and alterations to all the properties. Aside from such routine
    matters, Paulina concerned herself with the physical and moral welfare of
    the sick and poor of the district who either came to the door or were
    commended to her by the predikant. Once word got round that the young
    (and, so it was assumed, inexperienced) woman of the family was in sole
    charge, there was an increase in the number of petitioners but Paulina was
    determined that she should not be hoodwinked into giving charity to the
    undeserving so turned a deaf ear to some of the more outrageous tales of
    woe.</para>

    <para>It was exhausting work which left little time for socializing with
    her good friends Helena and Cornelia Droost and Mientje Blankken, although
    they only lived a step or two away. Letter writing of a personal nature
    was confined to uncharacteristically brief communications with her mother,
    step-sister and a married friend who now lived in Aachen. Her father was
    out of the house most of the time, occupied with his business concerns and
    his civic duties which often involved long hours of travel on top of the
    difficult situations he had to deal with and the important decisions he
    needed to take. In fact, Paulina's most constant companion during this
    period was her journal in which she wrote avidly at every available
    moment, dashing off line after line in her large and flowing hand using a
    pencil for speed rather than the more complex demands of pen and ink. She
    was always to judge that the hhat thoughts which she commited to paper
    during these few weeks in July were the most revealing and significant of
    all her writings.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title/>

    <para>The day of the luncheon seemed to come round very quickly so that,
    before she knew it, Paulina was being helped into her best day dress by
    her maid. Her mother and father had both returned to Haastrecht during the
    morning and were now also dressing ready to receive guests. The household
    staff were quietly and calmly going about thier tasks. All was well and
    even the sun was shining for Paulna's luncheon party.</para>

    <para>Marcellus was in his office attending to the post which had
    ccumulated during his brief absence and Paulina and her mother were going
    over the accounts together when their guests arrived by cab from Gouda
    station. By the time Johan, Gillis and Mary had descended from the vehicle
    the Bisdom van Vliet family had made thier way to the vestibule to greet
    them. The sight of Johan almost took Paulina's breath away, which came as
    something of a relief as it woud have been rather socially awkward had her
    feelings towards him suddenly changed.</para>

    <para>The luncheon passed well with both Mary and her mother complimenting
    the tastefully laid table whilst all the men were appreciative of the
    choice of wines. Everyone enjoyed the plentiful food whose many courses
    kept them at the table until well into the afternoon. As to conversation,
    the men had much to talk about since, despite all being liberal in their
    political persuasion, they had somewhat differing views on a number of
    issues which needed debating. Meanwhile, the women talked about children
    and household matters which, having neither, rather left Paulina on the
    outside. Her attention tended to drift towards Johan who deftly included
    her in his audience when he came onto the topic of his passion for the new
    steamships which, he predicted, would replace the use of wind power
    entirely within the next decade. His knowledge of the sea and enthusiasm
    for the new industry of building ships using metal rather than wood and
    engines rather than sail captivated her with his manliness.</para>

    <para>Once the party had eaten their fill, Paulina suggested that they
    took tea or coffee outside in the landscaped grounds across the lane to
    the front of the house. Whilst the ladies made their way to the table and
    chairs which had already been set up in the shade of a large Copper Beech
    tree, the men retired to Marcellus's office where he offered them cognac
    and a choice of cigars from the three factories in Haastrecht. Gillis
    discretely left his brother alone with Marcellus once the comparison of
    cigars and cognacs had been discussed for a polite length of time. He made
    his way slowly through the house and out into the gardens where he found
    the ladies taking their tea cold against the heat of the afternoon, a
    habit from the East Indies which had now become fashionable back in
    Holland.</para>

    <para>The private conversation between Marcellus and Johan did not take
    long. As Marcellus had expected, Johan formally requested his permission
    to pay court to Paulina using the words so carefully coached by brother
    Gillis. Marcellus asked Johan what his prospects were, as if he didn't
    already know, and made out to be modestly rassured by hearing of his
    considerable income from investments, his possible earnings from future
    sea voyages and the building of a fashionable house in Den Haag which
    would make a suitable family home, in due course. Marcellus made a show of
    giving his blessing with the caveat that Paulina herself should be
    agreeable to Johan's attentions, again he was privately sure that she was
    more than willing.</para>

    <para>Once reunited and everyone had drunk their fill of the various
    beverages, Marcellus proposed a stroll in the gardens. This provided him
    with an opportunity to let his guests see in the flesh, as it were, the
    stylish landscaping that they had already admired as the setting for the
    1757 family portrait of great grandfather Theodorus, with his wife and ten
    children. Marcellus privately held this forebear of his to be his role
    model. Theodorus was the first to be appointed burgemeester of Haastrecht
    at the begining of the 18th century, a role which had been handed down
    through the Bisdom van Vliet men in an uninterrupted line ever since.
    Successful in business, Theodorus had been wealthy enough to be able to
    buy up lands around Haastrecht, which included the castle Sloot van Vliet
    which enabled him to engrandise the family name from the simple Bisdom of
    his father, Adriaan. On the home front, Theodorus had built a new wing
    onto the house and commissioned the Royal Gardener to lay out the grounds.
    Then, to top it all, he had fathered twelve children almost all of whom
    had survived to adulthood without the losses in infancy and childhood
    which were usual.</para>

    <para>Marcellus had inherited the family interests at the tender age of
    nineteen and at a time when the Golden Age of Dutch prosperity from
    overeseas trade was long gone. It had been as much as he could do to hold
    onto his inheritance let alone lay out money on house, garden or land. He
    had married Maria when he was thirty three and under some pressure for his
    mother to provide heirs. His fancy was taken by the widow Ledeboer who
    also lived on the Hoogstraat , and who brought lands ajoining his, as well
    as her three surviving children, to their union. As time was to tell,
    Maria's age (she three years older than him) was to lead to
    disappointment. They only had one child, Paulina, and this shortly after
    their marriage in 1839. Now he once more found himself cajoaled by his
    mother, now aged eighty three, into finding a husband for Paulina before
    her child-bearing years had dwindled much further. A male heir was what
    was needed, especially now that Marcellus could feel the economic tide in
    Holland turning to the flood making a second Golden Age seemed possible.
    Today, he felt his hopes rise.</para>

    <para>Whilst Marcellus conducted his guided tour of the lake, the statues
    of Hercules and Neptune and all the specimon trees, Paulina and Johan hung
    back under the pretext of inspecting in the Copper Beeches which Adriaan
    had planted to mark the birth of his first two sons, Jacob in 1696 and
    Theodorus in 1698. The pair pursues their interest in Copper Beeches by
    returning to the small, formal garden behind the house where Adriaan had
    planted his own tree upon first arrival in Haastrecht in 1694. They
    wandered down to the water's edge where the River Ijssel bounded the edge
    of the property. Here, in this public private place, Johan took the
    opportunity to speak his well=rehearsed lines.</para>

    <para>"I do hope that I shall not be presuming too much upon such a short
    acquaintance as ours if i say that I am already at ease in your company.
    Would it be too much to hope that you might one day feel comfortable with
    me?"</para>

    <para>Paulina could hardly keep herself from jumping into the middle of
    his declaration with fulsome affirmations that she reciprocated any
    positive feelings he might have for her. However, she, too, had been
    carefully prepared against the possibility of just this situation
    occuring. So, instead she relied in as steady a manner as she could
    manage,</para>

    <para>" I, too, have felt that there is a naturalness to our
    meetings."</para>

    <para>Taking his cue, Johan responded,</para>

    <para>"Then might I hope that we might meet together more often and get to
    know eachother further?"</para>

    <para>"I should like that very much."</para>

    <para>"Then it will be my pleasure to call upon you as often as you will
    permit me to. In the meantime, I think that it is your birthday soon and
    wish to offer you a gift"</para>

    <para>With this, Johan produced a small package from his inside coat
    pocket and handed it to Paulina.</para>

    <para>"It is just a small token of my esteem which I hope will remind you
    of me when we are apart."</para>

    <para>Paulina unwrapped the present to find a tiny replica of a ship's
    cannon made out of solid silver. Before she could master her feelings she
    felt a flush of disappointment at such an unfeminine choice of gift.
    Hardly had this almost reflex response had time to enter her awareness
    than it was replaced in a more stable delight at his thoughtfulness. It
    also thrilled to have a tangible token of her womanhood, a symbol of her
    passage from unwanted spinster to a woman being paid court to by the man
    she loves. After a heartbeat's delay, Paulina smiled up at Johan and
    offered him her thanks - and her hand hand which he raised to his lips and
    tenderly kissed, holding her gaze with his liquid brown eyes.</para>

    <para>With that, it was done. Paulina Maria Bisdom van Vliet was about to
    be courted by Johan Jacob le Fevre de Montigny. It was hard to think of
    anything else to say now, so the couple just looked into each other's eyes
    for a second or two before turning back to the house where they quietly
    slid back inot the company of their families.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title/>

    <para>The last day of June was Paulina's twenty-ninth birthday which made
    for a constant stream of callers to the house. Villagers and tennants came
    bearing the best of their produce that they could manage as a token of
    their respect: fish, meat, eggs, bread, vegetables, fruit, cheese, flowers
    and small pieces of various needlecrafts. Paulina stationed herself on a
    chair behind the streetside window nearest to the main door so that she
    could give a wive of acknowledgement to each departing donor. More
    affluent well-wishers were the cause of frequent deliveries by tradesmen
    and by post of more substantial gifts as well as some of the newly
    fashionable cards. Soon every available space on top of side-boards,
    buffets and small tables was filled, despite the perishables having been
    conveyed to the pantry immediately.</para>

    <para>Among the few callers actually admitted to the house were Paulina's
    friends. First came Helena and Cornelia Droost who lived in the house next
    door. The daughters of a wealthy Schoonhoven silver dealer, there was
    twenty four years difference in the sisters' ages with Helena being
    fourteen years older than Paulina and Cornelia ten years younger. Next to
    arrive was Mientje Blanken, now nearing her fourtieth year, who lived with
    her uncle, an important figure in the village and friend of Paulina's
    father. Last, and in a flurry as usual, was Aaltje van Zijl who was just
    in her twenties and the daughter of another local family of substance.
    Aaltje's father was building the hofje, a courtyard of alms houses, at the
    poor eastside of Hoogstraat. which was a project heartily endorsed by
    Paulina's own father.</para>

    <para>On being shown into the kleine salon each woman kissed Paulina three
    times on alternating cheeks then tendered birthday good wishes. Everyone
    had brought a gift so Paulina was engaged with paper and ribbon for some
    minutes as she revealed writing materials and the latest novel, a pair of
    white lace gloves and a silver-backed hand mirror, which Aaltje assured
    her had come from Paris. Tea and delicate little cakes were served and the
    women fell into comfortable conversation. With these lifelong women
    friends gathered around her, it was not long before Paulina found that she
    could no longer keep her important news to herself;</para>

    <para>"There have been developments in my acquaintace with Lieutenant le
    Fevre de Montigny. I am now officially being courted by this
    gentleman!"</para>

    <para>There was an immediate clamour of excitement and congratulations
    followed by a great press of questions about when, where and how this
    happy circumstance had come about as well as damands for every kind of
    detail about the man himself. Paulina gleefully launched into an
    unnecessarily fulsome account of events and an impassioned description of
    Johan Jacob.</para>

    <para>The two older women had long abandoned any hope of marriage for
    themselves and it was with bitter-sweet feelings that they outwardly
    enthused about Paulina's suitor, having privately considered her to be
    destined to join them in spinsterhood. Cornelia and Aaltje, on the other
    hand, were young and bright with romatntic expectations for thgemselves
    which added a vicarious interest to their enquiries.</para>

    <para>What started out for Paulina as the recounting of her story as if it
    were a fairy-tale romance slowly changed in the telling. Her narrative
    transformed from a description of a girl's cherished dream into a mature
    woman's account of a real man and an actual possibility - no, probability
    - that she would marry him. The atmosphere in the room seemed to gradually
    become more calm, perhaps in response to Paulina's increasingly
    down-to-earth tone. The older women exchanged glances as both privately
    wondered if Paulina might be having second thoughts. But before they had
    time to formulate discrete but probing enquiries, there was a knock at the
    door and a maid came in bearing another gift.</para>

    <para>This present was a rather large package with a long letter in
    Aggie's hand accompanying it. Paulina laid the letter to one side to read
    at her leisure once her guests had departed. She requested the maid to
    clear the table of their now abandoned tea things and, once this had been
    done, laid the parcel on it in order to remove the cord and paper
    wrappings. What was revealed was a bolt of the finest silk satin fabric in
    a stunning magenta. The other women crowded round the table to feel the
    luxuriousness of the material and admire its rare colour. As Paulina
    unrolled the first length of the silk the better for it to be appreciated,
    a small square of paper fell out onto the floor. The maid, who was
    lingering by the buffet too curious to leave the room, swiftly retrieved
    the note from the floorand handed it to Paulina. The contents were a
    brief, intensely private and personal communication which Paulina took in
    at a glance before hastily secreting it beneath the discarded wrapping
    paper. The note read:</para>

    <para>"Dearest Paulina. This is for your bride dress. From your loving
    sister, Aegidia."</para>

    <para>A flush spread up Paulina's neck onto her cheeks and she remained
    quiet and thoughtful as her friends compiled a list of all the features
    which a gown in this most fashionable of colours should have. They began
    to debate hoops as against horsehair petticoats, fringes as against
    ruffles, wide sleeves as against narrow cuffs and whether a lace collar or
    ribbons would be a flattering at the neck-line. In order to give herself
    time to recover her composure, and to dispatch the maid from the room,
    Paulina sent for the latest editions of <emphasis>Le Petit Courrier des
    Dames</emphasis> which Aggie so that the women could persue the
    complicated draperies of the fashionable gowns illustrated therein.</para>
  </section>
</chapter>
