<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter version="5.1" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
         xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:xila="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude/local-attributes"
         xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
         xmlns:trans="http://docbook.org/ns/transclusion"
         xmlns:svg="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"
         xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
         xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
         xmlns:db="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
  <title>Juni 1869</title>

  <section>
    <para>The door before her opened and Paulina stepped out of the shadow of
    the house into the warm, summer sunshine.</para>

    <para>The early days of June had been exceptionally cold with flurries of
    snow by day and ice-cold nights as winter had reached through spring to
    try its grip on another season. But now the persistent sun swept winter
    into oblivion to give Gouda a glorious Sunday morning. Like many other
    families from the houses lining the sides of the haven, they had decided
    to take advantage of the uplifting weather and walk the short distance to
    Sint Janskerk for morning worship. The trees which shaded the quays were
    in their best green for the day. Children from the schutje moored
    alongside ran in and out of the tree trunks, klompen rattling rhythms on
    the cobbles. Paulina's nieces and nephews longed to join these other
    children in their games but the two governesses kept them all under tight
    control lest they become distracted and lag behind.</para>

    <para>This family party heading for church was not quite complete. Little
    Cornelis Catharinus was only eighteen months old so had remained in his
    nursery. His mother, Aegidia, who was due to deliver her eighth child in
    just a few weeks, had also stayed at home, feeling herself to be too large
    in her pregnancy to venture out and about. She remained indoors trying to
    rest on her <emphasis>chaise longue</emphasis> but actually feeling too
    uncomfortable to settle properly. So it was that Paulina, her half-sister
    - the maiden aunt - walked beside the head of the household and accepted
    the greetings of other church-goers in Aegidia's place.</para>

    <para>Paulina had been an impressionable fifteen year old when Aegidia
    married childhood sweatheart, Theodorus Pieter Viruly. Having recently
    been given Aernout Drost's <emphasis>Hermingard of the Oaken
    Mounds</emphasis> to read she was awash with the idea of romance between
    men and women, especially if the men were heroic. Hearing her parents talk
    about Theo's courageous business decisions and staunch political stands,
    it had seemed to her that he was made of the very stuff of heroism. Then
    there was all the excitement of Aggie's wedding preparations, the house
    being filled with swatches of fabric, dress designs, recipes and table
    dressing catalogues. The look of adoration in Aggie's eyes when she ran to
    Theo upon his arrival at the house and the aura of mystery and delight
    that came over everyone when the honeymoon was alluded to served to
    intensify the the attraction which the febrile girl-woman felt for her
    soon-to-be brother-in-law.</para>

    <para>Although Theo was now almost fifty years of age, Paulina still
    experienced some of the same excitement that she had felt for her romantic
    hero of all those years ago. Although somewhat changed in nature, she
    found that his allure had in some way grown over the years as he had risen
    to become both wealthy and powerful. Under his management the family
    laundry business had transformed itself into a highly lucrative soap and
    candle works in newly built premises. On the domestic front, he had taken
    an old canal-side merchant's dwelling and had it re-built as the grand
    house known simply as 'De Haven'. He had filled his new house with a
    suitable wife and their burgeoning family of healthy children whilst
    finding the time to rise in the world of politics.</para>

    <para>As the family group made their way along Oosthaven quayside, they
    were encouraged towards the church by the tolling of its four great bells.
    From time to time they were obliged to step aside for those worshippers
    who had ordered out their carriages, the east side of the haven being on
    the direct route to the great church. Each time Paulina took to the narrow
    footpath in the shadow of the houses, Theo unwittingly brushed against her
    arm and she began to feel a flush of excitement in anticipation of his
    next touch. She tried to feel ashamed of herself but the light was too
    bewitching, the sun too warming and the sound of the church bells too
    enchanting for her to be able to punish herself for taking an extra morsel
    of pleasure at this physical contact.</para>

    <para>Reaching Dubbele Buurt they had the best view of the Sint Janstoren
    as it rose high into the blue sky, being visible from as far away as
    Waddinxveen. Accident and design had resulted in a layered confection with
    a square base of three distinct stone storeys: the original fourteenth
    century construction being successively topped by additions in 1590 and
    1605. In the mid-seventeenth century, a hexagonal lantern had grown up
    from the stone stump with an openwork section housing a 36-bell carillon.
    Finally, a narrow waist flared again into a small onion-dome from which
    the weather-veined lightening rod seems reach all the way to God in his
    heaven.</para>

    <para>Paulina had the sensation of gently falling backwards as a her gaze
    followed the Sint Janstoren spire right to its tip. She almost reached out
    to Theo to steady herself but that head-swimming moment soon passed as her
    gaze responded to the more earthly need to watch where she was treading on
    the uneven and dung strewn road.</para>

    <para>As they reached the narrowness and bustle of Achter de Kerk a tall
    man in naval uniform stood aside to allow the family party to keep
    together as they went inside to take their places among the congregation.
    Paulina noticed that Theo nodded to him in thanks and, perhaps,
    recognition but no words were exchanged. Then she was caught up in the
    business of settling the family into their pews, taking her place near the
    end of the row so that she might be of some help to the governesses in
    managing the children, each woman now having charge of two young
    ones.</para>

    <para>As it turned out, Paulina was settled between the two eldest
    children: Catharina Johanna, aged eleven-and-a-half, and Maria Elisabeth,
    soon-to-be ten. Both girls were generally well-behaved in church, having
    reached such a stage in their understanding of the world as to appreciate
    the need for mannered behaviour during holy worship. Both also enjoyed the
    chance to show off their fine voices, the fruits of the labours of their
    singing master. Usually their already refined talents and well-developed
    lady-like qualities made Paulina feel quite the dull, country aunt, but
    she was not herself that day and seemed to rise above such
    self-consciousness.</para>

    <para>She had been to services in Sint Janskerk many times before and
    admired its beauty, as it were, from a mental distance. Today the feeling
    of standing back from the scene had left her and she became totally
    absorbed in the magical transformation wrought by the sunlight pouring
    into the vast space of the interior with its high wooden vaults and its
    white walls pierced by lofty glass windows. The great swags of gilded
    organ pipes seemed to shimmer with reflected light. Of all the wonderful
    windows it was the one depicting The Sacrifice of the Prophet Elijah that
    drew Paulina's attention that day. To be precise, she became totally
    absorbed in the image of Margaretha van Parma at the bottom of the
    window.</para>

    <para>In the sixteenth century Margaretha had been Landvoogdes van de
    Nederlanden and, as Governess of the Low Countries, had paid for this
    window to be made as a vanity piece. Paulina must have heard the story of
    Margaretha's life from one of her tutors but had relegated the details to
    the back of her mind. On this sunny, summer, Sunday morning this image of
    a powerful and worldly woman from three centuries ago became an almost
    tangible presence. From beneath the Governess's crown of gold a youthful
    woman's face looked out, exuding strength and confidence which flowed like
    warm wine through Paulina's arteries as she met the eyes in the glass
    portrait.</para>

    <para>Fashionably and opulently dressed in gold cloth, lace and furs,
    Margaretha still managed to be both pious and upright. By contrast,
    Paulina had never been very interested in her appearance, rising above the
    pain of knowing that the people of Haastrecht called her 'the farmer girl'
    behind her back. She had felt that no alchemy of fashion could transform
    her sturdy frame, plain looks and unruly hair into such a beautiful
    creature as Aggie and her friends. The sheer amount of effort it would
    take to make beauty from such unpromising material had always seemed to
    Paulina to be a travesty of nature and of what God had given her. Now,
    though, Margaretha van Parma was giving her permission to make the most of
    herself free from the burden of aiming for the impossible and without the
    worry that she was sinfully vain.</para>

    <para>The more she looked into Margaretha's luminous eyes the more she
    grasped a deeper message from this woman. Yes, Paulina could fulfil her
    destiny as a wealthy and powerful woman without sacrificing the feminine
    desire for marriage and children. Like Margaretha, she would be strong,
    proud and have a masculine consciousness of her place in this world yet
    make a marriage that would produce heirs and stand the test of time. But,
    and a chill note of caution came now, this could only happen if each party
    contracted to a marriage that left them free to follow their individual
    paths. Margaretha had made an undignified and unhappy marriage at sixteen
    to a boy two years her junior, to whom she bore twins, but this liaison
    had metamorphosed over the years into a lasting mutual respect for what
    each was achieving in their lives. Paulina now knew in her heart and soul
    that she would henceforth be her true self, which was so much more than
    the dutiful and dull woman of just moments ago.</para>

    <para>So taken up with these revelations was she that Paulina lost
    awareness of her surroundings until the great organ let out a rich,
    swelling cord startling her back into the present moment with its signal
    that the service was about to start. Her whole being resonated with this
    crescendo in celebration of new beginning and she woke to the moment,
    rising to her feet with the rest of the congregation to devote herself
    heart and soul to the first hymn.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title/>

    <para>The service over, the children set off for home with an enthusiasm
    which the governesses could not quite curb. Paulina had expected to stay
    by Theo's side on the return to 'De Haven' but a number of men were
    clearly intent on engaging him in conversation as he left the church. No
    doubt they were taking the opportunity to press their interests with the
    man who was not only their councillor and alderman but was also a senator
    in the Eerste Kamer of parliament in Den Haag. She waited for the bulk of
    the congregation to depart before wandering back towards Oosthaven by
    herself, yet not feeling alone. As she regained the quays she saw that the
    schuitje that had been moored alongside earlier was now being worked
    through the gates of the Donkere Sluis. Along with several other
    churchgoers, she stopped to watch as the little boat negotiated this
    awkward navigation, enjoying the unhurried nature of the activity and the
    feel of the day.</para>

    <para>From across the lock, a group of children began singing with great
    gusto the old rhyme to encourage the rowers of the 'little cooking pot'
    boat:</para>

    <blockquote>
      <para><literallayout><emphasis>Schuitje varen, theetje drinken,
Varen we naar de Overtoom.
Drinken er zoete melk met room.
Zoete melk met brokken,
Kindje mag niet jokken.</emphasis><footnote>
            <para>
Sail your boat, drink your tea,
We're sailing to the Overtoom*.
Drinking sweet milk with cream.
Sweet milk with bread lumps,
children, don't tell fibs.
*The Overtoom was a canal in the suburbs of Amsterdam that connected important waterways.</para>
          </footnote></literallayout></para>
    </blockquote>

    <para>Looking over at the impromptu choir, she was surprised to find her
    eyes meeting those of the naval officer whom the family had briefly
    encountered on the way into church. They exchanged smiles which encouraged
    the officer to make his way over the set of lock gates on the IJssel side
    as soon as they closed and she soon found him standing before her,
    extending his hand in introduction,</para>

    <para><quote>Lieutenant le Fèvre de Montigny at your
    service.</quote></para>

    <para>He bowed low over her hand before releasing it but continuing to
    look directly into her eyes. His own eyes were a liquid brown and she
    began to feel herself falling as if into a deep pool. He was tall, slim
    and very attractive. He had combed his thick, black hair back from his
    forehead and applied just enough Macassar oil so that it shone in the
    sunlight. His facial whiskers were also dark and dense, spreading down his
    jaw and across his top lip, yet his chin and neck were shaved bare as was
    the fashion in Den Haag.</para>

    <para><quote>I think you are a relative of Mr Viruly. You have his
    stature.</quote></para>

    <para>She was amazed that he, the first person whom she had encountered
    since Margaretha had awakened her, could appreciate that she was a
    significant woman.</para>

    <para><quote>I am Paulina Bisdom van Vliet, his wife's
    half-sister.</quote></para>

    <para>All her life she had insisted on being known as “Paulina” so that
    she would be distinguished from her grandmother, Paulina Maria
    Hondorff-Block, after whom she had been named. It came as a surprise to
    her to find that she had suddenly and without thought reclaimed her proper
    name, her own name.</para>

    <para><quote>Your father is the burgemeester of Haastrecht?</quote></para>

    <para>She nodded assent.</para>

    <para><quote>Then I have had the honour of making his acquaintance at my
    brother's house. Gilles was the burgemeester of Berkel and Rodenrijs and
    has just become burgemeester of Hillegerberg and Bergschenhoek. Both your
    father and Viruly were his supporters in gaining his improved
    appointment.</quote></para>

    <para>She was glad to hear that he moved in the same social circles as her
    family and was not going to prove an embarrassment to be seen talking to.
    She also liked that he was tall. Looking up to him made her feel feminine
    since she was herself taller than most men. Anxious now that their
    conversation should not flag, she enquired,</para>

    <para><quote>Are you in Gouda with your ship?</quote></para>

    <para><quote>I am between voyages at present and like to stay at the Hotel
    De Zalm here. So, it is fortuitous that we have met today. I see that you
    are watching the operation of the lock, do you have an interest in
    navigation?</quote></para>

    <para><quote>Since I was a child I watched boats pass our house on the
    Hollandse IJssel and bring cargo along the Vlist to the Haven in
    Haastrecht, but I know nothing of the sea or of the marine.</quote></para>

    <para>He easily took up her conversational opening and began to tell of
    his sea voyages, allowing Paulina to ask questions and show interest at
    appropriate points so that she did not feel excluded. They had just
    arrived at Curaçao in the West Indies, where Lieutenant le Fèvre de
    Montigny's ship was visited by Governor Landsbergen, when she noticed that
    Theo had detached himself from his followers and was approaching. Since
    the two men were acquainted, she expected Theo to join them but instead he
    slowed to a stop a pace or two away, clearly waiting for her to join him.
    She was somewhat reluctant to part from the handsome lieutenant but also
    understood that one did not keep Theodorus Pieter Viruly waiting. The
    lieutenant noticed the social dilemma she faced and quickly resolved it
    for her by turning and taking a step towards Theo, thus allowing her to do
    the same. The lieutenant then greeted Theo enthusiastically,</para>

    <para><quote>Good morning, Mayor Viruly! Let me give you my
    hand!</quote></para>

    <para>Theo only briefly touched the hand extended to him and grunted a
    greeting in reply before offering Paulina his arm and steering her in the
    direction of Oosthaven. So swift was her disengagement from the lieutenant
    that she felt her farewell was cut so short as to be almost rude. Minded
    to say something to Theo as she was rather cross with him not only for
    leaving her alone after church but also for tearing her away from her
    handsome new friend, she chided him,</para>

    <para><quote>Lieutenant le Fèvre de Montigny was good enough to escort me
    after church since your politics detained you for so long. I found his
    company most engaging and understood that you and he were acquainted. I am
    sorry to be parted from him so briskly and hope that I shall meet him
    again.</quote></para>

    <para>Theo was silent for some time before replying,</para>

    <para><quote>Yes, I have met le Fèvre de Montigny and so has your father.
    His brother is in politics and looks to do well. I am sorry if you thought
    me rather unfriendly just now.</quote></para>

    <para>There the matter rested and they were soon back inside De Haven and
    into the thick of family life once more.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title/>

    <para>Sunday dinner was a family meal and rather chaotic so it was well
    into the afternoon before Aegidia and Paulina were alone. Paulina went to
    sit with Aggie as she tried to rest since she said that she often got
    bored by being so inactive and left all by herself. It was not long before
    Aggie remarked upon the change in Paulina's demeanour, saying that she
    seemed somehow stronger in herself yet almost girlishly excited at the
    same time.</para>

    <para>Aggie knew her half-sister well having moved to the burgemeester's
    house following his marriage to her mother. Aggie had been seven when
    Paulina was born and the age gap between them had not always been
    comfortable. They became closer after Aggie's older brother and sister
    both died in the same year, throwing the two daughters into each other's
    company when the one was just past childhood at eleven and the other, at
    eighteen, was almost a woman. Their relationship came into full bloom
    after Aggie married and the children started to come along. She had felt
    able to confide things in Paulina which she did not care to share with
    their mother. In return, Paulina had confided her horror at the string of
    unappealing young men who had been put before her as potential husbands.
    They had laughed together at their coarse features, or their foppish
    dress, or their arrogant manners, or their blatant desire to advance
    themselves through marriage. Aggie had also wiped away the tears when the
    ones that Paulina did like had disappeared, never to return to her
    side.</para>

    <para>Now, once she heard that Paulina had been talking to a handsome
    young naval lieutenant that morning, Aggie pressed her for all the details
    of the encounter. As Paulina started talking about him she
    self-consciously realised that she sounded just like a girl in love. Aggie
    picked up on this immediately, asking,</para>

    <para><quote>Tell me, sister, did you perhaps flirt with him a
    little?</quote></para>

    <para>Paulina found herself blushing and left with no choice but to
    confess that perhaps she had – just a little.</para>

    <para><quote>I am so pleased for you that you have found someone who takes
    your fancy! Now, let us consider how suitable a match he would be for you.
    What do you know of his family?</quote></para>

    <para><quote>Well, his brother is a burgemeester and both papa and Theo
    know him. He is an officer in the marine, too, and looks so handsome in
    his uniform! He has such interesting things to say about his voyages and
    the places he has visited. I wonder if he has ever been in a battle? He
    didn't say.</quote></para>

    <para><quote>I think that you are getting a little distracted! If he were
    in the military then I would know exactly who his family is. There were
    illustrious military engineers called le Fèvre de Montigny, so he may be
    connected with them. In which case, he is of the patriciate and socially
    on a par with us. We should ask Theo or papa to find out
    more.</quote></para>

    <para><quote>Oh, but isn't that making rather a lot of fuss after just
    one, brief meeting?</quote></para>

    <para><quote>My dear! I have never seen you show such an interest in a man
    and I am so excited for you that I want to help all I can. He just might
    be the right one for you and we shouldn't let him get away! It is not as
    though you are a mere girl and this just an infatuation that will be gone
    by tomorrow! You will be twenty nine years old in a few days and have a
    mature woman's sensibilities and not a little experience in dealing with
    potential suitors. I think that we need to find out more about your
    handsome stranger.</quote></para>

    <para><quote>But what if he is married or I don't feel the same next time
    I see him?</quote></para>

    <para><quote>We must be patient and leave it to the men to find out more.
    But, in the meantime, perhaps we can make sure that you chance upon a
    second meeting? You said that he is resident at Hotel De Zalm? Well then,
    it should be easy! If you find reason to stroll in the Markt for long
    enough you are sure to encounter him. You might even take coffee at the
    hotel during the cheese market. How I wish that my condition allowed me to
    go with you! As it is, my great belly would be enough to put off any
    man!</quote></para>

    <para><quote>Poor Aggie, is it really so bad?</quote></para>

    <para><quote>I must confess that I am finding it exhausting this time. The
    doctor says that this must be my last pregnancy if I am to fully recover
    my health after the birth. But I seem to become pregnant so easily that I
    am not sure how I shall stop! I could go on to have another five or ten
    children before I am too old to conceive! What a dreadful
    thought!</quote></para>

    <para><quote>Our mama must have been about the same age as you when I was
    born yet there were no more children after me. Poor papa, he so wanted a
    son to inherit his position and wealth but all he got was me! Which brings
    me to the other thing that happened to me today: I have become resolved to
    do all that I can do in this life and not be hindered by the limitations
    on what is expected of me because of my sex. I was looking at Margaretha
    van Parma in the stained glass window I was sitting under in church this
    morning and she seemed pour her strength into me. So, if le Fèvre de
    Montigny is to be my husband, he had better know that I shall not bend
    myself or my destiny to accommodate his - or anyone else's - notion of
    wifely behaviour!</quote></para>

    <para><quote>Good gracious, Paulina. You are quite disconcerting
    me!</quote></para>

    <para><quote>Well, you might as well know straight away that I now call
    myself Paulina, with the 'a' that I was Christened with. I assure you that
    nobody will ever confuse me with old Oma now!</quote></para>

    <para><quote>I am quite sure that you are right in that! Now,
    Paulin-with-an-A, I have had quite enough excitement for one day so,
    please will you read to me for a while? Since I must spend so much of my
    day in idleness I thought I should exercise my mind in compensation.
    Whilst you were at church I began reading 'Max Havelaar' to see what all
    the fuss was about when it was published some years ago. I have to confess
    that Mr Douwes Dekker's style is most conducive to rest as it fails to
    excite. Yet, I feel that I must continue with it as the subject matter is
    important. Theo is concerned with the political debates about our East
    Indies colonies so it will be good to inform myself about the topic so
    that I might appear more knowledgeable and interested when he talks of his
    work in Den Haag.</quote></para>

    <para><quote>Is that the Multatuli book?</quote></para>

    <para><quote>Yes.</quote></para>

    <para><quote>What a strange <emphasis>nom de
    plume</emphasis>.</quote></para>

    <para><quote>Apparently it is Latin for 'I have borne much' – which seems
    appropriate for my situation! I fear that the poor man had a bad time of
    things in Java. It seems such a far-away place and such a different place
    to Holland that I find it hard to believe that his tales have much to do
    with us ordinary Dutch people. It has caused quite a stir, though. Maybe
    you will be able to put some excitement into it when you read a passage
    for me?</quote></para>

    <para>Paulina did try to make the tale interesting but Aggie was soon fast
    asleep and she did not chose to carry on with the book for herself.
    Unwilling to risk waking Aggie by leaving the room in order to fetch her
    writing materials, she reached for the novel by Ouida which Aggie had just
    finished reading and commended to her. Fortunately this was in translation
    from the original English, a language in which Aggie was competent but
    that was opaque to Paulina. So, to find <emphasis>Idalia</emphasis> in
    Dutch had been something of a treat, especially since the story was
    compelling enough to distract her from her passion for keeping her
    journal.</para>

    <para>Immediately captivated by the courageous, clever, independent and
    muscular Queen's Messenger with the exotic, Scottish name of Sir Fulke
    Erceldoune, Paulina had been gathered up and swept along with his headlong
    fall for the beautiful Countess Idalia Vassalis, who had saved his life,
    Hoping for a romantic, happy ending, it had been distressing to discover
    that Idalia was actually an enchantress who bewitched men then bent them
    to her political will before discarding them or, worse, sending them to
    their deaths. But all was not lost and Paulina became heartened again by
    the prospect of Idalia's love for Fulke being the saving grace which would
    reform her, showing her to be a virtuous soul worthy of the hero's
    devotion after all. The novel was proving to be a much more riveting way
    of exercising the moral faculties than her usual diet of the sermons and
    poetry of Utrecht minister Nicolaas Beets, whose latest tome remained
    buried in her luggage.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title/>

    <para>Despite Aggie's urging her to frequent the environs of Hotel De Zalm
    in the hope of another encounter with the handsome naval officer, several
    days elapsed before Paulina again set foot outside 'De Haven'. She was to
    accompany Theo once more but this time they were not headed for church but
    for the new railway station. It was another glorious summer day as they
    left the house and were handed into the Viruly's smart, new Victoria
    carriage with it's liveried driver. Paulina had a keen eye for horse flesh
    and was appreciative of the fine pair of bay mares which were harnessed
    and waiting patiently, their coats gleaming in the sunlight.</para>

    <para>The carriage hood was down so that they were open to the sights,
    sounds and feel of day. They had no sooner set off along Oosthaven heading
    for the Markt when the Sint Janskerk carillon began chiming out the
    Meideun tune to signal the hour for ten o'clock. Paulina let herself relax
    back into her seat so as to fully enjoy the music, the sun's warmth and
    the sights as they made their progress past the stepped gables and slender
    spires of the stadhuis in the centre of the market square before taking
    the Hoogstradt, crossing the Turfsingel and Kattensingel canal bridges to
    reach Stationsplein.</para>

    <para>It had to be admitted that there was rather more excitement for
    their outing today than there had been last Sunday for this was a day of
    celebration for Theo. The people of Gouda had not taken easily to the
    notion of rail transport when their business had done so well out of the
    shipping that passed through Holland's busiest river junction. It had been
    unfortunate that the first train line was laid to the north of the city
    centre, being unable to breach the walls and canals so as to arrive at a
    more convenient location. Indeed, the townsmen had refused to contribute
    to the building of a proper station leaving train travellers to make do
    with a rather basic wooden construction beside the single track which
    linked Rotterdam and Utrecht.</para>

    <para>Characteristically undaunted, Theo had worked hard on behalf of the
    Nederlandsche Rhijnspoorweg-Maatschappij, of which he was a shareholder
    and board member, and today his efforts would come to fruition. He had
    exercised his political skills to have the town boundary re-drawn so that
    the station now lay within Gouda's compass. His business acumen was
    instrumental in the development of a second track which, passing through
    Harmelen and Breukelen, would soon enable travel between Rotterdam and
    Amsterdam. A third line to Den Haag would follow making it possible to
    travel easily between Holland's three great maritime cities: Rotterdam,
    Amsterdam and Den Haag. Competition from the Hollandsche IJzeren
    Spoorweg-Maatschappij's direct line between Rotterdam and Amsterdam via
    Den Haag had been successfully beaten off, largely because Theo had
    advocated investment in modern engineering techniques to deal with the
    problems of laying track across waterlogged land.</para>

    <para>The Rhijnspoorweg line continued beyond Gouda to Utrecht and Arnhem
    then went on to Oberhausen across the border, thus opening up not only the
    whole of the central and eastern Netherlands but also Germany. Theo had
    grasped the possibility that at least some of the anticipated numbers of
    people on board all these trains might be encouraged to break their
    journey in Gouda and contribute to the town's trade. To this end he had
    persuasively argued that a station which made the right impression on the
    travel hardened and weary was crucial to local enterprise. Today was to
    see the first stage Theo's grand vision for his home town realised when
    passengers from Rotterdam and Utrecht would be able to alight at Gouda's
    distinctive new station building which offered all the facilities a
    traveller might require. A group of specially invited guests were to
    arrive on the next train from Rotterdam and join with the local
    dignitaries for a formal opening ceremony followed by inaugural
    festivities in the station's restaurant.</para>

    <para>Having arrived at the station in good time for the train from
    Rotterdam, Theo left Paulina to stroll around the building and platform
    whilst he went to check that all was in order. He had wanted to be early
    so that he could round up the chosen members of the welcoming party and
    ensure that everyone was in the right place at the right time, and doing
    the right thing. Anxious that Gouda and its station should gain the
    approval of the august company soon to arrive, he had worked hard to
    ensure that the building was ready, the staff well-trained and provided
    with new uniforms, and the restaurant able to lay on a sumptous mid-day
    meal.</para>

    <para>Paulina had caught some of his mood and paced restlessly and
    aimlessly around. First she wandered through the ticket hall with its
    window already manned in preparation for the first customers and the
    porters with their trolleys waiting to assist with luggage. Then she
    investigated the waiting rooms, declining the attentions of the maid who
    was eager to seat her in the women's room. Paulina was unable to sit or
    stand still, however, and soon passed out onto the platform. Everywhere
    was lavishly decked in bunting or garlanded with fresh flowers whose scent
    barely masked the lingering odour of fresh paint. Paulina found herself
    gazing hopefully in the direction from which the Rotterdam train would
    arrive, although she knew it was not yet due for some time.</para>

    <para>The excitement of the occasion was especially heightened for Paulina
    as her beloved papa was one of the honoured guests due to arrive by train
    as he returned from a week attending to his shipping business in
    Rotterdam. It had been decided that, following the station opening, she
    and papa would continue on home to Haastrecht together in the comfort of
    Theo's new carriage. On its return journey to Gouda the carriage would
    bring mama, Paulina and Aggie's mother, who wanted to be on hand in plenty
    of time for the arrival of the new baby. Paulina was looking forward to
    swapping news with her father, the urgency for which seemed to be further
    fuelled by their at daily exchange of letters. She had also begun to
    hanker for home and, if truth were told, was keen to exercise her spirit
    and mind in the management of the family house and estates. As was usual
    for daughters of the patriciate, her education had all been in
    preparationfor the conduct her own affairs upon her marriage. So far, she
    had been afforded little opportunity to test herself in this respect,
    having been cast as assistant to her mother. Paulina had always deferred
    to her mama's way of doing things but now her new-found confidence and
    strength of will made her determined to take charge and be autonomous. She
    found the prospect of being in control during mama's absence quite
    exhilarating.</para>

    <para>The tasks ahead of her were busily running through her head as
    Paulina turned to retrace her steps to the entrance hall. Suddenly he was
    there! Not in his uniform this time, but her heart recognised him before
    she was fully conscious of it and let out an involuntary cry then hastily
    put her hands to her face as if to push the noise back inside of her. At
    the muffled sound he turned from supervising the porter who was stacking
    his luggage and quickly covered the distance between them.</para>

    <para><quote>Is there something the matter?</quote></para>

    <para>He asked and before she had time to think about what she would say
    Paulina had replied,</para>

    <para><quote>Oh, no, not at all! I had so hoped to see you again but now
    it seems that you are going away, perhaps on a long sea
    voyage!</quote></para>

    <para>She was aware that this was a rather bold and forthright utterance,
    although it was truthful. But Johan Jacob le Fèvre de Montigny was not a
    man to be thrown by forwardness in a woman, finding the whole
    <emphasis>etiquette</emphasis> of courtship rather tedious. He happily
    replied in kind whilst hoping to be able to put a name to her vaguely
    recalled face.</para>

    <para><quote>Do not concern yourself, my dear, I am merely paying a visit
    to my brother in Hillegersberg. I shall not be far away and, in any case,
    will return to De Zalm in a week or so's time. Are you taking the train
    yourself?</quote></para>

    <para><quote>No, I am here in my step-sister's place beside Theo Viruly at
    the opening ceremony; and to meet my father who is arriving with the
    official party from Rotterdam. We are to go home to Haastrecht later today
    but I am sure that I shall be back in Gouda once my latest niece or nephew
    arrives.</quote></para>

    <para>At last, Johan placed the woman. She was the only daughter of the
    burgemeester of Haastrecht and she seemed to be setting her cap at him. He
    was intrigued!</para>

    <para><quote>My brother is among the burgemeesters from Rotterdam who have
    been invited today. Perhaps you would like to be introduced to
    him?</quote></para>

    <para><quote>Oh, yes, that would be delightful! You can meet my father,
    too! This has really turned out to be a most fortunate
    encounter!</quote></para>

    <para>Johan had a vague sense that he was not quite in control of the way
    things were going as the young woman seemed to be slightly more
    enthusiastic than his polite offer of an introduction warranted. Since he
    couldn't quite put his finger on what, if anything, was wrong with it, he
    went along with her enthusiasm and nodded his agreement.</para>

    <para>A sudden commotion of people arriving on the platform from inside
    the station building put paid to any further dialogue. Theo was
    marshalling the reception committee into place whilst the station master
    took up a position at the platform's edge, extracting his shiny new
    timepiece from the pocket of his smart uniform coat and consulting it. It
    would not do for his first train to be late! A distant whistle reassured
    him that all was well as Theo stepped up beside him in readiness to greet
    the distinguished city men.</para>

    <para>The driver skilfully halted his train so that the door of the first
    class carriage containing his most notable passengers came to rest exactly
    beside the two waiting men. The carriage door was opened with some
    ceremony by the station master and the men inside began to alight. Theo
    shook the hand of each before they passed on to mingle with the local
    mayors and patriarchs behind him. Paulina was only looking for one face,
    that of her father, Marcellus. As soon as she saw him she was hardly able
    to stop herself from running to him. He had seen her, too, and extricated
    himself from the round of greetings as soon as was polite so that they
    were soon embracing affectionately.</para>

    <para>Meanwhile, Johan had located his brother and worked his way into the
    crowd to place himself at Gillis's right elbow. The brothers did not
    exchange greetings and seemed not to acknowledge each other, yet they
    moved through the cluster of guests as one. Johan lost no time in shaking
    hands and swapping names with many prominent men who assumed that he, too,
    was important. He was charming and personable, seeming to be in the
    acquaintance of the burgemeester of the rapidly developing Hellegesburg
    district of Rotterdam. Gillis le Fèvre de Montigny had recently been
    appointed to this promising position after serving for several years in a
    smaller, less notable district where he had nevertheless made the right
    impression. Brother Johan eased himself into the social benefit afforded
    by his association with Gillis and merged with the invited guests.</para>

    <para>Paulina and Marcellus worked their way through the crowd to be near
    Theo as he delivered his formal speech, declared the station open and,
    after others had made their speeches, led the assembled party into the
    restaurant where they were seated for the meal. Paulina found that her
    appetite was unusually slight and that her eyes constantly sought out
    Johan, who seemed to have been been made room for at the end of a table,
    near the door. His brother sat next to him and appeared to be animatedly
    monopolising his attention. Occasionally they would look in her direction
    and she would quickly look away but just sometimes her eyes met Johan's
    only and they held each other’s gaze unabashed. Mostly, however, she was
    able to take him in as he devoted his attention to his food and his
    brother. He was every bit as handsome as she remembered and stirred her
    passion no less now that he has was out of his uniform and in a smart
    tailcoat and suit.</para>

    <para>For her own part, she was glad that she had put on her favourite
    carriage dress with its flatteringly cut jacket in a darker blue to the
    full-skirted, lightweight dress beneath. It was quite a new costume and,
    she had been assured by the dressmaker, fashionable. As was the Mantilla
    which she had been persuaded would complete the look. But Paulina found
    that her boisterous hair defeated all attempts to attach the flimsy
    Spanish creation which, in any case, made her feel uncomfortably tall as
    it's comb added a good hand's breadth to her height. She had tossed the
    Mantilla into a drawer at home and was now relieved not to have the worry
    of it.</para>

    <para>The meal over, people began to leave the table and pass out of the
    restaurant. The train for Rotterdam was due at any moment so leave-takings
    began. Theo and Marcellus passed among the Rotterdam guests, shaking hands
    and saying a few well-chosen words to each of them. Paulina tried to keep
    up with them and do as they did but was finding it difficult to connect
    socially with any of the men. She might have felt aggrieved by their
    overlooking her but was distracted from the whole enterprise when she
    noticed that Johan and his brother were heading through the throng in her
    direction. She then focussed her own efforts on managing matters so that
    Marcellus was at hand when the brothers arrived before her.</para>

    <para>Before Paulina could concern herself with including her father in
    the introductions she found that Gillis le Fèvre de Montigny had taken
    this social manoeuvre upon himself, deftly separating the four of them
    into a discrete group away from the mass of people. Gillis drew upon a
    slight previous acquaintance with Marcellus and the latter's current mood
    of fellowship to all around in order to engage his attention. Once he had
    ensured that all four were known to each other and a cordial atmosphere
    prevailed, he swiftly moved on to issue an invitation to dine at his new
    house in Hillegesburg. Marcellus explained that the family were waiting
    upon a new arrival so his wife would not be travelling far in the near
    future. Most extraordinarily, Marcellus then heard himself issue an
    invitation for the le Fèvre de Montignys to take lunchewon at Haastrecht
    the following week. The invitation was readily accepted, a date and time
    agreed and hasty farewells made as the Rotterdam train was now standing at
    the platform with Johan's luggage being loaded aboard.</para>

    <para>Once released from his civic duties, Theo had prevailed upon
    Marcellus and Paulina to come into the house and take refreshment with
    Aggie whilst Paulina's luggage was being stowed on the carriage. Once the
    sisters were together it was inevitable that an account of Johan's
    presence at the station opening should burst from Paulina. Marcellus,
    being a good natured man and exceedingly fond of his daughter, joined in
    with their excitement, proclaiming,</para>

    <para><quote>I do believe that you are a little enamoured of this
    gentleman!</quote></para>

    <para>To the surprise of all present Paulina announced,</para>

    <para><quote>Yes, father. He is the man I am going to
    marry!</quote></para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title/>

    <para>Everyone had been somewhat taken aback by Paulina's announcement but
    the tone of determination in her voice brooked of no contrary comments.
    Such a brief acquaintance seemed hardly the basis for a life-long
    commitment and would usually have been dismissed as a passing fancy.
    However, in the circumstances there was an element of relief as it was
    proving difficult to find a suitable husband for her. Many tactful
    introductions had been made over the years since she came of age but she
    had shown no interest in forming any sort of attachment either
    romantically or pragmatically.</para>

    <para>It had not been easy to entice eligible bachelors in Paulina's
    direction, either. She was somewhat out of the ordinary in her physical
    appearance, being both tall and sturdy, as well as lacking in any dress
    sense or gracefulness. She was educated to manage her inheritance but not
    accomplished in literature, music or art and spoke no foreign languages.
    Although she spent hours each day at her writing desk, the result was
    perhaps best described as mental outpourings.</para>

    <para>Paulina's enthusiasm for this man at least got over the first hurdle
    on the course towards marriage. However, two major stumbling blocks
    remained. Was this relative stranger a suitable person to be the husband
    of the only daughter of a wealthy and powerful patrician. Paulina stood to
    inherit a great deal of property in her own right but could only retain
    her father's power if she had a husband to act on her behalf. Even
    assuming his credentials passed scrutiny, there was the small matter of
    whether Johan Jacob le Fèvre de Montigny was actually interested in
    marrying Paulina.</para>

    <para>Because of these concerns, Marcellus made a point of having a
    private talk with Theo before leaving for Haastrecht. The two men pooled
    what little they knew of Paulina's potential suitor, starting with their
    shared assumption that he came from a family with an illustrious military
    past. That said, they next agreed that the brothers Gillis and Johan
    appeared to have been born in obscurity but to be men of means; where,
    they wondered, had this money come from? Theo was also privy to the
    rumours circulating at parliament in Den Haag concerning the dubious
    morals of the King's eldest son, Hendrik the Navigator. Johan's name had
    been mentioned as one of the set who joined in the Prince's notorious
    bouts of drinking and womanising. Neither man was keen to ally their
    innocent Paulina to a man of dissolute habits.</para>

    <para>Doubts clouded the enthusiasm of father and brother-in-law for
    Paulina's choice of husband and they saw it as their duty to find out more
    before matters progressed too far. Not only did they wish to spare Paulina
    the pain of future disillusionment, but they were also eager to avoid any
    scandal which association with the wrong sort of man might bring down upon
    their heads. It was agreed that Theo would quickly pay a visit to Den Haag
    where he knew of a clever and discrete man whom he would engage to
    investigate and report back directly on the young lieutenant.</para>
  </section>
</chapter>
