<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<article version="5.1" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
         xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:xila="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude/local-attributes"
         xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
         xmlns:trans="http://docbook.org/ns/transclusion"
         xmlns:svg="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"
         xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
         xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
         xmlns:db="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
  <info>
    <title>The Last of Her Line</title>

    <subtitle>Synopsis</subtitle>

    <author>
      <personname><firstname>Diane</firstname><surname>Reeve</surname></personname>
    </author>
  </info>

  <section>
    <title></title>

    <para>The <emphasis>Last of Her Line</emphasis> is a novel based on the
    life of Weduwe Mevrouw le Fèvre de Montigny - Bisdom van Vliet. It is set
    against the backdrop of the industrialisation of the Netherlands and the
    consequent social and political change. It is underpinned by its author's
    fascination with the widow's story, her love of all things Dutch and her
    enjoyment of historical research.</para>

    <para>On the 1 June 2023 the curator of a museum in Haastrecht opens a
    mysterious sealed packet believed to be the final element of the legacy of
    the museum's benefactor. Paulina Bisdom van Vliet died just days before
    her eighty-third birthday in 1923, childless and widow of more than forty
    years. Without heirs, she bequeathed her house and estates in South
    Holland to the people of Haastrecht instructing the trustees of what is
    now the museum that the house should be left exactly as it was on the day
    she died.</para>

    <para>Only child of businessman and burgemeester, Marcellus, and his
    wealthy wife, Maria Elizabeth, Paulina lacks the beauty, grace and
    accomplishment that women of her social standing require in order to be
    marriageable in late 19th century Holland. What she has instead is a
    strong character and a talent for management. When she falls for naval
    lieutenant Johan Jacob le Fèvre de Montigny and determines to marry him
    there is little her family can do despite their mixed feelings about the
    match.</para>

    <para>Following their marriage and honeymoon in the autumn of 1869, the
    couple set up house in fashionable Den Haag. Paulina continues with her
    life much as before albeit with Johan doing what she requires of him. But
    what does he get up to when not under instructions from his wife? Whatever
    it is, it comes to a stop when Paulina's grandmother and mother both die
    in 1871, leaving Marcellus alone and grieving. He makes the bold decision
    to demolish the family's old, traditional house and build a grand,
    <emphasis>fin-de-siècle</emphasis> mansion in its place. No sooner is his
    marvellous new house completed (and Paulina and Johan enticed back to live
    in it) than Marcellus dies.</para>

    <para>Paulina inherits all the family possessions, and takes hold of the
    reins of the public functions and duties which made the Bisdom van Vliets
    so very influential. Although excluded from public offfice because she is
    a woman, she uses Johan as an instrument of power where necessary. Not
    only does she play a major role in public and church administration, but
    she also determines the lives of countless families in the surrounding
    area, including her dependent tenants and employees. When, in 1881, Johan
    becomes seriously ill then dies, Paulina's life changes overnight as she
    loses the social place and administrative importance that were her due as
    wife of a burgemeester. As a widow, she uses her strength of character,
    social standing and wealth to re-invent herself as a major participant in
    the new era of social welfare.</para>
  </section>
</article>
